<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Stochastic Stenography</title>
<link>https://magsol.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://magsol.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Data, donuts, and detours</description>
<image>
<url>https://magsol.github.io/images/logo.png</url>
<title>Stochastic Stenography</title>
<link>https://magsol.github.io/</link>
<height>144</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.4.555</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 22:03:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Desolation</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/clover_treat.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="An adorable senior white bunny with dark shading on her ears enjoying a treat while sitting in human Mama's lap."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Content warning: discussion of mental health struggles, burglary, and profanity.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>While in a fugue this afternoon, I dug through the day’s mail and came across the latest biweekly edition of the <a href="https://www.ncronline.org/">National Catholic Reporter</a>, to which I have been a faithful subscriber for years; my wife affectionately calls it my “Jesuit rag.” I paged through it, not really paying much attention to the articles, but I stopped <a href="https://www.ncronline.org/culture/what-bluey-teaches-us-about-times-spiritual-desolation">when I hit this one</a>: “What ‘Bluey’ teaches us about times of spiritual desolation.”</p>
<p>I momentarily shook off my fuzziness and read it. It hit like a punch to the gut (no shortage of those today, for some reason). This paragraph rammed it home:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Desolation, as Ignatian spiritual director and writer Margaret Silf notes, is a spiritual state in which we turn in on ourselves, wallow in negative feelings and find ourselves cut off from community. We lose energy (Bandit spends the whole “TV Shop” episode looking for vitamins to give him an energy boost) and we lose sight of, and interest in, what’s important to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve always struggled with living in the present and it’s gotten a lot harder in the past decade. Having a kid has made it a mixed bag, though the guilt for realizing I was mentally elsewhere has dramatically increased.</p>
<p>The description for what I’ve been feeling is dead-on: <em>desolation</em>.</p>
<p>I’ve been teetering between professional realities to some extent for almost 3 years now, at times unwilling to commit to a decision, at other times physically incapable. But this year will likely prove definitive, and it’s <em>fucking terrifying</em>. I’ve identified pros and cons, benefits and pitfalls; but there’s <em>so much uncertainty</em> that it becomes this all-encompassing buzz of anxiety that doesn’t quite rise to the level of drowning out everything else, but it’s close. It’s a dull roar with a strong muting effect, exhausting to the point of being very easy to give in until the dull roar is everywhere: a “lights are on but no one’s home” feeling. In a way, committing fully and finally would probably help! And if I’m really honest, I’ve already made a decision—I made it awhile ago—I just haven’t executed on it, not yet.</p>
<p>Somehow, this professional waffling is only one dimension of the desolation that’s been buzzing in my ears.</p>
<p>Yesterday, I heard that while my mom was at home by herself recovering from foot surgery, someone broke into her home. Very fortunately, the intent didn’t seem to be violent; in fact, the person seemed like they were in the middle of a mental health crisis. In some twisted cosmic way, it was almost fortunate that my mom was home, as she is a trained social worker and trauma therapist; the police even commented on how well she’d handled herself. Meanwhile, I can’t help but think about how badly it could have gone; hearing my mom give me the blow-by-blow over the phone when I called her that evening filled me with an awful sense of violation, and a much bigger part of me than I’d like to admit would have preferred that she’d pressed charges.</p>
<p>I received that news via text message while sitting in our vet’s office, listening to the vet tech tell us about the myriad medications we would need to start giving our 9+ year-old senior bunny, Clover (shown in the header photo of this post), to help her stay comfortable as arthritis and other age-related issues takes hold. My wife and I found Clover about half a mile down our street around Memorial Day 2015 during a run together. At the time, we were barely 6 months into our new jobs and location, and we still felt very lost and lonely—finding Clover, getting her taken care of, and welcoming this sweet and sassy bun into our family was one of the few signs that we were where we were meant to be. Finding ourselves nearing the other end is crushing.</p>
<p>After getting home from the vet, I heard that UGA, through some mistake in its software or its processes (they’re always vague about things like this), overpaid me this past month and will be asking for some of the money back. This is the third time in three years that an administrative mistake has resulted in me either having to repay UGA out of my own pocket or never seeing promised money in the first place, and I am… well, I’m <em>fucking furious</em>. I have no recourse, because each of these failures happened somewhere in seventeen layers of bureaucracy, so no individual or group could ever take responsibility. Except for me, of course: since it was my budget mistakenly entered, or my grant mistakenly paid out, or my salary mistakenly given, it’s on me to make the university whole again.</p>
<p>I’m seeing COVID rates start to increase again. Raging antisemitism has a stranglehold with people I once thought were allies and friends. Polls ahead of the November election in the US paint a dire picture of the potential outcome. A longtime and deeply meaningful friendship seems to have changed sometime over the past three years and I don’t know why.</p>
<p>There’s so much noise, so much desolation; all I want to do is turn inward. I know it’s self-defeating—the indecision is paralyzing, which makes any decision completely overwhelming, perpetuating the cycle—but I don’t know how to find that radical acceptance: being completely rooted in the present, for all its faults and uncertainties.</p>
<hr>
<p>I feel an overriding desire to wrap this post up on a positive note but right now I can’t find one, and doing so would be disingenuous. It’d be giving into the desolation by painting a sunnier picture than what actually exists, and in doing so, conveying the subtle but critical message that I don’t need anyone’s help.</p>
<p>Which isn’t true at any level, but holy shit is it difficult to admit: I can’t do this on my own. Even the decision of where my professional life goes from here is not one I can make unilaterally. Maybe some people can; I’m just not one of them. Even if I didn’t have an amazing partner and equal to bounce ideas off of who can see through my every rationalization and weak-ass defense, I’d still seek out the advice of my family, friends, and mentors.</p>
<p>So if there’s any positive ending to this post, I suppose it’s this: I know what I need to do, but I absolutely need help doing it. I can’t beat back the desolation on my own. “We’re all in this together” is something I readily say to everyone—and I mean it!—but I carve out an exception for myself. I’m trying to end that, to reach out when I can tell I’m not only in over my head but am actively digging myself deeper.</p>
<p>Ok, speaking of digging a hole, I lied. <em>This</em> is the positive ending.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VM56KXM4y4c" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Desolation},
  date = {2024-06-13},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-06-13-desolation},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“Desolation.”</span> June 13, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-06-13-desolation">https://magsol.github.io/2024-06-13-desolation</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 22:03:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/clover_treat.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 23: Nearing the Finish</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We’re at day 23 of <code>#WeblogPoMo2024</code>, and this is post number 7 for me—one every three-ish days, give or take. And in today’s post, I’m here to say: I’m not sure how many more posts there will be. I’m in and out of travel for most of the remaining month, and while there will be plenty of downtime (and, assuming, WiFi access), I’m not expecting joy-writing to be high on the priority list.</p>
<p>Simply put: between jet lag, phoning home, and a really nasty bee sting I picked up that’s taking its sweet time healing—not to mention said travel—I don’t really see much time for this.</p>
<p>I could be wrong! There might be another post, or two, or even THREE (gasp). Anything is possible! But given the stress of travel, I want to temper the expectations of my most important of readers: me.</p>
<p>So in possible lieu of any further <code>#WeblogPoMo2024</code> posts, please enjoy these <em>Homeworld 3</em> screenshots that were actually taken by yours truly.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/motherships.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Two Hiigaran motherships.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/warsage.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>This was a hard mission.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/noctuua27.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The atmosphere on this one was unreal.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/noctuua-fleet.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Gonna be tough for the enemy to break this line.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 23: {Nearing} the {Finish}},
  date = {2024-05-23},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 23: Nearing the
Finish.”</span> May 23, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 18:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 16: Python Profiling Rocks</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I was digging through some code written by somebody else and trying to establish benchmarks against some new data we had just received. In doing so, I noticed the application was spending a <em>lot</em> of time at one particular stage. Upon inquiry, my coworkers said something to the effect of “oh yeah, that part always takes a long time to run.”</p>
<p>In looking through the code in question, some ideas began to form in my head, but I was missing data. So I turned to an old Python friend: <code>cProfile</code>!</p>
<p><code>cProfile</code> is a built-in package—as in, part of the default Python distribution—that performs code profiling and is dead-simple to use. Given that I was interested only in a small slice of the overall program, I did have to dig a bit to understand how to essentially “wrap” a certain part of the program in profiling, so that was new for me.</p>
<p>It basically amounted to:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> cProfile, pstats</span>
<span id="cb1-2"></span>
<span id="cb1-3">profiler <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> cProfile.Profile()</span>
<span id="cb1-4">profiler.enable()</span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">###</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># All the code you want to profile goes here!</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">###</span></span>
<span id="cb1-8">profiler.disable()</span>
<span id="cb1-9">stats <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pstats.Stats(profiler)</span>
<span id="cb1-10">stats.dump_stats(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"outputdir/outputfile.stats"</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p>That dumps out the profile information (in a binary format, sorry) to a file. From there, you can spin up something like IPython to read the binary and print out the stats:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb2-1">s <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pstats.Stats(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"outputdir/outputfile.stats"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-2">s.sort_stats(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"tottime"</span>).print_stats()</span></code></pre></div>
<p>And then you have all the runtime stats of the code enclosed by your profiler! It even helped me identify a strange <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?O(n%5E2)"> search loop; easy to miss, because it was a 1-liner, but was responsible for <em>over 50%</em> of the observed runtime! I probably would never have found it on my own.</p>
<p>For more information, <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/profile.html">check out the docs on the built-in Python profilers</a>!</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 16: {Python} {Profiling} {Rocks}},
  date = {2024-05-16},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 16: Python Profiling
Rocks.”</span> May 16, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>programming</category>
  <category>python</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 21:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 13: Return to Hiigara</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6ojRQyBqtOg"><em>Homeworld 3</em> went live</a>. I’ve actually been playing the game since Friday, May 10, when backers of its original kickstarter got early access.</p>
<p>I’ve been a fan of <em>Homeworld</em> ever since the first game came out in 1999 to little fanfare, despite garnering a much-coveted “Game of the Year” award for being among the first (or the actual first?) truly 3D real-time strategy games. Of course, that wasn’t its only credit: its beautiful and devastating story of an entire people who suddenly found themselves without a home, its haunting soundtrack (“Adagio for Strings” has always hit me differently, thanks to that game), and graphics that were remarkable for its time.</p>
<p>While I may be among the few who enjoyed the maligned expansion <em>Cataclysm</em> (2000), I very very VERY much loved its sequel, <em>Homeworld 2</em> (2003). Fast forward to the early stages of the pandemic lockdown in 2020 to the release of <em>Homeworld: Remastered</em>, which was among the best “remasters” of classic games (<em>Homeworlds</em> 1 and 2!) I have ever played. This came out around the same time as the <em>Homeworld 3</em> kickstarter announcement, which I eagerly backed.</p>
<p>Of course, at the time, the projected release date was Q4 2022. El oh el. Still, it’s clear from both official reviews and my own experience playing the finished game that the developers used the extra time to really lock down the polish.</p>
<p>As with every previous <em>Homeworld</em> game, it’s gorgeous. Jaw-droppingly beautiful. The soundtrack is, yet again, haunting, complete with modern “Adagio” renditions you can hear if you listen closely. And the story is gripping, always somehow managing to harness the vastness of space and imbue it with malign intent, and the only people you can rely on are your comrades-in-mothership.</p>
<p>I won’t spoil anything, but I will post a few screenshots. These aren’t mine—I took a few from a screenshots channel in the <em>Homeworld</em> Discord—as I haven’t finished the game and know for a fact that some depict missions I have not yet encountered.</p>
<p>It’s a wonderful game. Highly recommend.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/battle.PNG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Devs made good on promises to include actual megaliths.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/crash.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>It’s beautiful. Also, this mission is brutal.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/harvest.PNG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Resource collectors harvesting materials inside a giant megalith.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/ice.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>I have not reached this mission yet, but WOW does it look beautiful.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And what gaming session would be complete without a little <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/sidon.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sidon, my best friend.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 13: {Return} to {Hiigara}},
  date = {2024-05-13},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 13: Return to
Hiigara.”</span> May 13, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>gaming</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 21:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 10: Homelab extravaganza</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>For today’s <code>#WeblogPomo2024</code>, I wanted to delve a little more into my current Homelab setup, which I’ve only alluded to previously. The <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/">series of blog posts I wrote over a year ago detailing my journey setting up a home Mastodon instance</a> was kind of the spark that started this whole homelab kick. I’ve since retrofitted an old desktop (after <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/">replacing it</a>) as an Unraid server, and have a whole collection of applications already humming along.</p>
<p>My latest efforts have involved getting self-hosted <a href="https://nextcloud.com/">Nextcloud</a>] up and running… which is highly non-trivial. I’ve wanted off Dropbox for quite awhile now (I don’t use anywhere <em>near</em> the 2TB allocated in the base paid plan, but I definitely use a lot more than the 2GB allowed in the free tier… oh yeah and numerous privacy issues), but getting Nextcloud running has been a whole thing unto itself. It highlighted an entire hierarchy of reconfigurations and upgrades I needed to undertake across the broader homelab to make Nextcloud possible.</p>
<p>It’s also brought to the forefront the biggest philosophical question I’ve had: <strong>do I allow external access to Nextcloud, or restrict it to local requests only?</strong> Nextcloud is arguably designed for the former, but allows for the latter <em>with some non-standard configuration changes</em>. Obviously I’d like to keep external access to any homelab resources to an absolute minimum—if Mastodon is the only thing that’s externally accessible, I’m fine with that. But a filesharing service with an entire ecosystem of applications is not exactly meant to be confined to a small home network. Hence, my waffling.</p>
<p>For now, I’m going down the path of: keep it internal, but look at ways of allowing selective external access, along the lines of the Tailscales and Twingates of the world, both of which are compatible with Unraid. We’ll see.</p>
<p>Stay tuned!</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 10: {Homelab} Extravaganza},
  date = {2024-05-10},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 10: Homelab
Extravaganza.”</span> May 10, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>homelab</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 16:32:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 7: The importance of personal projects</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I don’t think I’m alone in having a menagerie of personal projects. The constituents of said menagerie morph (some slowly, some quickly) as time passes, but it’s never empty. It hasn’t been empty since… high school? Earlier?</p>
<p>Yes, it’s sometimes disheartening to see how little progress I make on so many different fronts. Though, by simply writing out that sentence, I get just an inkling of how ridiculous it sounds.</p>
<p>But these projects, simply, keep me sane. I love creating things; I love building things; I love trying something out in the real world that is often outside the narrow purview of what my immediate employer is looking for. I like trying things for things’ sakes, though sometimes there is also a practical reason.</p>
<p>Lately I’ve been trying to get a new outdoor wildlife camera setup working. It’s a bit more technically complicated than <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/index.html">the one I posted about last year</a> so it’s taking me a bit longer to get things working. But I’m really enjoying doing it.</p>
<p>Personal projects are, after all, <a href="https://angelostavrow.blog/a-love-letter-to-personal-projects">all about delight</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Like most things, I think when it comes to <code>#WeblogPomo2024</code>, it’ll be a cadence of “when I can” as opposed to “EVERY F#$&amp;ING DAY OR DIAF”. After all, <a href="https://www.tumblr.com/rsingwriting/187070321479/i-saw-a-post-talking-about-how-terry-pratchett">if I’m writing a nontrivial fraction of the number of words Sir Terry Pratchett wrote on a daily basis during his illustrious career</a>, I’d say I’m doing pretty well.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 7: {The} Importance of Personal
    Projects},
  date = {2024-05-07},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 7: The Importance of
Personal Projects.”</span> May 7, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 16:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 3: mutter</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today, as I was getting back up to speed on work (just in time for the weekend, lol) following travel in the first half of the week, I noticed…something.</p>
<p>Occasionally, my command line would—for lack of a better term—“hitch”.</p>
<p>It became more noticeable as I would type faster; eventually I took to typing gibberish, and it became clear that there definitely was a hitch.</p>
<p>A few minutes of searching (read: tweaking the search parameters, and filtering out “AI”-generated fluff), I found exactly what I was looking for: what is apparently <a href="https://askubuntu.com/a/1509474">a known issue with Ubuntu 22.04.4</a>. The fix, aside from upgrading wholesale to 24.04 (not quite ready yet), was a new <code>mutter</code> install.</p>
<p>I installed it and rebooted, and the hitch is gone. Thank you, internet!</p>
<hr>
<p>Yeah, I missed <code>#WeblogPoMo2024</code> yesterday, so I’m already behind. I’ll continue to do the best I can!</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 3: Mutter},
  date = {2024-05-03},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 3: Mutter.”</span> May
3, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>open source</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 20:24:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024: BEGIN!</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-01-weblogpomo2024-begin/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-01-weblogpomo2024-begin/welcome_shannon.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A flatscreen TV showing the words 'Welcome, Shannon' with a flowery background."></p>
<p>It’s been two months (to the day!) since I last posted here. Not a <em>long</em> stretch, relatively speaking, but a respectable one. It’s been a busy couple of months to be sure, but if I’m honest I just haven’t been making time to write anything down. Not for lack of things to write—I feel like I’m always composing blog posts in my head—but working+parenting+running+sleeping typically seems to be a potent enough combination to push out all but the highest priority items that don’t fall in any of those buckets.</p>
<p>Enter <code>#WeblogPoMo2024</code>, something I’d never heard of before seeing <a href="https://social.lol/@hl/112366042124108733">Henry post about it on Mastodon</a>.</p>
<p>Seems challenging while also reasonable: no 2000+ daily word count goal, no minimum running mileage to hit. Just a blog post. I may not finish it (I’d really like to finish an Advent of Code one of these years), but it’d be a nice goal to shoot for. I know from the multitude of early faculty writing workshops I’ve attended that, at least for me, the single most consistent motivator to write is to <strong>write with other people</strong>. The group accountability just <em>works</em> for me. So maybe it’ll work here, too!</p>
<p>Join me, won’t you? Or just bug me until I hit “post”.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024: {BEGIN!}},
  date = {2024-05-01},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-01-weblogpomo2024-begin},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024: BEGIN!”</span> May 1,
2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-01-weblogpomo2024-begin">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-01-weblogpomo2024-begin</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-01-weblogpomo2024-begin/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 20:24:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-01-weblogpomo2024-begin/welcome_shannon.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Burnout Marathon</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon/clouds.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Landscape photo of stringy cirrus clouds near sunset."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>This post contains references to recent events at the University of Georgia involving the deaths of two undergraduate students.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>February was a bruiser of a month: somehow both the shortest of the year by any objective measure, and also the most intense of the past year at least.</p>
<p>For several days this past week I’ve felt that “hollow muscle” sensation that goes beyond mere fatigue. It’s that feeling where you’ve been hopped up on cortisol for days (or longer) at a time and then you finally, blessedly, are able to relax; it feels a lot like a multi-day hangover or even withdrawal. My hands shake, my legs feel wobbly, and on a whole I feel as though I could take a nap at any time.</p>
<p>I’m sure it’s happened to me in the intervening years, but the last time I vividly remember it was right at the start of 2014, as I was entering the final year of my PhD, and I had just started on fluoxetine. It helped me to finally start to sleep through the night on multiple consecutive nights, but I was waking each morning with this same feeling: heavy and tired, sure, but also all my muscles shook, as though coming down from a high. It lasted for at least a week but went away as my sleep and exercise routines evened out.</p>
<p>This past week was one of the worst in recent memory. Somehow, the tragedies of two UGA students dying—one of them <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/02/23/1233354257/university-of-georgia-death-student">murdered on trails we’ve run millions of times</a>, the other (<a href="https://www.ajc.com/news/crime/uga-student-wyatt-banks-remembered-as-a-friend-to-all-who-loved-to-travel-cook/FUHEEYMEVRA53PSTCXJRGNUUUU/">who died by suicide</a>) a graduate of my high school—were only a part of what made the past week so difficult.</p>
<p>For all the progress I’ve made in learning to cope with and even reverse burnout, I still have no idea how to handle acute situations, especially when it’s multiple in just a few days’ time and the feeling of being hit from all directions is overwhelming. My therapist assured me that, since I didn’t physically or emotionally hurt anyone else or even myself in the immediate aftermath, that alone puts me way ahead of the curve. That helps to hear, but it really doesn’t <em>feel</em> like it.</p>
<p>I’ve had a love-hate relationship with my Garmin Fenix watch ever since purchasing it back in 2015. It has a feature that estimates your current fitness “state”, including categories like “Productive”, “Maintaining”, “Peaking”, or “Recovery.” It measures all of this mostly using heart rate data, which by itself is suspect from a watch; as good as watch-based optical heart rate monitors have gotten, they’re still a “good estimate” at best by comparison to chest straps or pulse monitors at doctor’s offices.</p>
<p>But for the past <em>10 days</em> it’s had me in “Maintaining” or even “Unproductive” for the longest period I can remember, despite making an active push to increase my weekly running mileage. And the reasoning Garmin provided for the classification was pretty damning: it said my activity level was good, but that my fitness was nonetheless still decreasing, a sign that I needed <strong>more recovery time</strong>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon/unproductive.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A screenshot of Garmin's 4-week fitness state summary, which shows the Feb 19-29 period as in either a Maintaining or an Unproductive state, relative to the other 2.5 weeks before it that show mixtures of Productive and Maintaining."></p>
<figcaption>When even Garmin is consistently telling you to calm your shit, maybe it’s time to chill.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I took Monday off from work. I am so, so grateful to have that flexibility to take time when I need it, but wow I needed it. I don’t really remember specifics from the weekend until about Monday evening; that’s how brain-dead I was.</p>
<p>I don’t have any pearls of wisdom for getting through acutely stressful situations; I wish I did. An outlet for both the physical and the emotional/mental energy certainly helps (obviously, outlets that do NOT involve hurting other people). In my case:</p>
<ul>
<li>A pretty intense 30-minute throwing session in my backyard with my pitchback at about 8:30pm. The fact that I escaped without taking a single baseball to the face while the half of the yard I was standing in was in pitch darkness is one minor miracle. That my shoulder wasn’t sore the next day is another.</li>
<li>My wife and I ran together <em>twice</em> this week for the first time since Z was born over three years ago.</li>
<li>I’ve thrown myself into my work this week: I had several very productive work sessions with my colleagues at PredxBio as we continue to build out some new spatial biology models; I wrote some draft SciPy abstracts (we might submit <em>three</em>!); and I approached a potential contractor for one of my grants.</li>
<li>I managed to create a self-sufficient home media server, allowing me to cancel our AppleTV+ subscription a mere 24 hours before it was set to renew for its increased price.</li>
<li>After ignoring the “Focus” mode feature on iOS basically since it appeared, I spent 15 minutes <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/@magsol/111983809170453826">creating a new mode</a> that all but completely disables my phone every night at 8pm. It’s been nothing short of wonderful.</li>
</ul>
<p>So I guess, at least for me: intense physical labor with focused mental applications (winging a baseball and then being forced to field a return; or a high-intensity work schedule that draws on my experience) seems to be my ideal way of coming down from peak activation. I’ve reached out to some friends who have also provided some important feedback—feedback which was obvious in retrospect, but which I was too activated in the moment for it to even occur to me (my therapist had some fascinating insights here about human psychology and our tendency to cling to rules or procedures that make no sense in the moment, but we cling to them anyway because we just want one thing to work the way we expect it to). That back-and-forth with trusted friends also helped to clarify and crystallize my thoughts.</p>
<p>Basically, no quick fix. Certainly no “anti-trigger” on the same intensity and timescale but opposite directionality. Maybe people who can do that exist; I’m certainly not one. But I did learn the hours of the nearby indoor batting cage, and my birthday is coming up, so hopefully I’ll be able to report on that soon. That’s something positive to come out of all this. Small; very small. But positive.</p>
<p>May the memories of the two students be a blessing.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Burnout {Marathon}},
  date = {2024-03-01},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“Burnout Marathon.”</span> March 1, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon">https://magsol.github.io/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>burnout</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2024 16:12:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-03-01-burnout-marathon/clouds.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Legend of Makar</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><a href="makar.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-1"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/makar.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A picture of the Ubuntu landing screen for logged in users, on an ultrawide screen monitor set on a small desk."></a></p>
<p>I built my first desktop from components when I was 15, a sophomore in high school. With the exception of my college workstation (laptops hadnt’t <em>quite</em> reached ubiquity yet), I’ve assembled every desktop I have ever owned since then.</p>
<p>It’s a skill and a pasttime I deeply enjoy, but one which I don’t have the opportunity to explore very often. Even though “every desktop since age 15” sounds impressive, in real numbers it amounts to just a handful:</p>
<ul>
<li>age 15: my family’s home computer</li>
<li>age 19: a server for my dorm room</li>
<li>age 22: my graduate desktop</li>
<li>age 25: the lab’s new workstation during a rotation (not mine, per se)</li>
<li>age 29: my “first real job” home desktop</li>
<li>now: the one in this blog post!</li>
</ul>
<p>There were certainly upgrades throughout that timeline—I swapped hard drives and memory in and out of that dorm server many times; my first “real job” desktop saw at least one GPU upgrade; my graduate desktop was a true exercise in frustration as I spent the first <em>two years</em> diagnosing an <a href="https://magsol.wordpress.com/2010/06/28/one-final-technical-appeal/">intermittent and nigh-irreproducible freezing</a>—but it’s actually rare I get brag to folks that I’m “assembling my new computer from parts.”</p>
<p>So I figured: for this round, I’d go all out with full documentation in the form of a blog post 😁</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Long post ahead
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Let the record show: the reader was warned of the length of the post that follows.</p>
</div>
</div>
<section id="hardware" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hardware">Hardware</h3>
<p>The first step in any desktop build: the hardware! I’ve been scoping out the major components off and on for over a year now, using resources like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@GamersNexus">GamersNexus reviews</a> and <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/">Tom’s Hardware</a> to get a feel for what CPUs / motherboards I should look into.</p>
<p>As an example: I’d spent 11 of the past 12 months with the latest Intel processor locked in, but changed my mind at the [relative] last second when all the head-to-head CPU benchmarks showed the latest AMD Ryzen 9 processors going toe-to-toe with Intel on multithreaded applications (i.e., my work’s bread and butter). That, coupled with AMD’s <em>shocking</em> advantage in power draw and smaller advantage on price made it an immediate no-brainer to switch.</p>
<p>For the curious, here’s the full list of hardware I ended up going with:</p>
<ul>
<li>CPU: <a href="https://www.newegg.com/amd-ryzen-9-7950x-ryzen-9-7000-series/p/N82E16819113771?Item=N82E16819113771">AMD Ryzen 9 7950X</a></li>
<li>Cooler: <a href="https://www.newegg.com/deepcool-ak400-zero-dark-plus/p/N82E16835856230?Item=N82E16835856230">DeepCool AK400 Zero Dark Plus 120mm</a></li>
<li>Motherboard: <a href="https://www.newegg.com/msi-mag-x670e-tomahawk-wifi/p/N82E16813144595?Item=N82E16813144595">MSI MAG X670E Tomahawk AM5 ATX</a></li>
<li>Memory: <a href="https://www.newegg.com/g-skill-96gb/p/N82E16820374465?Item=N82E16820374465">G.SKILL Trident Z5 48GB 288-pin PC RAM DDR5 6800 PC5 54400</a> (4x)</li>
<li>GPU: <a href="https://www.bestbuy.com/site/gigabyte-nvidia-geforce-rtx-4090-gaming-oc-24gb-gddr6x-pci-express-4-0-graphics-card-black/6521518.p">NVIDIA RTX 4090</a></li>
<li>PSU: <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0B433ZCRP?psc=1&amp;ref=ppx_yo2ov_dt_b_product_details">MEG Ai1300P PCIE 5 1300W</a></li>
<li>Storage: <a href="https://www.newegg.com/samsung-4gb-990-pro/p/N82E16820147878?Item=N82E16820147878">Samsung SSD 990 PRO 2TB M.2 2280</a> (2x)</li>
<li>Case: <a href="https://www.newegg.com/black-fractal-design-torrent-atx-mid-tower/p/N82E16811352143?Item=N82E16811352143">Fractal Design Torrent Black E-ATX Mid Tower</a></li>
<li>Monitor: <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B088HH6LW5/ref=ppx_yo_dt_b_asin_title_o05_s00?ie=UTF8&amp;psc=1">Samsung 49-inch Odyssey G9</a></li>
</ul>
<p>To address the elephant in the room: no, this build was not cheap, at <em>all</em>. This is all top-of-the-line hardware, meant to 1) last a very long time, and 2) facilitate my kind of intensive number-crunching machine learning work. But I also put it together after having secured an agreement that my sabbatical employer<sup>1</sup> would kick in a small amount, too.</p>
<p>There are all kinds of additional considerations I went through—you’re probably asking, why only M.2 drives? believe me, that was a whole thing, but oddly kinda boiled down to “supply chain problems, lol”—so I’m happy to get into it offline.</p>
<p>But for now, let’s jump into assembly!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="clear_desk.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-2" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-2" title="My workspace for assembly. Thanks, Gamers Nexus!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/clear_desk.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A clear desk space with a Gamers Nexus antistatic mat."></a></p>
<figcaption>My workspace for assembly. Thanks, Gamers Nexus!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="unboxing-and-assembly" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="unboxing-and-assembly">Unboxing and Assembly</h3>
<p>Once I had all the components (this was also a Whole Thing<sup>TM</sup>), it took me about 3 days to put everything together. That’s actually a record—the longest it had taken me to assemble a desktop had previous been <em>3 hours</em>. I don’t really know what to chalk that discrepancy up to. Maybe rustiness (it’s been almost a decade since my last full build)? Reverence (I love doing this so much, I want to soak it up)? Nerves (first time building an AMD machine since the dorm room server)?</p>
<p>General fatigue?<sup>2</sup></p>
<p>Anyway.</p>
<p>I started with the case. It came highly recommended through Gamers Nexus, especially for custom cooling. I’ve always dreamed of a fully water-cooled rig, but as the time to finalize the build crept closer, I decided to stick with a traditional air-cooled setup. This case was great in that it lets me do either but defaults to an excellent air-cooled configuration.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[1, 1], [1, 1]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="case/box_case.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="case" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-3" title="Unboxing the case."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/case/box_case.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Unboxing the case."></a></p>
<figcaption>Unboxing the case.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="case/case1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="case" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-4" title="I love the plexiglass covers: easy to remove, but also great for seeing inside."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/case/case1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="I love the plexiglass covers: easy to remove, but also great for seeing inside."></a></p>
<figcaption>I love the plexiglass covers: easy to remove, but also great for seeing inside.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="case/case2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="case" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-5" title="Lots of airflow vents."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/case/case2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lots of airflow vents."></a></p>
<figcaption>Lots of airflow vents.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="case/case3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="case" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-6" title="Lots and lots of fans."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/case/case3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Lots and lots of fans."></a></p>
<figcaption>Lots and lots of fans.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Next were all the internal components. Since the case is really just a vehicle for the motherboard, which is really just a vehicle for <em>everything else</em>, I wanted to work my way from the inside out. Especially given the downright titanic proportions of the 4090, I wanted to assemble the motherboard as much as possible before slotting it into the case and losing a lot of physical wiggle room and visibility.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[100], [50, 50]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="before_the_storm.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="unboxing" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-7" title="All the internal components, unboxed from shipping but still in their retail boxes."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/before_the_storm.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="All the internal components, unboxed from shipping but still in their retail boxes."></a></p>
<figcaption>All the internal components, unboxed from shipping but still in their retail boxes.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="boxes.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="unboxing" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-8" title="Everything arrived! Well, everything else arrived."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/boxes.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Everything arrived! Well, everything else arrived."></a></p>
<figcaption>Everything arrived! Well, everything <em>else</em> arrived.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="boxes_internal_components.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="unboxing" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-9" title="Just the internal components that go on the motherboard… minus the GPU."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/boxes_internal_components.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Just the internal components that go on the motherboard… minus the GPU."></a></p>
<figcaption>Just the internal components that go on the motherboard… minus the GPU.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The CPU and associated cooler were first. These were, thankfully, pretty straightforward. The only difference here from my prior experience with Intel was that AMD doesn’t seem to ship its CPUs with stock coolers; hence, I needed to get a custom one. Otherwise, everything slotted in exactly as I remembered.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[100], [100], [50, 50], [50, 50], [50, 50]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/motherboard_unpack.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-10" title="The motherboard is inside that antistatic wrap on the right. Zapping that with a small static discharge would be, ah, rather unfortunate!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/motherboard_unpack.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The motherboard is inside that antistatic wrap on the right. Zapping that with a small static discharge would be, ah, rather unfortunate!"></a></p>
<figcaption>The motherboard is inside that antistatic wrap on the right. Zapping that with a small static discharge would be, ah, rather unfortunate!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/motherboard.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-11" title="The motherboard, in all its glory."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/motherboard.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The motherboard, in all its glory."></a></p>
<figcaption>The motherboard, in all its glory.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/cpu_unbox.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-12" title="The “brain” of the computer. I guess."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/cpu_unbox.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The “brain” of the computer. I guess."></a></p>
<figcaption>The “brain” of the computer. I guess.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/cpu_box.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-13" title="The CPU box is actually quite large, but that’s because 90% of it is this “pedestal foam.” I know it’s to keep things from getting jostled, but it just looks like a throne."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/cpu_box.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The CPU box is actually quite large, but that’s because 90% of it is this “pedestal foam.” I know it’s to keep things from getting jostled, but it just looks like a throne."></a></p>
<figcaption>The CPU box is actually quite large, but that’s because 90% of it is this “pedestal foam.” I know it’s to keep things from getting jostled, but it just looks like a throne.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/motherboard_cpu_slot.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-14" title="The slot on the motherboard where the CPU goes, with a plastic safety cover on it. You do NOT want to damage the pins underneath it!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/motherboard_cpu_slot.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The slot on the motherboard where the CPU goes, with a plastic safety cover on it. You do NOT want to damage the pins underneath it!"></a></p>
<figcaption>The slot on the motherboard where the CPU goes, with a plastic safety cover on it. You do NOT want to damage the pins underneath it!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/motherboard_cpu_install.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-15" title="After removing the plastic cover and quadruple-checking the CPU alignment, it fit perfectly!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/motherboard_cpu_install.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="After removing the plastic cover and quadruple-checking the CPU alignment, it fit perfectly!"></a></p>
<figcaption>After removing the plastic cover and quadruple-checking the CPU alignment, it fit perfectly!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/cpu_cooler.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-16" title="The custom cooler I bought. Just slots right on top of the CPU."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/cpu_cooler.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The custom cooler I bought. Just slots right on top of the CPU."></a></p>
<figcaption>The custom cooler I bought. Just slots right on top of the CPU.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="cpu/cpu_cooler_installed.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="cpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-17" title="Everything fit! Yay!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/cpu/cpu_cooler_installed.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Everything fit! Yay!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Everything fit! Yay!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Next up: memory (or RAM). I was originally going with just a single 2-pack of 48GB DIMMs for a total of 96GB, but my sabbatical employer insisted I max out the memory so I can work with 100+GB single images they have from clients.</p>
<p>That entailed a bit more research on my part on AMD-compatible motherboards to learn what their RAM limits were. I found one with 192GB as its upper limit: hence that motherboard, and hence why I have so much RAM!</p>
<p>I think I enjoy installing RAM the most: there are no moving parts, other than the clips on the motherboard itself that very helpfully “click” when you have properly seated the memory. It’s very satisfying.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[100], [50, 50]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ram/motherboard_memory.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="ram" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-18" title="The four RAM chips in the plastic on the right go in the four motherboard slots in front of the CPU on the left."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/ram/motherboard_memory.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The four RAM chips in the plastic on the right go in the four motherboard slots in front of the CPU on the left."></a></p>
<figcaption>The four RAM chips in the plastic on the right go in the four motherboard slots in front of the CPU on the left.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ram/motherboard_dimms.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="ram" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-19" title="If you ever have fewer DIMMs than motherboard slots, look for a schematic like this that tells you which slots you should install RAM in first."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/ram/motherboard_dimms.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="If you ever have fewer DIMMs than motherboard slots, look for a schematic like this that tells you which slots you should install RAM in first."></a></p>
<figcaption>If you ever have fewer DIMMs than motherboard slots, look for a schematic like this that tells you which slots you should install RAM in first.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ram/motherboard_memory_installed.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="ram" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-20" title="Everything fit! Yay!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/ram/motherboard_memory_installed.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Everything fit! Yay!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Everything fit! Yay!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>At this point, I <em>should have</em> installed the storage devices. But for reasons lost to the passage of time, I didn’t. Instead, I installed the motherboard into the case.</p>
<p>Part of my rationale, I think, was that I knew I couldn’t install the GPU until the motherboard was seated in the case; the GPU was just too big to be installed without the support of the case itself. I also knew some of the M.2 slots were <em>under</em> the GPU; this created some uncertainty about whether the GPU would actually sit correctly if an M.2 device was installed directly under it. My priority here was the GPU—it was so large, it could only fit in one of two slots, and of those two only one was honestly preferable—and to seat the GPU, I needed to install the motherboard into the case.</p>
<p>All in all, motherboard installation is pretty easy: just put the motherboard in the case and carefully screw it down. If the screw holes in the motherboard don’t align with the struts in the case, then something has gone horribly wrong and you should stop.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[1, 1]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mobo/motherboard_installed1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="mobo" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-21" title="Everything fit! Yay!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/mobo/motherboard_installed1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Everything fit! Yay!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Everything fit! Yay!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="mobo/motherboard_installed2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="mobo" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-22" title="Everything still fits! Yay!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/mobo/motherboard_installed2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Everything still fits! Yay!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Everything still fits! Yay!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>For one final diversion before the monstrosity that is the GPU, I installed the PSU, aka the power supply. Given that wholly <em>half</em> the power supply’s capacity is going to the GPU, I knew I needed something relatively beefy, hence the 1300W monster PSU. But I also knew I wouldn’t have very many other components that needed direct power.</p>
<p>So a <em>modular</em> PSU was key: one with lots of outlets for potential devices, but whose cords could be disconnected and removed when not needed so as not to clog up the inside of the case with unplugged power cables.</p>
<p>Another reason I love this case is because, at a time when most cases now put the PSU somewhere in the bottom, this case puts the PSU at the <em>top</em>, and even “slightly outside” the case itself! There’s a panel that pops off where the PSU sits, and the cables are then snaked through an opening to the rest of the case for added compartmentalization. It’s quite nice.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[50, 50], [33, 33, 33]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="psu/psu.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="psu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-23" title="That’s the PSU."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/psu/psu.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="That’s the PSU."></a></p>
<figcaption>That’s the PSU.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="psu/case_slot_for_psu.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="psu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-24" title="Once you pop the top cover off the case, you can see the divot where the PSU fits."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/psu/case_slot_for_psu.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Once you pop the top cover off the case, you can see the divot where the PSU fits."></a></p>
<figcaption>Once you pop the top cover off the case, you can see the divot where the PSU fits.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="psu/case_with_psu.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="psu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-25" title="Fits like a glove!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/psu/case_with_psu.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Fits like a glove!"></a></p>
<figcaption>Fits like a glove!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="psu/psu_cables1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="psu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-26" title="Literal bags’ worth of cables, depending on my hardware."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/psu/psu_cables1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Literal bags’ worth of cables, depending on my hardware."></a></p>
<figcaption>Literal bags’ worth of cables, depending on my hardware.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="psu/psu_cables2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="psu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-27" title="Here are cables that will provide core power to the motherboard."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/psu/psu_cables2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Here are cables that will provide core power to the motherboard."></a></p>
<figcaption>Here are cables that will provide core power to the motherboard.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Alright. Couldn’t ignore the <a href="https://www.artstation.com/artwork/m85BXZ">Demon King in the Depths</a> any longer. Time to install the GPU.</p>
<p>I knew this thing would be huge going in, but I was still shocked, and I say this as a still-owner of a venerable 1080 Ti. This thing spans the volume of nearly 3x 1080s. It’s absolutely insane. And yet, still <em>technically</em> only takes the space of 2 PCI devices.</p>
<p>Suffice to say, I made absolutely certain before purchasing that all the measurements fit what I had to work with. For a component that was almost half the entire monetary AND eletrical budgets of this build, this was the one I wanted to get right the first time.</p>
<p>Actual installation was a snap, as it has been ever since the advent of separate GPUs. But it seriously felt like plugging an Apollo command module into a 120V home garage outlet.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[100], [33, 33, 33], [33, 33, 33]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gpu/gpu_box_case.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-28" title="Here we go."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/gpu/gpu_box_case.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Here we go."></a></p>
<figcaption>Here we go.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gpu/gpu_unboxed1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-29" title="Unboxing the beast."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/gpu/gpu_unboxed1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Unboxing the beast."></a></p>
<figcaption>Unboxing the beast.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gpu/gpu_unboxed2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-30" title="I could barely hold this with one hand."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/gpu/gpu_unboxed2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="I could barely hold this with one hand."></a></p>
<figcaption>I could barely hold this with one hand.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gpu/gpu_unboxed3.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-31" title="My already-oversized DumbRunner coffee mug for scale."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/gpu/gpu_unboxed3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My already-oversized DumbRunner coffee mug for scale."></a></p>
<figcaption>My already-oversized <a href="https://dumbrunner.threadless.com/designs/1-dad-in-age-group/accessories/mug/standard">DumbRunner coffee mug</a> for scale.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gpu/gpu_installed.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-32" title="In the immortal words of my dad’s dad: “It FITS. JUST. FINE.”"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/gpu/gpu_installed.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="In the immortal words of my dad’s dad: “It FITS. JUST. FINE.”"></a></p>
<figcaption>In the immortal words of my dad’s dad: “It FITS. JUST. FINE.”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gpu/gpu_old_psu_cables.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-33" title="If you have an older-style PSU, you’ll need no fewer than FOUR ATX CABLES to power this monster (technically three, but four is recommended)."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/gpu/gpu_old_psu_cables.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="If you have an older-style PSU, you’ll need no fewer than FOUR ATX CABLES to power this monster (technically three, but four is recommended)."></a></p>
<figcaption>If you have an older-style PSU, you’ll need no fewer than FOUR ATX CABLES to power this monster (technically three, but four is recommended).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="gpu/gpu_new_psu_cables.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="gpu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-34" title="If instead you have a newer PSU, you’ll have access to a single cable that supplies variable wattage, averaging 600W."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/gpu/gpu_new_psu_cables.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="If instead you have a newer PSU, you’ll have access to a single cable that supplies variable wattage, averaging 600W."></a></p>
<figcaption>If instead you have a newer PSU, you’ll have access to a single cable that supplies variable wattage, averaging 600W.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Whew.</p>
<p>The penultimate hardware step was the two M.2 SSDs. These are the latest in long-term flash storage (NVMe drives) that plug <em>directly</em> into the motherboard for absolutely insane transfer speeds. They’re ideal for—you guessed it—data-intensive computing.</p>
<p>But their positioning wasn’t ideal: two of the motherboard’s four slots were directly under the GPU, and I wasn’t certain the GPU would fit properly if I installed an M.2 under it.</p>
<p>The short version is: the GPU actually fit just fine, but the M.2s themselves didn’t play nice with the arrangement of the motherboard’s southbridge. Fortunately I found a configuration that worked, but this part took a ton of swearing and <em>over an hour</em> of trial-and-error before I finally got everything seated.</p>
<p>The next hard drive will be a standard 2.5” SSD, mmk thx bai.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[1, 1, 1]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="nvme/nvme_boxes.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="nvme" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-35" title="Storage unboxing."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/nvme/nvme_boxes.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Storage unboxing."></a></p>
<figcaption>Storage unboxing.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="nvme/nvme_unboxed1.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="nvme" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-36" title="These things are TEENY."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/nvme/nvme_unboxed1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="These things are TEENY."></a></p>
<figcaption>These things are TEENY.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="nvme/nvme_installed2.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="nvme" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-37" title="Slotted into two motherboard slots (GPU not shown)."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/nvme/nvme_installed2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Slotted into two motherboard slots (GPU not shown)."></a></p>
<figcaption>Slotted into two motherboard slots (GPU not shown).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The last bit of the hardware was to wire everything up! In particular: the motherboard, CPU cooler, case fans, and GPU all needed to be connected directly to the PSU for power.</p>
<p>This is always, in my opinion, the most tedious part of any build. Snaking wires throughout the inside of the case always results in snarls and makes any future work (fixing problems, upgrading hardware) tricky at best. Many cases in the last decade have “cable management” pathways built-in to help with this, but it still comes down to the human to make it happen. And it’s annoying at best.</p>
<p>In this case, I did… ok. Well enough.</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[1, 1]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="wires/internal_wiring.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="wiring" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-38" title="These pathways are along the “bottom” of the motherboard, so most of the wiring can be kept hidden and out of the way of the main components."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/wires/internal_wiring.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="These pathways are along the “bottom” of the motherboard, so most of the wiring can be kept hidden and out of the way of the main components."></a></p>
<figcaption>These pathways are along the “bottom” of the motherboard, so most of the wiring can be kept hidden and out of the way of the main components.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="wires/internal_installed.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="wiring" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-39" title="Everything (except the GPU) is plugged into the PSU."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/wires/internal_installed.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Everything (except the GPU) is plugged into the PSU."></a></p>
<figcaption>Everything (except the GPU) is plugged into the PSU.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Ok! Everything is installed! What happens next?!</p>
</section>
<section id="boot-up-and-software" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="boot-up-and-software">Boot-up and Software</h3>
<p>We’ve got our build! And she’s gorgeous 😍</p>
<p>Now, the moment of truth: booting up and installing an operating system. Or, in this case, two: I wanted to install Ubuntu (22.04 at time of post) on one of the M.2s, and Windows (11) on the other.</p>
<p>I started with Ubuntu.</p>
<p>I don’t know about other linux distributions—I’ve been on the Ubuntu train ever since Red Hat went corporate, and frankly haven’t had a reason to look back or sideways—but Ubuntu has always been relatively straightforward when it comes to install:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Create a boot disk (usually a USB disk).</li>
<li>Boot off the disk</li>
<li>Profit!</li>
</ol>
<p>Step 2 is always the tricky part, especially on a new build: I never know which function key brings up the boot order 🥴 (spoiler alert: it’s F11)</p>
<p>Once I hit the right sequence of keys, the rest of the process was pretty much point and click. Boom! I had Ubuntu installed!</p>
<div>

</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout="[[50, 50], [100]]">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ubuntu/turn_on.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="ubuntu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-40" title="The first power-up! So much suspense!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/ubuntu/turn_on.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The first power-up! So much suspense!"></a></p>
<figcaption>The first power-up! So much suspense!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ubuntu/turned_on.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="ubuntu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-41" title="SHE LIVES. You can tell by the lights."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/ubuntu/turned_on.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="SHE LIVES. You can tell by the lights."></a></p>
<figcaption>SHE LIVES. You can tell by the lights.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 100.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="ubuntu/ubuntu_install.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="ubuntu" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-42" title="The Ubuntu installer screen! Things are working!"><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/ubuntu/ubuntu_install.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The Ubuntu installer screen! Things are working!"></a></p>
<figcaption>The Ubuntu installer screen! Things are working!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Next up: Windows.</p>
<p>Getting Windows 11 installed, relative to Ubuntu, was a <em>giant pain</em>. In the intervening years, Mircrosoft seems to have gone the route of “install now, license later”—which, honestly, I appreciate—and has provided multiple pathways for creating an installer.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, only one of those pathways seems to <em>actually work</em>. I initially went the ISO route, since that’s pretty much equivalent to how I installed Ubuntu.</p>
<p>But that didn’t work. And, weirdly, the internet doesn’t seem to know why. The best hint I found came from <a href="https://answers.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/forum/all/no-device-drivers-were-found-tried-everything-w11/a53aa16b-5d4c-4f8a-abc6-e5106152a220">this forum post</a>, which seems to suggest that AMD-specific drivers <em>aren’t included</em> in the ISO installer, thereby making install via ISO on an AMD system… well, impossible.</p>
<p>There were no details on this “include AMD drivers during the install” procedure, and by this point I’d run out of patience (I’d tried multiple sub-pathways, even and including installing Windows <em>10</em> instead; all the same result).</p>
<p>So I went with the one procedure the internet seemed to agree would always work: “get a friend with a Windows PC and run the media installer that only works on Windows.” Yes this is an actual piece of advice on an actual Microsoft forum. Since the media installer option <em>only</em> runs on Windows, you’re in this weird Twilight Zone of needing a Windows computer in order to install Windows on a computer.</p>
<p>Mmk.</p>
<p>This worked, finally. Of course, that was just the warm-up; the install process itself is “<a href="https://exple.tive.org/blarg/2023/12/07/polished-glass/">a disaster from stem to stern</a>.” Thankfully, following that guide helped to minimize the worst of the creeping Windows enshittification. A few important points:</p>
<ul>
<li>Definitely <a href="https://answers.microsoft.com/en-us/insider/forum/all/set-up-windows-11-without-internet-oobebypassnro/4fc44554-b416-4ecb-8961-6f79fd55ae0f">create a local account</a>. It requires <em>pulling out your ethernet cable</em> and running a shell command, but it’s reasonably straightforward.</li>
<li>For my US readers: you may also want to select “Global English” rather than “US English” in the language selection step, as this apparently eliminates some awfulness in the start-up screen.</li>
<li>The guide mentions widgets in the traditional “Start” button location. That was the case for me too, but I don’t think I actually flipped any “Personalization” switches before realizing the Start menu was back where it should be. Not sure what I did, but at least initially that was definitely the case for me, so watch out.</li>
</ul>
<p>At this point, we picked up a Windows license and a couple Office licenses from a friend of the family for some steep discounts (that was awfully nice), so I could unlock the power of this <a href="https://i.makeagif.com/media/10-03-2016/hfPN-9.gif">fully armed and operational</a> Windows 11.</p>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next">What’s next?</h3>
<p>That’s about it—a complete build from components, up to installing two operating systems. So what’s next?</p>
<p>Well, the first thing was to give it a name! I struggled with this for a bit. On one hand, I’d only just finished <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> in late December (yeah, I intentionally sandbagged, savoring the final stages). But on the other hand, most of the devices in my house already have <em>Zelda</em>-themed names.</p>
<p>(Devices that have a <em>Zelda</em>-themed name: 1 of 2 laptops, 2 of 2 smartphones, 1 of 2 iPads, 7 of 8 Raspberry Pis, 1 NAS, and now 1 desktop. WOW, y’all.)</p>
<p>But! In a conversation over Mastodon, I was reminded that this isn’t really a bad thing.</p>
<p></p><div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0;"> <iframe src="https://fosstodon.org/@jni/111730083884821265/embed" class="mastodon-embed" style="max-width: 100%; border: 0;" width="100%" height="400" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe><script src="https://mastodon.social/embed.js" async="async"></script></div> <p></p>
<p>So I took the first name that came to mind that seemed incredibly appropriate: <a href="https://zelda.fandom.com/wiki/Makar">Makar, the ancient Sage of Wind</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="https://static.wikia.nocookie.net/zelda_gamepedia_en/images/b/b0/TWW_Makar_Artwork.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-43" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-43" title="Makar, in his element."><img src="https://static.wikia.nocookie.net/zelda_gamepedia_en/images/b/b0/TWW_Makar_Artwork.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Makar, in his element."></a></p>
<figcaption>Makar, in his element.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>From there, it’s been a matter of configuring two full-blown operating systems. Ubuntu is pretty much the workhorse: that’s where I’ll make heavy use of the GPU. I’ve already installed all the CUDA dependencies and a Python environment with the basic setup, and thanks to the M.2 drives I have plenty of speedy storage for large datasets. On the Windows side, this is indeed for gaming, but also for office productivity (especially if I don’t have my laptop handy). Most of these basics are in place, but it’ll be an ongoing process.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I have some n@zis to mow down in <em>Wolfenstein</em> and some segmentation models to run on spatial omics data. Until next time!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><a href="full_install.jpg" class="lightbox" data-gallery="quarto-lightbox-gallery-44" data-glightbox="description: .lightbox-desc-44" title="Beautiful. Absolutely stunning."><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/full_install.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Beautiful. Absolutely stunning."></a></p>
<figcaption>Beautiful. Absolutely stunning.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>I swear, there’s a post coming about this. Sometime.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>I built this in my second week of sabbatical. The first week was a veritable <em>fire hose</em> from which I was struggling to surface. That, plus the general post-holiday malaise, plus university stuff still demanding my attention… yeah this is probably the best answer.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {The {Legend} of {Makar}},
  date = {2024-01-25},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“The Legend of Makar.”</span> January 25,
2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar">https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>makar</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2024 19:09:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/makar.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2023: A year of extremes</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/landscape.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A picture of a forested landscape at sunset, the sun coming through the bare tree branches."></p>
<p>Where 2022 tried its hardest to kill me, 2023 merely put that killer instinct in neutral. A vast improvement to be sure, but it requires substantial context to fully appreciate.</p>
<p>Ok, maybe that’s not fair to 2023. It had some highs. It also had some lows. All told, 2023 was one of the most bimodal years in my recent memory, perhaps second only to 2020.</p>
<section id="the-good" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-good">The Good</h3>
<ul>
<li>Running (and health + fitness in general) was <em>huge</em> for both me and my wife in 2023. We both set annual running mileage records<sup>1</sup> that outpaced the last couple years by massive margins.</li>
<li>Burnout recovery was tangible. The difference is night and day. Even though I still have a long way to go, I can get through most typical weeks—even the occasional atypically strenuous week—without needing to aggressively power down.</li>
<li>Related to the previous point, I set and held some boundaries, especially around work.</li>
<li>I snagged myself a pretty sweet gig with <a href="https://predxbio.com/">PredxBio</a> as their Principal AI/ML Scientist, starting January 2024. It’s technically a sabbatical (I’ll post about this later in more detail), but I’m really excited for the change.</li>
<li>I’ve picked up a few at-home side projects that I’m really enjoying. This culminated in a <code>#DecemberAdventure</code> over on Mastodon that saw a lot of tinkering around building out a homelab. It’s still in the proof-of-concept stages but I’m really having fun with it!</li>
<li>My wife and I downloaded, played through, and beat <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>. It was pretty much <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_wxU3z9VxOY">the opposite of this, but just as beautiful</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>I cannot underscore enough how groundbreaking it was for us to find a stride<sup>2</sup> with our running and general activity levels.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/running_yearoveryear.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A screenshot from a Garmin Connect progress report, showing huge running mileage increases in 2023 relative to 2022 and 2021."></p>
<figcaption>A Garmin Connect annual mileage summary. The second column is number of runs, third column is total annual mileage, and the last column is average milege per run.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My own health improved dramatically over the course of the year (especially after being kicked while down by getting COVID on the evening of December 31, 2022): not only did my labs empirically show this improvement at my end-of-year physical, but my two half marathons this year were separated by 6 months (April and October) and by <em>20 minutes</em> (<a href="https://track.rtrt.me/e/DMP-SAVWHALF-2023#/tracker/RW4KTAP2">2:31</a> in April, <a href="https://results.raceroster.com/v2/en-US/results/cbqshhkjvt39snge/detail/egpe264973f6ynms">2:12</a> in October). Both still technically rank among my slowest half marathon finishing times, but the trend is so, so encouraging.</p>
<p>My burnout has also improved dramatically. Where I could barely make it through a work week in 2022, this past year—through careful planning, tracking of my activity and burnout levels, and changing course as needed—I could maintain relatively normal levels of work intensity, while still protecting time for things I needed and wanted (workouts, hobbies, socializing, sleeping).</p>
<p>Part of this burnout management culminated in seeking out an opportunity with PredxBio, a Pittsburgh-based startup in spatial biology. I started with them just this past Tuesday, and I’m thrilled to see where this change of pace takes me.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-bad" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-bad">The Bad</h3>
<ul>
<li>Despite my burnout recovery, I still had some weeks that fried me so badly I needed to clear my schedule to power down. Not often, but more than zero.</li>
<li>I can’t recall a time when I’ve muted, unfollowed, or blocked more people than after October 7. The sudden influx of middle east geopolitical “expertise” was unreal.</li>
<li>My frustration levels with professionals and their uncritical embrace of hype around AI are high. I’ll be the first to admit: AI does cool stuff, but putting everything else aside to build AI into our workflows without acknowledging its real, myriad weaknesses is really disheartening.</li>
</ul>
<p>I submitted a large grant application in late September, and three days later submitted a smaller seed grant application. This was one example of a week where I pushed myself too hard and needed an acute and immediate recovery period. Another example was mid-November: I was in charge of organizing and MCing a panel on “AI in Higher Education” at my department’s annual “Research Day”, and it just happened to coincide with several instructional milestones that same week. In both cases, I needed to clear my schedule for a couple days. I’m fortunate to be able to do that, but I was also completely non-functional those days.</p>
<p>Speaking of the seed grant: I heard back only weeks ago that our application was denied. Certainly not an unlikely outcome, but what really frustrated me was the following:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Due to the volume of proposals, reviewers were not asked to prepare written critiques.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is one of my biggest critiques of the academic system on a whole<sup>3</sup>: feedback either isn’t given, or it’s given too late to use, or—at its most destructive—it’s actively misleading.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-ugly" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-ugly">The Ugly</h3>
<ul>
<li>We started the year with COVID. I got the “long” version.</li>
<li>While burnout recovery has improved my overall bandwidth, it’s made room for long-simmering and unresolved resentment, frustration, and anger around a variety of things. This needlessly consumed a lot of spare cycles and left me run down.</li>
<li>Everything happening in the middle east since early October.</li>
<li>Nihilism crept in this year. <a href="https://infosec.town/notes/9nx5yvs2am7mdbcs">This toot</a> helped point it out to me, but charting a path out is proving difficult.</li>
</ul>
<p>After almost three years of avoiding COVID, my wife and I caught it just before leaving a holiday family reunion in Arizona (though didn’t show symptoms until days after returning home). Our infections were both relatively “minor”—the medical term, though I had a fever hovering just below 102F and she had the worst congestion of her life—but even after I tested negative (it took me almost two weeks to fully clear it), I developed new and lingering respiratory symptoms I’d never had previously. These symptoms lasted for months, nearly into the summer, and included exercise-induced asthma: I would start every run feeling like I was drowning. For the first 20 minutes of a run, my lungs wouldn’t open; I’d feel like I had an elephant sitting on my chest. Eventually my lungs would open, but I’d often be exhausted by that point, making my return to running <a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/10/05/return-of-the-100-mile-month/">very slow and very frustrating</a>. Even now, a year later, I still deal with occasional symptoms, though they have thankfully substantially decreased in intensity and frequency.</p>
<p>I’ve also noticed that my brain has spent a lot more time (and energy) spinning on people who and events that have left me angry or otherwise upset. This has always been a weakness of mine and a regular point of discussion and focused work with my therapists over the years, but in 2023 it got a lot worse.</p>
<p>Resentment was a big problem, especially since I’ve no way of knowing whether the resentment came from something real or because <a href="https://theness.com/neurologicablog/conspiracy-thinking-and-pattern-recognition/">my brain connected disparate events in a way that was completely fictitious</a>.</p>
<p>Combined with real-world events, an impending US Presidential elections with massive implications, and ongoing ambivalence or outright antipathy toward any kind of COVID countermeasures (<a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#maps_new-admissions-rate-county">despite the current wave that is second only to the massive Omicron wave of late 2021</a>), real nihilism crept in. What kind of world am I raising our daughter in? What kind of world am I handing off to her? What can I possibly do to change any of this? <a href="https://amyjko.medium.com/things-i-hope-for-in-2024-8688c4fbd959">Reading Amy Ko’s hopes for 2024</a> helped, as did the numerous reminders to “think global, act local”.</p>
</section>
<section id="plans-for-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans-for-2024">Plans for 2024</h3>
<p>I gave up on resolutions years ago, but I still set goals and make plans for achieving those goals. I also try to prioritize and set my goals up for success.</p>
<p><strong>My biggest priority this year, I think, is to tackle the lingering resentment and default-to-anger</strong>. It drained me so needlessly last year, and there’s never going to be any shortage of things and people to be outraged about / at. I’ve seen a lot of memes with pithy reframings, and while I think those are valuable, they don’t quite hit the mark for me; “consider if a person is worth your anger” still feels too antagonistic, too “me-vs-them.”</p>
<p>Instead—and in line with what we teach our daughter!—I want to allow myself space to feel and observe these reactions, and then to inspect and interrogate them. This not only refocuses on me outside of a combative context, but also forges new neural pathways to make this process second-nature.</p>
<p>My other plans, in no particular order:</p>
<ul>
<li>1000+ miles running (will probably write about this on my running blog soon-ish)</li>
<li>Reorganize my upstairs office, complete with a home server rack to consolidate hardware</li>
<li>Donate donate donate! (there is SO MUCH STUFF around the house we just don’t use)</li>
<li>Set and hold boundaries, especially around work, but also around family and friends</li>
</ul>
<p>There are other smaller items in there too—I’ve learned a lot more about kubernetes networking and foresee an overhaul of my cluster configuration in the near future; I’m also toying with some yard improvement ideas to try and improve the drainage; and I cannot underscore how much I want to clear out the garage, since it’s about 1/3 full of stuff we literally never touch and most likely never will again—but those are on more of a “as time and energy allow” basis.</p>
<p>I wish everyone a wonderful 2024.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Post-COVID lockdown mileage records. My insane all-time annual record set in 2014 still stands. For now.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>What can I say? The past few years have been a <em>marathon</em>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I have an entire draft written about my issues with academia at the institutional, state, and local levels, but I don’t know when, or even if, I’ll post it; if you want to talk about it though, I’m happy to.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {2023: {A} Year of Extremes},
  date = {2024-01-05},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“2023: A Year of Extremes.”</span> January
5, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes">https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>new year</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 19:45:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/landscape.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Advent of Adventure</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_mordor_full.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A gritty image from behind a small group of heroes, facing down a massive robotic army, in a shattered land that looks a lot like Mordor (generated by DALL-E)."></p>
<p>This past Monday evening, from a tiny cabin in Dahlonega, GA, I turned to my wife and said: <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/what-a-week-huh">“What a week, huh?”</a></p>
<p>We had a much-needed mini-vacation in the middle of the week to recoup and relax. It wasn’t nearly long enough to fully come down from the cortisol high but it at least jump-started the process. We even got a hike in, and did some stargazing. Even as relatively small as Athens is, there’s still a lot of light pollution, the lack of which is breathtaking if you can get a little further out.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/milky_way.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A nighttime shot of the stars, including a faintly-visible Milky Way."></p>
<figcaption>It’s tough to see, not the least of which because of iPhone 15’s aggressive low-light compensation, but the Milky Way is visible from the left-middle almost to the branches of the tree.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve felt guilty—for many reasons; there’s never a shortage, but in this case because I’d originally wanted to participate in this year’s <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">Advent of Code</a>. I was introduced to it two years ago, too late to finish it completely, but at the time I enjoyed it. Last year I was too burned out to get more than a few days in, so I was feeling particularly motivated this year.</p>
<p>But then the end-of-semester shenanigans were an order of magnitude worse than expected, and December entered with a bang and from the mountains I lamented not having logged a single activity.</p>
<p>Then I came across <a href="https://eli.li/december-adventure">December Adventure</a>.</p>
<p>I <em>loved</em> the main idea: the goal is just to write a little bit of code, every day, in the month of December. Or, really, to make progress on any project or projects, a little bit each day.</p>
<p>So consider this not only my inaugural <code>#DecemberAdventure</code> post, but a bit of a catch-up on the things I’ve been doing that have brought me a tiny bit of joy in the dismally oversaturated realities of the past couple months.</p>
<section id="retropie-redux" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="retropie-redux">RetroPie, redux</h3>
<p>Astute readers here may recall that this is <a href="../../posts/2017-01-06-gameify-your-raspberry-pi/index.html">something I’d already done a few years back</a> (ok, <em>several</em> years back, geez). However, that was a Pi 3B+, which did ok with NES and SNES games, but ground to a complete standstill on any 3D games—N64 was beyond it.</p>
<p>Armed with a Pi 4B with 4GB of RAM, I sought to bring RetroPie back! I’d also seen in the documentation that the Nintendo Switch Pro controllers were supported, so getting that working was another goal of mine (rather than the generic USB controllers I’d used last time).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/retropie_open.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>An open view of the Pi inside the SNES enclosure, complete with a fan.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A few other minor changes from last time: now I had a <a href="https://www.canakit.com/raspberry-pi4-retro-gaming-case.html">cool mini-SNES enclosure</a> for the Pi, which came with room for a single fan to help keep things cool. I was pretty sure the fan was overkill, but I figured, what the heck. I also actually wired the Pi to ethernet, rather than relying on wifi like last time. It took a little bit of adjusting, but it was a change I’d wanted to make to our home network backbone anyway.</p>
<p>The result: a snazzy new RetroPie!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/retropie.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The SNES enclosure, with power and ethernet cables plugged in.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did still run into some issues with getting the <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/docs/Nintendo-Switch-Controllers/">Nintendo Switch Pro controller</a> working. Specifically, the Bluetooth: <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/forum/topic/34226/cannot-pair-nintendo-switch-pro-controller/7">this issue in the discussion forum</a> mirrored my problems exactly. I could turn on diagnostics for the Pi and see that it was detecting every single button press and stick movement, but for some reason those changes weren’t being propagated to the <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/docs/Controller-Configuration/">emulator software</a>.</p>
<p>In the end, I plugged the Pro controllers into the back of the Pi, and they worked beautifully. It just meant I had to sit on the floor, feet from my TV, in order to play. Like the days of Yore, I suppose.</p>
</section>
<section id="chatgpt-and-dall-e-for-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chatgpt-and-dall-e-for-science">ChatGPT and DALL-E, for “science”</h3>
<p>I recently started a new collaboration investigating the utility of commercial LLMs—specifically, <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/guides/vision">the new GPT 4 with vision</a>—in understanding, deciphering, and analyzing biomedical image data.</p>
<p>I’ve thrown a little bit of my [OPENLY AVAILABLE] data at it. To use the academic lingo: the performance to date has been decidedly unimpressive. But work continues.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, it’s also given me the opportunity to play around again with image generators (I stopped paying Midjourney a long time ago). In particular, I’ve been keen to see if ChatGPT’s integration with DALL-E has allowed for better <em>iteration</em> on images—carrying over context from previous image prompts to iterate on and improve subsequent images.</p>
<p>With Midjourney, iteration often entailed copy/pasting the previous prompt and making subtle changes that I thought would give me what I was looking for. Here, I was hopeful that, given the conversational interface with ChatGPT, I could now just tweak the things I wanted to change by “having a chat.”</p>
<p>Yet again, I was disappointed. But I did come up with some interesting mash-ups. Inspired by a <a href="ai_symposium_keynote.jpg">recent keynote speech</a> at our Institute of AI Symposium, I wanted to see what favorite universes of mine I could combine.</p>
<p>If anyone has read any of Brandon Sanderson’s Stormlight Archive, they will immediately recognize <a href="https://coppermind.net/wiki/Herald">the ten Heralds</a>. For those who haven’t: think of the Heralds as <em>deeply flawed and damaged, likely insane</em> superheroes. Maybe not “The Boys” level awful, but certainly not your aw-shucks-go-team plucky Avengers.</p>
<p>Well, I tried putting them in different situations. First I tried oil paintings in the medieval ages.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_medieval.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The 10 Heralds, depicted in a medieval oil painting style.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_medieval2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A second attempt at the same image.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In both cases, you may notice… there are more than 10 individuals. I couldn’t find a way to <em>guarantee</em> the number I was asking for, as you’ll see.</p>
<p>Next I tried the Heralds in the Lego universe.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_lego.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The 10 Heralds as LEGO heroes.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Again, it <em>seems</em> as though there are 11 people? And what’s with the bird motif, suddenly? I said nothing about birds.</p>
<p>This continues when I tried putting the Heralds in the Marvel Avengers universe.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_avengers.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The 10 Heralds as the Avengers.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Again, I count 11 individuals, with no fewer than three wearing Iron Man-like powered suits. You can’t <em>all</em> be Iron Man!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_avengers2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The 10 Heralds as the Avengers, again.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once more, the weird bird motif shows up, despite no mention of birds in the prompt (or any part of the ChatGPT discussion thread). There also only seem to be 9? And Captain America’s shield is just… floating there. I do love that Iron Spider suit, though; I wonder which Herald that is.</p>
<p>From here I tried pitting the Heralds against <em>Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</em> enemies, but set in <em>The Expanse</em> universe.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_mordor.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The 10 Heralds fighting demonic robots on a shattered landscape in a gritty world.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As far as I can tell, there are only 5 Heralds, but otherwise this picture is pretty cool. I love how Mordor-esque the landscape is, and even though the robot army bears no resemblance to anything in <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>, it’s still pretty neat.</p>
<p>The second attempt was a lot closer to what I was looking for:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_vs_guardians.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The 10 Heralds fighting demonic spider-like robots on a shattered landscape in a gritty world.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Still only 9 Heralds as far as I can tell, and again the humanoid robots aren’t recognizable, BUT I <em>love</em> the giant arachnid enemies. I can definitely see that as an <em>Expanse</em>-ification of the classic <em>Breath of the Wild</em> <a href="https://zelda.fandom.com/wiki/Guardian">Guardians</a>.</p>
<p>From here I tried a smattering of other things.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/jez_as_pres.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A United States Presidential headshot of Jezrien, the leader of the Heralds.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/kaladin_botw.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A picture of Kaladin, one of the Knights Radiant, in the art style of Breath of the Wild.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/roci_as_zonai.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A depiction of the Rocinante, the Martian gunship from The Expanse, if it were engineered as a Zonai construct from Tears of the Kingdom.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/roci_in_hateno.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Another depiction of the Rocinante, this time showing it having landed in Hateno Village, in the art style of Breath of the Wild.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Each one of these deviates significantly from what I would have expected, which is not a problem per se. I would say that they do seem to have a tendency to gravitate toward certain modes, and it’s <em>really hard</em> to pull the image generators off those modes.</p>
</section>
<section id="rae-rae-rae-your-robot" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rae-rae-rae-your-robot">Rae rae rae your robot</h3>
<p>I backed the Luxonis kickstarter last year for the <a href="https://shop.luxonis.com/collections/oak-cameras-1/products/rae">rae robots</a> (Robotics Access for Everyone), and since getting them, they’ve been… tricky.</p>
<p>The forums are full of folks just <a href="https://discuss.luxonis.com/t/rae">trying to get them working</a>, and the associated documentation is extremely sparse to entirely nonexistent. It’s a brand-new product, but the team definitely hasn’t had a chance to catch up on the documentation side.</p>
<p>I ended up getting things working, but it required multiple lines of advice combined in different ways.</p>
<p>Firstly, I started with the <a href="https://docs-beta.luxonis.com/hardware/rae/get-started/?v=Advanced+%28manual%29">Advanced (manual) setup</a>, and this… ended up being impossible, at least if you want your rae to show up on Robothub (which, currently, is the only way to install and run apps). I’ll write a later post documenting this side, but suffice to say, it just doesn’t work.</p>
<p>Secondly, I couldn’t get the hard reset button on the bottom of the rae to work. I may have been doing it wrong. But I found <a href="https://discuss.luxonis.com/d/2328-newbee-quick-starter-to-get-code/3">this excellent post outlining a “soft reset”</a> that worked perfectly.</p>
<p>Thirdly, from the moment I pushed the power button on the rae, I just pointed it at the QR code from Robothub (linked from the <a href="https://docs-beta.luxonis.com/hardware/rae/get-started/?v=RobotHub+Cloud">Cloud setup instructions</a>) and held it there for several minutes. Eventually, the lights started flashing blue at regular intervals and the screen indicated it was connecting to my local wifi network. The rest worked as advertised (even if the lights turn red, apparently this is a known bug).</p>
<p>I haven’t done anything else with them yet, except name them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/rae.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Two rae robots, with name tags on their tops: one says 'koume', the other says 'kotake'."></p>
<figcaption>Zelda fans, unite.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next">What’s next?</h3>
<p>Consider this my first official entry into <code>#DecemberAdventure</code>, and maybe retroactively through the whole month of December so far.</p>
<p>After today, I’ll try to post regular updates on Mastodon about my <code>#DecemberAdventure</code> activities. Now the semester is <em>largely</em> over—there are still some outstanding obligations, but without class there should be more time for tinkering.</p>
<p>And relaxing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/coffee_shop_fireplace.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="First-person perspective of the interior of a warm and cozy coffee shop, with a fireplace at one end. There's a coffee table in the middle, a decorated Christmas tree on the right, and other decorations are hung on the mantle. A painting of a reindeer is on the wall above the fireplace."></p>
<figcaption>More of this, please.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Advent of {Adventure}},
  date = {2023-12-08},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Advent of Adventure.”</span> December 8,
2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure">https://magsol.github.io/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>advent of code</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>rae</category>
  <category>retropie</category>
  <category>dall-e</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 15:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_mordor_full.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rebuilding</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/athhalf_2023_finish.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A photo of me crossing the finish line at Ath Half 2023 this past October, holding up my arms in exhausted triumph."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Content warning: discussions of body image, eating habits, diet culture, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_COVID">long COVID</a>. Also, language.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has been a very long road back from long COVID.</p>
<p>I can vividly remember where I was a year ago: in the depths of burnout, taking naps almost every day just to get by; weekly migraines; running in place yet accomplishing nothing; maybe getting in a few miles of running per week, and <em>years</em> since I could string together more than about 10 push-ups at once.</p>
<p>And <em>then</em> COVID hit, and even though the active infection was relatively mild, some symptoms stuck around for months after: exercise-induced asthma and sleep apnea being the two most disruptive and frustrating. When I started running again in late January, every single outing was, frankly, infuriating: the first couple miles were agonizing. My lungs wouldn’t open; it felt like drowning. My heart would race. And by the time my lungs finally opened up, I was usually exhausted by then anyway. The Savannah Women’s Half in April rolled around, and <a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/04/03/three-years-later/">even though I finished</a>, it was a 1-minute improvement over the previous October’s Ath Half.</p>
<p>Six months, 1-minute improvement, for my <em>second</em>-slowest half marathon time ever.</p>
<p>This was also when I started seeing a specialist for my breathing. I experienced a brief reprieve in January from the migraines that had been plaguing me for the past several months—burnout recovery!—but they started back up again in late January and through all of February before I realized they were due to my other new long COVID symptom, sleep apnea; an at-home sleep study later confirmed it.</p>
<p>Additionally, I started seeing a dietician. Not an influencer or “lifestyle coach”, someone with an actual fucking degree in nutrition—and someone who came recommended for athletes. I figured if I really wanted to manage these symptoms, I was going to need to hit them from every angle: medical interventions, dietary changes, and a regular workout regimen.</p>
<ul>
<li>The <strong>medical interventions</strong> front has been, by far, the most disappointing. Despite seeing highly recommended pulomnary and sleep specialists, their treatment options have been severely limited by insurance companies refusing to reimburse them. I’ve also been disappointed by their unwillingness to “work the system”, forcing me to advocate for myself despite seeking these people out <em>specifically because I lack specialist knowledge</em>. I’ve had to rely on data from a pulse oximeter I purchased myself to monitor and adjust my nighttime sleep habits, and have incorporated my own series of stretches and pre-run exercises to open up my lungs. It’s all helped, but it’s been <em>in spite of</em> seeing a specialist rather than <em>because of it</em>. tl;dr welcome to healthcare in America.</li>
<li>The <strong>dietician</strong>, conversely, has been an incredible success. We instantly found an amazing rapport and have had monthly check-ups since to evaluate how things have been going to make tweaks as needed. She helped identify how lacking my protein intake was and gave me lots of options for increasing it, many of which my wife and I have seamlessly integrated. She’s also helped improve my fueling <em>before</em> runs and workouts, and best of all she <em>soundly</em> rejects diet culture which I <em>deeply</em> appreciate. Restriction simply doesn’t work; instead, we found a menu rotation that is working for me, and for everything else I try to approach it with mindfulness and intention (that helps a lot with the “oops I just ate an entire bag of chips while standing over my sink” incidents).</li>
<li>The <strong>physical exercise</strong> has also been incredibly successful, though it took a long time and was probably the most consistently frustrating. Exercise takes time and extended commitment, neither of which I had much of in April when work ate up a lot of my energy and every run was guaranteed to start with 15-20 minutes of simulated drowning. But around this time my wife and I started <em>regularly</em> incorporating 2x/week weightlifting sessions, the first time either of us had even entered a weightroom in <em>years</em>, to say nothing of multiple sessions each week. By August I’d added a third weekly session for my own areas of focus, and by September I was experimenting with a <em>fourth</em> (though that was very, very difficult to maintain consistently and so would tend to be “schedule permitting”). It took a LOT of intentional planning—and commitment to saying “no!”—to guard and protect my 3x/week weightlifting sessions AND 4x/week runs.</li>
</ul>
<p>Strava was able to see the consistency, starting in April.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/strava_fitness.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A line plot showing Strava's proprietary fitness indicator over the last calendary year. It increases sharply in March and April and remains there through the rest of the  year."></p>
<figcaption>Strava’s fitness proxy. Note the sustained levels for the past 6 months.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s taken a long time, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I stopped wearing my pulse oximeter back in August and haven’t had sleep apnea episodes since July.</li>
<li>The migraines also disappeared entirely around July.</li>
<li>By July, I’d started clocking longer runs than any in the previous 3 years.</li>
<li>In August, I could run 9 miles without walking.</li>
<li>In September, I could run 12 miles without walking, and at a faster pace than I ran 9 back in August.</li>
<li>Also in September, I could bench press multiple reps of over 200lbs in the middle of a larger superset.</li>
<li>In October, I ran Ath Half. While technically it is now my <em>third</em>-slowest half marathon time, I beat my April Savannah Women’s Half time by <em>18 minutes</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>I was deep in the middle of one of my longest weight sessions in years when I took this picture.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/me_gym.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A picture of me in the middle of a weightlifting session, looking sweaty and tired and strong and self-conscious."></p>
<figcaption>Mid lift session photo.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Normally, I <em>hate</em> photos like this. Further, I don’t particularly like how I look. But I wanted to take this picture because, in the moment, I felt <em>strong</em> and <em>powerful</em>, sentiments I hadn’t felt toward myself in quite some time. It was one of the first times in years where I felt like I actually belonged in the weight room. I’ve only just started feeling like I belong with the other local runners, too.</p>
<p>I still have bad days. My breath still occasionally catches and, for a moment, my lungs feel like they’re closing back up; maybe it’s some last vestiges of long COVID, maybe I inhaled some pollutant in the air (plenty to choose from), or maybe it’s in my head. I still get headaches that knock out entire swathes of a given day, though now they’re almost exclusively because of burnout recovery (a very “two steps forward, one step back” process), rather than apnea. Some days I just… push myself too hard, too fast, and I need to back off. My recovery periods are still longer than they used to be—whether this is long COVID related, burnout related, age related, or some combination of all of the above, I don’t know. I still get frustrated with how much slower I still am running than I used to be, in spite of the <em>incredible</em> progress I’ve made over the past 6 months. I still eat tortilla chips straight out of the bag while standing over the sink. I still look at my body in the mirror and critique it.</p>
<p>But even if I don’t get back to running 1:40 half marathons, I’m already back to sub-10 minute/mile half marathons. I’m already back to benching 220lbs. I’m consistently running 20+ miles/week. I’ve run <strong>almost 700 miles this year</strong> (on track for 800+!), complete with <a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/10/05/return-of-the-100-mile-month/">my first 100-mile month in years</a>, after running 308 and 377 miles in each of the last two years. I’m stronger and healthier and happier than I’ve been in such a long time, and I’m so, so grateful for it.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Rebuilding},
  date = {2023-11-09},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-11-09-rebuilding},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Rebuilding.”</span> November 9, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-11-09-rebuilding">https://magsol.github.io/2023-11-09-rebuilding</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>covid</category>
  <category>running</category>
  <category>weightlifting</category>
  <category>food</category>
  <category>health</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 13:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/athhalf_2023_finish.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="216" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Hero Of Everything</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/link_cece_hat.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="An in-game picture of Link from _Tears of the Kingdom_ with pink hair and dark lipstick, and wearing the Cece hat. Picture from this Polygon article: https://www.polygon.com/legend-zelda-tears-kingdom/23725926/tears-of-the-kingdom-totk-best-hat-outfit-cece-mushroom-hat-how-to-get-slay ."></p>
<p>This is the first of two <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> related blog posts I’ll be making. Don’t worry—there won’t be any story spoilers in either one. But <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/@magsol/110792987901449157">my wife did just beat the game this past week</a> (my game isn’t anywhere near the end), so I did want to put down some spoiler-free thoughts on the topic, as well as more detail surrounding <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/@magsol/110776842879244818">recent discoveries on hybrid-powered flight</a> I’ve been posting about on Mastodon.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I just wanted to put in writing something my wife and I hit on very quickly after starting <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>: the many hats Link wears. Sure, he has a Big Bad he needs to put down—the whole “Hero of hyrule/time/twilight/the skies/winds/dreams/etc” thing—but this is about the <em>side quests</em>. In games prior to, oh I don’t know, 2017, these always included a few non-warrior talents: escorting people places, fetching an item, taking care of animals, and so on.</p>
<p>But <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> (and to an only slightly lesser extent, <em>Breath of the Wild</em>) took this to a whole new level. Just focusing on the main story quest is starting to feel like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_ChQK8j6so8">only doing the bare minimum</a>.</p>
<p>Without further adieu, I give you (this list is most likely incomplete, so please feel free to contribute!):</p>
<p><strong>The List of Roles Link Is “Hired” (Willingly…?) Into Aside From, You Know, Actual Hero-ing in <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Farmer</li>
<li>Gardener</li>
<li>Construction worker</li>
<li>Lumberjack</li>
<li>Babysitter</li>
<li>Cook</li>
<li>(Electrical / Mechanical) Engineer</li>
<li>Elementary School Teacher</li>
<li>Chauffeur</li>
<li>Journalist</li>
<li>Photographer</li>
<li>Research Assistant</li>
<li>Cartographer</li>
<li>Test driver</li>
<li>Undercover secret agent</li>
<li>Uncle</li>
<li>Historian</li>
<li>Election Official / Campaign Worker</li>
<li>Equestrian</li>
<li>Spelunker</li>
<li>Blacksmith</li>
<li>Miner</li>
<li>General</li>
<li>Privateer</li>
</ul>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {The {Hero} {Of} {Everything}},
  date = {2023-07-30},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“The Hero Of Everything.”</span> July 30,
2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything">https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>video games</category>
  <category>zelda</category>
  <category>tears of the kingdom</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 14:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/link_cece_hat.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Upgrading the Raspberry Pi Cluster</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/setup.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="My home office desk, with the GamersNexus rubber mat, along with all the hardware materials for the cluster upgrade, including: a stack of PoE HAT boxes, a Netgear 8-port PoE switch, a small power brick from Anker with two 2-port USB-to-outlet adapters, and my laptop."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
An ode to time zones
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>As I write this up, I’m sitting in my SciPy hotel room. It’s a nice way to relax and unwind after a <em>long</em> day of travel and tutorials, but I also apologize for any timezone weirdness or general grammar or syntax errors.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>In the seven months since <a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">standing up my own Mastodon instance</a>, the Mastodon team has made quite a few releases. Up until last week, I was running <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/tree/v4.0.2">4.0.2</a>, which had originally been released back in November 2022 when I started this crazy journey.</p>
<p>I’d also been wanting to perform a hardware upgrade of the Pi cluster. The server rack I built back in mid-2022, while effective at protecting the cluster from toddlers, was a mess of cables on the inside: turns out, five stacked Raspberry Pi boards have a lot of associated cabling!</p>
<p>My plan for hardware updates included:</p>
<ul>
<li>installing <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/products/poe-plus-hat/">power-over-ethernet (PoE) hardware-attached-on-top (HAT)s</a> on each Raspberry Pi, so I could supply both power and networking through the ethernet cable</li>
<li>rewiring the 3x Raspberry Pi case fans to be USB-powered, rather than depending on connections to the GPIO boards of each Pi</li>
<li>downsizing the power brick inside the server case</li>
</ul>
<p>This all took quite a bit of work. And, oddly enough, the software was the <em>easy</em> part.</p>
<section id="upgrading-mastodon" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upgrading-mastodon">Upgrading Mastodon</h3>
<p>This was “merely” a matter of running an upgrade using the latest Helm chart from Mastodon’s repository. There was a minor wrinkle: the chart had been <em>substantially</em> updated from the one I used to install Mastodon back in December 2022. It <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart">has its own repository now</a>!</p>
<p>I had to carefully go through the chart I used to originally install Mastodon, and the new chart, to make sure I was correctly transferring old configuration values to the new chart. I really only made two mistakes in this process:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>I forgot to fill in the mailer configuration</li>
<li>When specifying the tag, I first put “4.1.3”, instead of “v4.1.3” 🤦‍♂️</li>
</ol>
<p>Fortunately, both were easy fixes. What was a bit trickier was the re-emergence of a <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/73">well-known race condition</a> in the database migration process. It took three separate re-starts of the upgrade process, but it eventually ran to successful completion, and my instance is now running 4.1.3!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Of course, <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/releases/tag/v4.1.4">4.1.4</a> was just released 3 days ago as of this writing. Of course.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="hardware-upgrades" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hardware-upgrades">Hardware Upgrades</h3>
<p>If the software upgrades took a day, the hardware upgrades took a week.</p>
<p>I mentioned I wanted to install PoE HATs on each Raspberry Pi so they could draw both their power and network connectivity from a single ethernet connection.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/poe_hat.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A stack of 6 PoE HAT boxes, waiting to be unboxed and installed, one per Raspberry Pi."></p>
<figcaption>How many HATs does one person need?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>What I didn’t mention is: there’s more to it than that. To power devices using PoE, you also need networking hardware that is PoE-compatible. This meant replacing my standard 6-port unmanaged switch with a PoE-compatible switch.</p>
<p>It also meant upgrading from 6 ports to 8, since I also wanted to add a 6th Pi to the cluster—which, when you include the necessary port for connecting the switch to the <em>rest</em> of the network, means a minimum of 7 ports.</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/poe_switch.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="A Netgear 8-port unmanaged PoE+ switch. Officially, its product number is GS308P."></p>
<p>To start, I had to shut down and disassemble the Raspberry Pi cluster (which you can see in <a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">this post back in January</a>). Here was the result, along with the 6th Pi I wanted to add:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/rpis.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Six Raspberry Pi boards, all on the desk."></p>
<figcaption>So much pi(e).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With the Pi cluster itself out of the homemade rack, you can see the interior with all the rest of the cabling:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/rack_interior.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Interior shot of my homemade server rack, which is really just a wooden crate with some cut-outs for intake/exhaust fans and a clear plexiglass side for viewing. Inside the Raspberry Pi cluster has been removed, leaving the original 6-port switch, power brick, ethernet cables, power cables, and fan cables. So many cables."></p>
<figcaption>Cables cables everywhere but not an ounce of space.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Yeah. It was pretty crowded, even without the little stack of 5 Raspberry Pi boards. Clearing some of that out via PoE sounded really, really good.</p>
<p>The first step was to install the PoE HAT on each Raspberry Pi. Here’s a before shot:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/single_pi.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A single Raspberry Pi 4B board, unmodified."></p>
<figcaption>A standard Raspberry Pi 4B.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And here’s what it looks like when I’ve installed a PoE HAT on it:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/pi_hat.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A single Raspberry Pi 4B board, now with a PoE HAT on it."></p>
<figcaption>A standard Raspberry Pi 4B, now with a PoE HAT on it.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As an aside: this adds a surprising amount of weight to the Pi! By itself it wasn’t all that noticeable, but once I’d re-stacked the Pi cluster, I was more than a little shocked by how much heavier it was! Something to keep in mind.</p>
<p>The server rack I built has three Pi case fans as intake, and previously these were powered by literally hooking them into the 5V GPIO pins of three of the Pi boards. Now that all the Pi boards had HATs on, their GPIO pins were entirely inaccessible. Which was fine, because I’d wanted to convert the intake fans to USB power anyway—I’d done this already for the two exhaust fans, which I had cannibalized from an old desktop RAM cooler.</p>
<p>Fun fact: these old RAM cooler fans were the same size as the Pi case fans, but for some reason were 12V fans (and USB is, by default, 5V), so I needed to leverage <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ohm%27s_law">Ohm’s Law</a> and buy a converter that upped the resistence in order to increase the voltage.</p>
<p>Fortunately, this was not the case for the Pi case fans: they needed 5V, and 5V is what any standard USB plug provides. All that was needed was some minor rewiring so the fan leads connected to the corresponding wires inside a USB cable. The end result looked something like this:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/rewired_fan.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A standard 5V Raspberry Pi case fan with its two cables connected to the corresponding power/ground wires inside a USB cable that has been cut open."></p>
<figcaption>Some minor surgery later and we have a USB powered fan!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I could now plug all five rack fans (three intake, two exhaust) directly into a new and smaller power brick, courtesy of some USB-to-outlet adapters to help further compress the size.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/power_brick.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A small Anker power brick with three standard outlets on the front, two of which have USB-to-outlet adapters plugged in, and each adapter has two USB ports. With two additional USB ports in the back, there are six USB outlets on the brick to power the five USB fans, and one standard outlet to power the PoE 8-port switch."></p>
<figcaption>There are two more USB outlets in the back of the brick.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>All that was left at this point was to reassemble the Pi cluster. As I said, I was surprised by the sturdiness of six Pi boards with PoE HATs:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/full_cluster.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The reassembled Pi cluster, with six Raspberry Pi boards stacked up, each with a PoE HAT."></p>
<figcaption>Behold this fully armed and operational Pi cluster.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It took several days’ worth of spare time to get everything together, but I’m proud to say that when I plugged the power brick into the wall, <em>every</em> single light and fan turned on all at once.</p>
<p>It was beautiful.</p>
<p>And mere minutes after, our Mastodon instance was back up and running, too! No commands or instructions needed on my part. Which is, frankly, impressive: as complex as kubernetes is, and as difficult as it can be to stand up applications in it, it’s remarkably robust once you’ve got it up and running.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next Steps</h3>
<p>I’ll probably just enjoy this for a bit 😀</p>
<p>But later, I’ll upgrade Mastodon again. On the hardware end, I don’t really have any additional ideas for the moment! Longer term, though, I have plans to move the Pi cluster into an <em>actual</em> homelab server rack (along with our home NAS, a full-sized home server, and all the networking equipment we have currently lying on the floor).</p>
<p>But that’s for another time 👋</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Upgrading the {Raspberry} {Pi} {Cluster}},
  date = {2023-07-10},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Upgrading the Raspberry Pi Cluster.”</span>
July 10, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster">https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>kubernetes</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <category>hardware</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 21:52:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/setup.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This post is about burnout</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/burnout.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Midjourney-generated image of an art easel with a picture of a raging fire, anthropomorphized with a giant smile on its face. Meant to convey a ham-fisted 'this is fine' metaphor."></p>
<p>…but before I get to that, I want to talk about a movie I saw recently and a book I read recently.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Caution
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The following section contains some minor character spoilers from the 2023 film <em>Spider-Man: Across the Spider-Verse</em>. No major plot reveals.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>My wife and I were recently able to see an evening showing of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spider-Man%3A_Across_the_Spider-Verse"><em>Across the Spider-Verse</em></a>. It was phenomenal; we loved it. As someone who stuck with the MCU movies a little longer than most of my friends, I’ve been feeling “meh” toward superhero flicks for about a year now. We haven’t seen the newest <em>Black Panther</em>, <em>Ant-Man</em>, nor <em>Guardians</em> movies, nor have we felt an overriding urge to watch them even when they hit streaming (though I’ve heard the <em>Guardians</em> movie is pretty solid, so that may be the exception. Maybe).</p>
<p>The <em>Spider-Verse</em> movies, even though solidly in the superhero genre, have been universally incredible. Possibly helped by the fact that there’s only two of them, with the third due out in March 2024. The animation is beautiful, the writing is top-notch, the humor is subtle and perfectly timed, and the characters are <em>fantastic</em>. I loved how this movie dove more into Gwen’s own background, and I was particularly pulled in by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spider-Man_2099">Spider-Man 2099</a>.</p>
<p>He’s a relectant hero (like all the Spiders), doing what he thinks is right, ultimately trying to prevent what happened to him (which was terrible, even by the generic Spider-Trauma Barometer™️) from happening to anyone else.</p>
<p>Except… he fought too hard for too long. Even surrounded by others, he isolated himself. He made hard decisions, and bit by bit the consequences of those decisions ate him up. He stared into the abyss, and the abyss eventually took up residence. He lost sight of <em>why</em> he started his work in the first place—when you have to repeat “We’re the good guys!” twice in a row, practically shouting it at your subordinates, one has to ask who it is you’re trying to convince—and became the very thing he ostensibly started out fighting against.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Caution
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The following section contains some minor character spoilers from the 2023 novel <em>The Frugal Wizard’s Handbook For Surviving Medieval England</em>. No major plot reveals.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>I also just devoured the latest Brandon Sanderson book, <em>The Frugal Wizard’s Handbook For Surviving Medieval England</em>, which was officially called “Secret Project #2” for most of the past 12 months since his big 2022 Kickstarter. It’s not part of any of Sanderson’s other established universes, so it’s a wonderful standalone novel about a near-future dimension-hopping guy who loses his memories upon arriving in an unknown dimension set in Medieval England. He has to figure out who he is and why he’s in that dimension, as others—both natives of the dimension, and people from his own—are trying to kill him.</p>
<p>I loved the story because, while it had many familiar beats storytelling beats around a journey of self-discovery, its final conceit and ultimate reveal about the character had a surprising amount of depth.</p>
<p>Ultimately, it was a story of a character who’d had a lot of bad breaks in his life, coupled with a few poor decisions, which culminated in internalizing the belief that <em>he was not deserving</em>. When he inevitably failed, he believed he deserved it. His well-meaning “friends” gave him the usual “you need to try harder, good things come to those who try.” Which of course is strictly true, but leaves out important context: when you’ve had a string of failures, either from bad decisions OR simple bad luck—or most realistically, some ugly combination of both—you start internalizing those failures <em>as the default mode</em>.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You lose a little—and that makes you wonder if you deserve to lose. So you lose some more. And it all compounds. You’re behind, no matter how you scramble to stop it. You’re too far gone.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The memory loss ends up being a godsend, because by the end—when the main character has regained his memories—he can compare himself to someone who, just days before, took action he believed was right <em>without the mental baggage of failure as the default</em>, and for that very reason ended up winning more often than he lost.</p>
<p>But the critial discovery, to me at least, was that belief in oneself does not exist in vacuum. You don’t necessarily believe in yourself because you woke up one morning and made the decision. You also look (through the lens of your own experience) at your wins and losses in the past, and use that assessment to decide <em>whether or not you’re worth believing in</em>. And that self-assessment can be brutal; it can end up digging a hole that is nigh impossible to get out of, perpetuating failure.</p>
<section id="where-theres-smoke" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-theres-smoke">Where there’s smoke…</h3>
<p>In January 2015, I started a tenure-track position at the University of Georgia. In August 2021, I was officially promoted to Associate Professor, with tenure. And by early 2022, I was convinced that I needed to leave academia entirely, a sentiment that has not changed since then.</p>
<p>Why leave? For those reasons and all the parts of that thinking that led here, I’ll have a post later. Maybe. I’ve been working on a version of it for nearly two years now, but I’m not yet sure if it will see the light of day. It may just be for me.</p>
<p>For now, the reason is simple: I’m completely and utterly, spiritually and physically and emotionally, so-far-beyond-the-abyss, <strong>burned out</strong>.</p>
<p>Of course, the reasons why the burnout got so bad are legion, and I will concede that many of those reasons are my own fault:</p>
<ul>
<li>I have a hard time asking for help</li>
<li>I enjoy what I do to the extent of saying “yes” to things that sound exciting (everything sounds exciting!) without considering how it will get done</li>
<li>I’ve always been somewhat of a people-pleaser, and so setting hard boundaries is difficult and exhausting, and it’s easier (in the short-term) to give people what they want</li>
</ul>
<p>This has led to a situation where I’ve begun to expect failure as a rule. Not with scientific experiments or with code development—that’s wholly different (at least in my brain), and that’s not what I’m talking about here; if anything, my lab’s science has been one of the bright spots in all this—but rather, interacting with people: I expect that I’ll disappoint them somehow, which becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy because it’s happened <em>so often</em> in the last few years.</p>
<p>And it happened because I was so severely burned out that I could barely function. I mentioned this in my <a href="../../posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/index.html">new year’s post</a>, though not really the full extent of it. Honestly, I’m not sure what its full extent is. If I take a really close look at the contours, I may have been burned out since early 2019, shortly after receiving my NSF CAREER award notice. I’ve been hobbling along ever since.</p>
<p>This burnout led to anger and resentment, and a feeling of having to single-handedly hold things together: that I was the only one competent enough to do what needed to be done. Inevitably, balls were dropped—because this is not a sustainable approach to literally anything—and the failures mounted, leading to feelings of nihilism and anhedonia.</p>
<p>This went on for years. I stared into the abyss for far too long, and when I had a chance to step back, I did not like the person I was becoming. We’re so far beyond schedule tweaks, productivity hacks, and “write for 30 minutes each day”; we’re well into “I need an entire semester, possibly an entire academic year, off, just to begin the healing process in earnest.”</p>
<p>And yes, that’s ostensibly what sabbaticals are there for. But in a final might-be-hilarious-in-10-years power move, I’ve been denied to even submit a <em>request</em> for a sabbatical because “there’s no one else to teach the class you’ve been assigned for the fall, and there are already 40+ students registered.”</p>
<p>Somewhere around this time in 2022, while I was working for Quansight, I was given the opportunity to do a 3-day online training in PyTorch for a client. In classic “me” fashion, I enthusiastically volunteered. But when the day came, I was so stressed out by the idea of teaching—a primary source of my burnout—that I broke out in <em>full-body hives</em>. That has happened to me only once before, though in that case we traced it to what was most likely improperly cooked shellfish.</p>
</section>
<section id="embrace-the-process" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="embrace-the-process">Embrace the process</h3>
<p><em>Recognizing</em> burnout is important. <em>Counteracting</em> burnout is important. Both of these steps are difficult to ascertain and implement. This blog post about <a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2023/05/the-python-language-summit-2023-burnout.html">burnout among core Python package maintainers</a> addresses some of that. But there’s a third burnout thread I have to constantly remind myself of:</p>
<p>Burnout decimates your physical and mental capabilities, and they don’t return overnight. It’s such a kick in the teeth when just recognizing burnout is so challenging, and moreso to stem the tide, but just because these have been done does not mean life immediately snaps back to normal.</p>
<p>I’ve spent the last couple years wondering why running seems so much harder than it used to be, while running so much slower than I used to. I spent the day after the SciPy 2023 paper submission deadline (just this past Friday evening) kicking myself for not getting the paper done and feeling like a failure because of it. Years ago, debugging Python and PyTorch errors was straightforward, and prototyping machine learning models was relatively easy for me; while writing this paper, every error message was a multi-hour-long block on my progress. Working through them was like wading through molassess, and at the time I couldn’t understand why.</p>
<p>It’s because burnout doesn’t vanish overnight. It impedes your faculties, like sand in joints, simultaneously slowing things down and increasing the resistence. The knee-jerk reaction is to push harder, which flares the burnout and ultimately undoes forward progress. Which feeds into the failure mindset, and thus perpetuates the cycle.</p>
</section>
<section id="not-just-surviving-but-thriving" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-just-surviving-but-thriving">Not just surviving, but thriving</h3>
<p>I’ve been in survival mode for years now, just trying to get through each day and not really seeing more than a week or two ahead. It’s a good way to stay alive, but a terrible way to live. I’ve gone through long stretches where I have no motivation to create, or to learn, or to grow; instead, all my energy is focused exclusively on getting from one day to the next.</p>
<p>I don’t want to simply survive, I want to <em>thrive</em>. I want to build, I want to learn, I want to grow. And as has become very clear over the past few years: <em>that won’t happen for me if I stay in academia</em>. I haven’t been able to make it work, and I’ve been at this for almost 9 years now. I’ve said it jokingly for years, but it’s also the hard truth: academia is a pie-eating contest where the prize is more pie.</p>
<p><strong>So, I’m leaving</strong>. It suffices to say that by prioritizing healing from my burnout, and by extension prioritizing my family and friends and personal interests and hobbies, it is clear beyond any doubt that there is simply no viable universe in which these priorities can be met while remaining in academia. Of course, I’m existentially terrified—who leaves a tenured position for industry?!—but I’m also excited by the mere possibility of thriving.</p>
<p>Burnout recovery is going to take awhile; after all, I spent years getting to this point. But I’ve also spent the better part of the last few months starting the recovery process, and there’s already been noticeable improvement. I have sustainable routines in place that are clearly doing me good, but I can’t make some of the biggest changes while I’m still in academia.</p>
<p>I’ve recognized my burnout, and I’m taking every step I can to make the changes I need to thrive. But I have to keep reminding myself that things won’t improve overnight, even when I’m doing everything right. It’ll take some time for the pea soup in my brain to clear out, and it’s been an agonizingly slow process of rebuiding my physical body (not helped by potential long COVID symptoms, but that’s a post for another day).</p>
<p>But I at least want the <em>chance</em> to thrive. So I’m taking it. Wish me luck.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {This Post Is about Burnout},
  date = {2023-06-06},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-06-05-this-post-is-about-burnout},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“This Post Is about Burnout.”</span> June 6,
2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-06-05-this-post-is-about-burnout">https://magsol.github.io/2023-06-05-this-post-is-about-burnout</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>burnout</category>
  <category>movies</category>
  <category>books</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 22:05:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/burnout.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My thoughts ahead of Tears of the Kingdom</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/totk_poster.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Official Nintendo poster for The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom."></p>
<p>For those who aren’t following the <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/@daysuntil">increasingly unhinged ravings of my countdown bot on Mastodon</a>, <em>The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</em> is coming out on Friday, May 12.</p>
<p>And for those who’ve only heard in passing–or who have perhaps never heard–of the Zelda video game franchise: its latest installment is coming out this Friday, May 12, and the Zelda community is absolutely <em>giddy</em> with anticipation.</p>
<p>I could wax historical over its 35 years and 20 different games spanning nearly a dozen (more than a dozen?!) different Nintendo consoles; I could swoon over its cultural impact, influencing other genres and changing, perhaps even unknowingly to many people, how game and puzzle creators approach their design; I could go on about the record-shattering success of its predecessor from 2017, <em>Breath of the Wild</em>, and how this is only the second time in the history of the franchise that Nintendo has made a direct sequel to a previous game; and I could blather on <strong>for.ev.er.</strong> on the established Zelda lore and all the branching theories that its rich storytelling has spawned.</p>
<p>But instead of doing any of that, I just want to put forward one small hope for the game: <strong>I really hope that the game opens with a playable Link getting the absolute snot beat out of him by Ganondorf.</strong></p>
<section id="personally-guide-link-to-his-near-demise" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personally-guide-link-to-his-near-demise">Personally guide Link to his near-demise</h3>
<p>From the trailers, we know the game starts with our eponymous heroes stumbling upon Ganondorf, and something happens where they get separated, Link is grievously injured, and the Master Sword is damaged; <a href="https://youtu.be/uHGShqcAHlQ?t=177">here’s the part of the latest trailer where it happens</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s the relevant screenshot of it happening:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/link_injured.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Screen capture from the latest trailer where Ganondorf's malice is damaging the Master Sword and injuring Link."></p>
<figcaption>This should literally not be possible.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s horrifying on multiple fronts. We know it happens sometime near the very beginning of the game (setting the stage for the whole thing), and we also know—one small tidbit of Zelda lore—that it <em>should not be in any way possible for the Master Sword to be damaged by evil. It just shouldn’t.</em> So the fact that it <em>is</em>, is truly terrifying on its own.</p>
<p>But here’s where I’m hoping the game takes it up one more notch: I’m hoping that part at the beginning, where the questing heroes find Ganondorf and get their asses kicked, is <strong>fully playable</strong>.</p>
<p>There’s precedent for this, in fact it’s happened in at least a few games I’ve played, going back almost 20 years!</p>
<section id="quake-4-2005" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quake-4-2005">Quake 4 (2005)</h4>
<p>You play the part of a space marine from Earth tasked with helping push back an alien invasion. For most of the first part of the game, you’re working with your unit to sabotage one of the main “conduits” of the alien military that allows them to communicate and coordinate with each other. You’re eventually successful, but right after, a big bad thought killed in Quake 2 suddenly appears—very clearly alive—and you have to fight him.</p>
<p>You lose. You’re guaranteed to lose. But you still have to fight him. Not only that, but you have to stay alive just long enough to see how every strategy you’ve deployed up until this point fails in spectacular fashion. You can’t even dent the guy’s armor.</p>
<p>Of course, what follows is a long cutscene involving a partial assimilation… it’s a neat sequence, but it requires a bit of a, uh, “constitution” for gore.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/quake4_makron.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="First-person screenshot of the first Makron fight from Quake 4."></p>
<figcaption>The Makron, from the player’s perspective.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="jedi-outcast-2003" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="jedi-outcast-2003">Jedi Outcast (2003)</h4>
<p>You play the role of Kyle Katarn, a mercenary-turned-jedi-turned-mercenary-again. In the pre-sequel-trilogy world, he’s actually the guy who stole the Death Star plans and got them to the Rebellion (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars%3A_Dark_Forces"><em>Dark Forces</em></a>). In the next game (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars_Jedi_Knight:_Dark_Forces_II"><em>Dark Forces II: Jedi Knight</em></a>), Kyle discovers he’s force-sensitive and trains to become a Jedi. In doing so, he brushes so close to the dark side that he instead chooses to cut himself off from the Force entirely.</p>
<p>That’s where 2003’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars_Jedi_Knight_II:_Jedi_Outcast"><em>Jedi Outcast</em></a> picks up: he’s back to being a mercenary. One of his missions puts him in an Imperial research lab that appears to be trying to infuse objects with Force energy (think Force batteries). At the end of the mission, he runs headfirst into the Dark Jedi masterminding the whole thing, Desann.</p>
<p>Desann promptly takes his partner hostage, and when Kyle threatens him with a blaster, Desann fires up his lightsaber and dares Kyle to take his partner back. That cues up a fully-playable fight.</p>
<p>I mean, Kyle is a tried-and-true mercenary and at this point in the game has a pretty decent arsenal, too. But the fight is an absolute joke. Energy weapons? Desann just deflects with his lightsaber. Projectile weapons? He Force Pushes backwards and away from him. And explosives? He levitates back towards you. I don’t think it’s actually possible to land a single hit, but you still have to try, just so you can see how woefully inadequate you are when you bring a blaster to a fight with a fully-trained Dark Jedi.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/jedioutcast_kylevdesann.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Kyle versus Desann digital art, both characters locking lightsabers. Credit to [DeviantArt user wienernose](https://www.deviantart.com/wienernose/art/Kyle-Katarn-vs-Desann-758186366)."></p>
<figcaption>An artist’s depiction of the fight at the end of the game, where you actually stand a chance of winning.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="all-i-ask" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="all-i-ask">All I ask</h3>
<p>That’s what I’m hoping for from <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>: a chance to bring everything we stocked up from <em>Breath of the Wild</em> to the opening fight against Ganondorf, and to lose badly in spite of it all, driving home just how much badder this baddie is than the one we faced at the end of the previous game.</p>
<p>It’s hard to oversell just how overpowered Link was by the very end of <em>Breath of the Wild</em> (assuming your play style leans more toward Completionist than Speedrunner, of course); bringing all that might to bear as <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> kicks off and seeing it just break like waves on the surf would be one hell of an opener.</p>
<p>It’d also be a cool bonus if our last completed <em>Breath of the Wild</em> game slotted into a new <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> game so we started with exactly the same equipment, but I’m not married to that one.</p>
</section>
<section id="oh-and" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="oh-and">Oh, and</h3>
<p>Speaking just for myself: <em>Breath of the Wild</em> was a singularly amazing game, reminding me how much I love to explore and create just for the sake of exploring and creating (not just in video games, either). At the end of the day, I truly don’t care if the opening fight is playable or not. If the Nintendo team can bring that same wonder, that same reward for simple curiosity—kicking over that last rock just for the sake of seeing what’s underneath—then I’ll happily sink another [REDACTED] hours into it.</p>
<p>THREE. MORE. DAYS.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {My Thoughts Ahead of {\_Tears} of the {Kingdom\_}},
  date = {2023-05-09},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“My Thoughts Ahead of _Tears of the
Kingdom_.”</span> May 9, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk">https://magsol.github.io/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>gaming</category>
  <category>zelda</category>
  <category>totk</category>
  <category>tears of the kingdom</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 16:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/totk_poster.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Three years later</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/forsyth_park.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Head-on view of the middle of Forsyth Park in Savannah, GA, including the fountain in the middle and trees along both sides of the main walkway."></p>
<p>Oh by the way, I have a second blog.</p>
<p>Like this one, it fell into disuse over the past few years. And like this one, I’ve been trying to revive it recently. I’d always intended for that blog and this one to be completely non-overlapping in their respective content, but life, as they say, finds a way.</p>
<p>(Me. I’m talking about me, here. Of course the blog isn’t alive, jeez.)</p>
<p>At any rate, you most likely won’t see me advertise that blog here ever again, but just this once, I wanted to point to a post I made detailing my half marathon this past weekend in Savannah, GA, and the three-year history that particular event has.</p>
<p><a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/04/03/three-years-later/">Here’s the link</a>. Enjoy.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Three Years Later},
  date = {2023-04-04},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-04-04-three-years-later},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Three Years Later.”</span> April 4, 2023.
<a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-04-04-three-years-later">https://magsol.github.io/2023-04-04-three-years-later</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>running</category>
  <category>covid</category>
  <category>pandemic</category>
  <category>getaway</category>
  <category>travel</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 16:10:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/forsyth_park.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon: Conclusions, musings, ramblings, ravings</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/numenor.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Aerial view of an ancient but advanced civilization, an island-nation (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html">Part V: Actually installing Mastodon</a></li>
<li>Conclusions <em>(this post)</em></li>
</ol>
<p>I know what you’re thinking:</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-94586"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/dexhorthy\/status\/856639005462417409","author_name":"dex","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/dexhorthy","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EDeployed my blog on Kubernetes \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/XHXWLrmYO4\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/XHXWLrmYO4\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; dex (@dexhorthy) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/dexhorthy\/status\/856639005462417409?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EApril 24, 2017\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-94586").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>And honestly… you’re not wrong.</p>
<section id="running-mastodon-has-gotten-easier" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="running-mastodon-has-gotten-easier">Running Mastodon has gotten easier</h3>
<p>In the time I spent planning and writing this blog post series, many of the issues and bugs I ran into already have official fixes (I’ve tried to note PRs, whether merged or still open, where relevant throughout the series). The biggest news of note came down just late last week: <a href="https://blog.bitnami.com/2023/02/bitnami-arm-containers-available-at.html">Bitnami’s images on DockerHub now universally support ARM</a>, making practically the entirety of <a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III</a> obsolete.</p>
<p>There are also discussions (perhaps only internally?) around refactoring the Helm chart to pull the prerequisites out entirely, refocusing instead on Mastodon itself.</p>
</section>
<section id="joining-mastodon-has-gotten-easier" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="joining-mastodon-has-gotten-easier">Joining Mastodon has gotten easier</h3>
<p>And honestly, it’s not like there’s a huge crowd of folks looking to run their own Mastodon instances, especially not with such a rich landscape of instances already up and running.</p>
<p>Granted, there doesn’t really seem to be a unified way of <em>finding</em> an interesting instance; that particular aspect of diving into Mastodon still feels very “cannot be found except by those who already know where it is.” That’s a bit orthogonal to the blog series—especially since I set up my own instance not because I couldn’t find what I was looking for, but because I just wanted to see if I could—but still an ongoing consideration.</p>
</section>
<section id="other-notes-on-the-process" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-notes-on-the-process">Other notes on the process</h3>
<p>I do want to strongly underscore <strong>how grateful I am to the Mastodon dev team for all their help through this process</strong>. I would very likely still be mired in getting search up and running without their knowledgeable, kind, and patient assistance. <a href="https://www.patreon.com/mastodon/">Go support Mastodon’s open source work and, as a bonus, receive access to their dev Discord</a>.</p>
<p>The official GitHub repository is also a wealth of information, and I cannot enumerate just how helpful it’s been since they moved the helm chart maintenance and development <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/">into its own repository</a>, separate from the <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/">main Mastodon application</a>.</p>
<p>My biggest gripe with this whole process really just boils down to the complexity of kubernetes and its ecosystem. There is <em>so. much. stuff.</em> to understand to get even the most basic kubernetes applications up and running. Helm is helpful—in a way—because it hides so much of this complexity, but this becomes a double-edged sword when <em>invariably</em> something isn’t working quite right. Frankly, with the lone exception of the <a href="https://github.com/kubernetes-sigs/nfs-subdir-external-provisioner">NFS provisioner</a> I use for storage in kubernetes applications, I have yet to install an application via Helm that <em>didn’t</em> also require diving into the <code>values.yaml</code> and backend templates to figure out what was <em>really</em> going on.</p>
<p>Unfortunately I don’t have an easy answer, either. For someone well-versed in kubernetes and its ecosystem, this whole process probably would have taken a day; for me, it took a month. I’m ok with that, because I learned a lot from the process of doing it myself, but I’m also more cognizant now of just how much I still don’t know about kubernetes.</p>
<p>Until this unfathomably steep learning curve is smoothed out a little, I feel that it’s incumbent upon us who’ve dabbled somewhat in kubernetes to help lift up the folks coming behind us. Hence this blog series!</p>
</section>
<section id="final-final-notes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-final-notes">Final, final notes</h3>
<p>Is there anything I missed? Anything that isn’t clear? Please feel free to drop a comment on this post or any of the previous ones if you have some additional thoughts on the topics.</p>
<p>I’ve also gone back and added links to all the posts in the series to all the other posts in this series, so you won’t have to click through sequentially to see them all.</p>
<p>I really enjoyed putting this series together, and I already have some ideas for similar undertakings, both within and without the world of kubernetes (perhaps I’ll finally have a blog series around something ML and/or CV related, zomg). Until then!</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon: {Conclusions,} Musings, Ramblings, Ravings},
  date = {2023-02-28},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon: Conclusions, Musings, Ramblings,
Ravings.”</span> February 28, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions">https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 09:52:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/numenor.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon, Part V: Installing and configuring Mastodon</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/mastodon_crew.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Close-up of two Mastodon-like sailors on the deck of a ship at sea (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li>Part V: Actually installing Mastodon <em>(this post)</em></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">Conclusions</a></li>
</ol>
<p>Heyyy, we’ve finally arrived! Months and multiple blog posts later, here’s how to actually install a Mastodon instance on your k3s cluster of Raspberry Pi computers!</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">helm</span> dep update</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">helm</span> install mastodon ./ <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--create-namespace</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--namespace</span> mastodon <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-f</span> path/to/custom/values.yaml</span></code></pre></div>
<p>The <code>dep update</code> will pull down any new versions of the Bitnami charts needed to install the prerequisites we went over in <a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III</a>.</p>
<p>The <code>install</code> command creates an application called <code>mastodon</code>, using the templates in the current directory (hence <code>./</code>), creates a new k3s namespace named <code>mastodon</code> for all the pods to occupy, and then the <code>-f</code> flag provides a path to the <code>values.yaml</code> file we customized back in <a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II</a>.</p>
<section id="is-that-it" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="is-that-it">Is that it?</h3>
<p>A lot of things are going to happen at this point.</p>
<p>First, there a couple of pods that will appear as one-time “jobs”, the most notable (to me) of which is the <code>precompile</code> pod. This one in particular <em>can take awhile</em>… or maybe it was just because it was running on little Raspberry Pi SBCs; the 4Bs are certainly fast, but they’re still pretty resource-constrained by workstation or server standards, so be patient here. Just because it’s taking awhile for anything to show up doesn’t mean something is wrong.</p>
<p>Second, there is a db-migrate job that kicks off. Despite the name, this actually happens both if you’re migrating <em>and</em> if you’re installing Mastodon for the first time. For some reason, there’s a race condition among these initial one-time pods, and if the db-migrate job doesn’t kick off right when it’s supposed to, it may never happen; there’s <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/18">an open ticket looking at this problem</a> and a <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/pull/37">PR with a proposed fix that hasn’t yet been merged</a>. It’s something to keep an eye on; there are manual fixes specified in the open issue (basically the pod equivalent of turn-off-and-back-on) that I had to employ at least a couple of times.</p>
<p>Finally, there was an issue with sidekiq not properly registering the ingress task–kind of important for an application that relies heavily on ingress activity! But it required a very simple one-line addition to the <code>values.yaml</code> file, and it’s not even an issue anymore since <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/pull/1">this PR was merged</a> back in early December 2022.</p>
</section>
<section id="yep-thats-it" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="yep-thats-it">Yep, that’s it</h3>
<p>And that’s pretty much it! You should have a shiny new Mastodon instance up and running at this point (hit the ingress endpoint to check it out)! Your work as instance administrator is only just beginning, though–you need to check out all the options you have available in terms of setting up and configuring your instance (creating its welcome message and purpose, setting up how new accounts register, and importing any new emojis you might want), but in terms of command line kubernetes, with the exception of continued maintenance and occasional updates, that’s it!</p>
<p>I’ll have a wrap-up post coming soon with more of my own thoughts on the whole process.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon, {Part} {V:} {Installing} and Configuring
    {Mastodon}},
  date = {2023-02-24},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon, Part V: Installing and
Configuring Mastodon.”</span> February 24, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon">https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 17:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/mastodon_crew.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
