<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Stochastic Stenography</title>
<link>https://magsol.github.io/</link>
<atom:link href="https://magsol.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Data, donuts, and detours</description>
<image>
<url>https://magsol.github.io/images/logo.png</url>
<title>Stochastic Stenography</title>
<link>https://magsol.github.io/</link>
<height>144</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.8.25</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 10:55:13 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>An Ode to UGA</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/nameplate.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="My UGA nameplate, which hung outside my Boyd office. It says School of Computing, University of Georgia. Shannon Quinn, PhD. Associate Professor."></p>
<section id="the-mid-aughts" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-mid-aughts">The Mid-Aughts</h3>
<p>I still remember it vividly. I was in Cleveland, Ohio, driving to or from something wedding related, as it was April 4, 2014—the day before Cathryn and I got married. I had my phone on me, and like it did a lot that weekend, it started ringing. But it was a 706 number I didn’t recognize. Uncharacteristically, I pulled off into a parking lot (normally I just let calls roll to voicemail… even when I’m just sitting at home<sup>1</sup>) and answered. It was none other than the Computer Science department head at UGA, offering me the job of Assistant Professor with joint appointments in Computer Science and Cellular Biology!</p>
<p>I don’t remember exactly when I told Cathryn the news (it was sometime over the wedding weekend), but I <em>do</em> remember that, at the time, I told the department head I needed a week to consider it, as I was literally about to get married and was then immediately jetting off to an island without cell service for my honeymoon. Suffice to say I accepted, but that made for an added element of excitement to an already electrified weekend.</p>
</section>
<section id="present-day" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="present-day">Present Day</h3>
<p>Why then, over a decade and tenure later, did I leave UGA? Well, a lot of reasons. But that’s not the point here.</p>
<p>Sometime during the 2020 pandemic lockdowns, I opened a blank Markdown file and began writing a document that I steadily added to over the intervening years, cataloging and distilling the various reasons that I felt academia and I were not long for this world. In reading over it again for the millionth time, I’m left with this strange feeling of simultaneous inevitability and happenstance: a sort of causal superposition.</p>
<p>On one hand: of <em>course</em> I left, holy see you later Batman. On the other hand, it’s not difficult to envision permutations of universes in which I stayed; some of these universes differ from our own by a single grant decision, a single job offer, even a single day with one less fire to put out.</p>
<p>This post isn’t about why I left UGA<sup>2</sup>. It <em>is</em> a collection of complicated thoughts and feelings as I begin the process of closing the door on a place that has <em>profoundly</em> influenced the direction of every single aspect of my life. I hope you, dear reader, find some useful nugget here to take with you, but I want to be painfully blunt up front: this post is, first and foremost, for me.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/where_the_other_road_led.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>I did (also, this book is amazing).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="what-ill-miss" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-ill-miss">What I’ll miss</h3>
<p>At the risk of sounding trite, it’s not <em>what</em> I’ll miss, but <em>who</em>: the people. The people are the part of UGA I will miss the most, hands down. One can’t count on an institution to always have your back, but people are another story. In no particular ordering:</p>
<p>My Lilly Fellows cohort, and my Lilly mentor. They stoked not only my interest in teaching, but were also lovely, well-rounded people. Some became writing buddies, others gave us advice for our <a href="../../posts/2019-06-03-quinnwitz-in-ireland/index.html">2019 Ireland trip</a>.</p>
<p>The Cellular Biology department heads, past and present: Kojo, Mark, Dennis, and Jim. Multiple longtime collaborators I met through Cellular Biology: Karl, Jonathan, Silvia, and Rachel. This department came about as close as possible to making me believe that whole institutions <em>will</em> stick by you through thick and thin, because this one sure did: from Kojo intervening on my behalf with regards to teaching assignments; Jim taking me out to lunch to discuss grant proposal strategies; all of the above <em>clearly</em> whipping votes in the department’s tenure discussion. I will deeply miss Karl’s sense of humor, Jonathan’s warm and even-keeled presence, and Rachel and Silvia’s fascinating research questions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/peasant1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>I met Travis (left) and Jim (middle) at the Peasant for drinks shortly after informing them of my departure. I’ll deeply miss these two, and their leadership and vision.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The Institute of Bioinformatics leadership, Travis and Holly, who took a giant risk on me in multiple ways. They are incredible leaders with a laser-focused vision for the unit and more than enough talent to execute. They singlehandedly restored my belief that we don’t <em>necessarily always</em> rise to the level of our incompetence; sometimes we actually reach exactly where we’re meant to be, where we can do the most good. And they’re just wonderful people to boot.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/iob_retreat.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Entrance to the April 2025 IOB Retreat. This is where my mind was blown at just how effectively the IOB was run.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My research collaborators: Kyle, Russ, Nicole, Meredith, Ginger, Jason, and Michael. Lots of other folks who were at UGA but left before I did (usually to go to another university).</p>
<p>Other faculty and staff I interacted regularly with, officially or unofficially: Carl, Brad, Mica, Kimberly, Evette, and Sandra. Special shoutout to my “work wife” <a href="https://arischlesinger.com/">Ari Schlesinger</a>, who only started at UGA in the fall of 2023, but with whom I forged a quick friendship thanks to our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ygxDs_zcayo">common background</a>. I tried to be the resource for her that I wish I’d had at that career stage. She’s since become a close friend of both mine and Cathryn’s (and Z really loves her too!) so I’m optimistic we’ll stay in touch.</p>
<p><strong>But if you’re a prospective student and remotely interested in her work, reach out to her—I can’t think of a line of CS research inquiry more relevant or important right now!).</strong></p>
<p>An uncountable number of students, but <a href="https://quinngroup.github.io/people.html">this page</a> is a good place to start.</p>
<p>But most of all, and above all, I’ll miss working with my Dad.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/redandblack.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The header of the <a href="https://news.uga.edu/father-son-faculty-members-team-up-on-nsf-grant/">2016 Red and Black article</a> we appeared in when our joint research work was just beginning.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My Dad has always been a bit of a personal and professional hero of mine, and it’s no stretch to say that my journey into the tenure-track was at least <em>slightly</em> because of him. Getting not one, but <em>two</em> federal grants with him—an NSF grant in 2015 (I was a co-PI), and an NIH grant in 2021 (I was the lead PI!)—is something I’ll cherish forever. I still hold out hope that, as I grow in my new role, I’ll be able to cultivate new opportunities for external collaboration that might include my Dad.</p>
<p>I guess there is one “what” that I’ll miss: I’ll miss that STEM building office that I had for all of four months. At least at time of writing, it’s one of the newest buildings at UGA, and so the office itself (while nothing special) was just lovely. I even had a few opportunities to bring Z there a couple of summer days when we needed to kill some time, and she loved it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/stem_building.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The newest building on campus (for now). It was also right next to the IOB building.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/new_office.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>It was nothing flashy, but wow it was nice.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/z_newoffice.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>It’s always “bring your kid to your cool office” day.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="what-im-proud-of" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-im-proud-of">What I’m proud of</h3>
<p>To pick up from the previous section: my Dad and I got a handful of publications with both our names on them. Together with the two grants, and I think that’s pretty effing awesome.</p>
<p>I got a coveted <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1845915">NSF CAREER award</a>. That got me tenure, and was among the first times I could recall being paid to work on something that I had <em>created</em>, that I was <em>super</em> excited about, and which I really believed in.</p>
<p>I published in <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.aaa1233">Science</a>, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1145/2939672.2939730">KDD</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/ISBI.2018.8363732">ISBI</a> (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/ISBI.2018.8363735">twice</a>!), and even places like <a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.01983">JOSS</a> that aren’t high-impact in the traditional sense but are—or so I believe—<em>incredibly</em> valuable outlets that help make more parts of modern academia sustainable.</p>
<p>I was the chief architect of an <a href="https://www.cs.uga.edu/majors-degrees/content/data-science-bs"><em>entire undergraduate curriculum</em></a>. I’m personally not a fan of the direction it’s gone since launch, but I was really proud of the idea in principle and did my best to get it there.</p>
<p>Along those lines, I’m really proud of all the <a href="https://github.com/eds-uga/">digital classroom materials</a> I created for all the courses I taught. Which reminds me: there are private “master” repos with things like autograders, assignment keys, and other notes that I should perhaps make visible?</p>
<p>Around the same time I got my NSF CAREER, I also won a Lilly Teaching fellowship, a departmental teaching award, and a university research award.</p>
<p>I received (and still receive) messages like this one:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/student_email.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A very recent email from a former student.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>and I’ve lost count of the automated UGA emails to the effect of “a student from this semester’s graduating class identified you as someone who had an outsized impact on their development”, which is just so incredibly humbling and affirming.</p>
<p>Speaking of students, I’m <em>immensely</em> proud of everything they accomplished, especially given the circumstances under which many of them worked. Everyone’s situation is different, but the default situation of a student is <em>difficult</em>: especially graduate students, especially international students, especially students supporting themselves and/or another person, especially part-time students, especially non-traditional students, especially minority students or otherwise underprivileged students. And that’s just the baseline, the default, standard operating procedure if nothing goes <em>wrong</em>; at least a handful of my students were not so lucky. But they worked around those problems, too. I watched as students with minimal or even zero background in computing finish up as experts in their areas by the time they left; there is no single greater reward to a mentor.</p>
<p>Publications, posters, conference talks, DOIs, awards; they’re all nice, great even. But for me, I’m proudest when I see that light go on in a student’s brain, and they transition from asking me “what do I do next” to telling me “here’s what I think we should do next”.</p>
<p>We did some great work too, which admittedly I’ll miss (so I guess this should go in the previous section, at least in part) but which I’m also proud of. I spent over a decade working on analyzing ciliary motion, and loved it. It was my first-ever research project, and also my last (the NSF CAREER funded it). In addition, I worked with my Dad on studying the effects of tuberculosis on the mitochondria of lung cells (NSF and NIH grants); I also developed tracking and analysis methods to understand how toxoplasma parasites invade host cells (collaborator on an NIH grant). A project I was really excited for was to conduct a pilot study on how to introduce <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_science">Open Science</a> tools and techniques into graduate education; we even got an NSF grant for this work!</p>
<p>I’m very proud of the <a href="https://osbd.github.io/">Open Science in Big Data workshop</a> I ran for four consecutive years in conjunction with the annual IEEE BigData Conference; for four years, I pulled that off pretty much single-handedly. It gave me an excuse to invite some of my professional heroes to give keynote talks, and as a result I’m still in contact with a few of them, and a few I consider friends.</p>
<p>There were myriad other projects that were one-offs, or which never quite panned out, but which contributed to my overall portfolio in some way, and for which I am grateful.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-i-started-but-didnt-finish" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-i-started-but-didnt-finish">What I started (but didn’t finish)</h3>
<p>To a certain extent, <em>everything</em> I worked on in my 10+ years at UGA would fall in this category. It’s a blessing and a curse of academia: the work is never truly done. But here are just a few that stick out to me.</p>
<p>By any metric, my NSF CAREER project was a rousing success, except for one stated objective: I was never able to fully reveal quantitative definitions for previously-unknown ciliary motion phenotypes, nor was I able to observe whether these phenotypes provided any insights into the specific underlying pathologies. Imagine: diagnosing ciliopathies by simply watching how cilia move! I really think the hypothesis is a good one, but I wasn’t able to close this circle, mostly due to a combination of 1) lack of data that was high enough resolution, and 2) just not enough time (the 2020 pandemic lockdowns landed right smack in the middle of this project, and shut down laboratories just as we were starting to purchase materials to conduct experiments; to say this was a <em>huge freaking wrench</em> in things would be an understatement).</p>
<p>Along those lines, I’d written a few versions of a draft NIH R01 that posited a connection between the SARS-CoV-2 virus, ciliary health, and the virus’ ability to invade lung cells. It was rejected twice, but the third submission would have been a major overhaul, one which I think would have been extremely competitive: it brought in some of my <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spatial_biology">spatial biology</a> experience from my 2024 sabbatical with <a href="https://predxbio.com/">PredxBio</a>. The program officers at NIH who read it loved it. It was a genuinely exciting project, taking and building on work I was intimately familiar with and moving it in a new direction. Work on this R01 proposal even dovetailed into some semi-serious conversations with the dean of UGA’s fledgling medical school about creating a brand new research institute focused on spatial biology in medicine and collaborations with industry. I’ve no doubt someone will pick up these ideas and run with them, but I’ll always be curious as to how they would’ve turned out had I been the one to execute.</p>
<p>I also feel as though we weren’t able to get out of the prototype stage in the collaboration with my Dad. The reasons for this are complicated (read: the source of a great deal of acute anger<sup>3</sup>), but suffice to say we were dramatically and unexpectedly under-resourced. We did the best we could with what we had and still accomplished some fascinating things. But we’d hoped to use what we built to scale up into a full genome screen of the tuberculosis pathogen and identify genes that contributed to its ability to shut down host cell defenses. Sadly, we never reached that point. Nevertheless, we accomplished enough that, again, I’ve no doubt someone will pick up the pieces and run with them.</p>
<p>The 2020 pandemic and subsequent lockdowns changed <em>a lot</em>, and projects-in-progress were no exception. A big casualty was that NSF project on Open Science in graduate education: we’d planned, submitted a proposal, and received funding to 1) recruit a variety of graduate students into our cohort, 2) organize multiple activities and workshops <em>each year</em>, and 3) collaborate with folks at <a href="https://cyverse.org/">CyVerse</a>, <a href="https://carpentries.org/">The Carpentries</a>, and even cohorts at UNC Chapel Hill and Penn State. Very little of that actually happened, as in-person arrangements were pretty much a non-starter for an entire calendar year: the lockdowns began in March, and this project was officially awarded <em>the very next month</em> in April. We did the best we could in subsequent years, but it was a shadow of what we’d originally hoped for it to be.</p>
<p>I have an entire section at the end of my academic CV dedicated to opportunities that were canceled due to COVID. A really big one: I was offered a 1-year role at NIH in their “Data Scholar” cohort. I had to turn it down; I won’t go into specifics, but suffice to say COVID killed this 2020/2021 opportunity to take an immediate sabbatical and work on something fascinating. Who knows how my trajectory may have shifted.</p>
<p>A very recent unfinished task was the design and proposal of a brand-new undergraduate degree: “Applied Computational Sciences.” This was pretty much the first thing IOB wanted me to tackle in moving to their unit, given my experience with building the BS in Data Science. Granted, in that previous role, I was merely a single committee member (even though I personally authored most of what was approved); this time, though, I was the actual Chair and lead of the initiative. I was incredibly excited, not just because I love anything interdisciplinary, but also because I saw this as a chance to actually do what I’d originally hoped for Data Science to be: a truly interdisciplinary computing degree that teaches the domain first and the tools second. But I left before I could finish the preliminary groundwork and data gathering required of new degree proposals.</p>
<p>Teaching in general felt very unfinished. As part of my Lilly fellowship, I’d hoped to convert all my classes to a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flipped_classroom">flipped</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ungrading">ungraded</a> format. That… didn’t happen. Partly because the pandemic crashed down very shortly after my fellowship, but also because I simply had too much teaching; surviving trumped thriving.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/last_class.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>I took this picture after I finished teaching on the last day of Spring 2025 classes. It was a gorgeous day, but ended up being prescient as it was also my actual <em>last</em> day of teaching.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="what-id-hoped-and-still-hope" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-id-hoped-and-still-hope">What I’d hoped (and still hope)</h3>
<p>While he was interviewing me, my now-supervisor mentioned that he was intrigued by the professional goals on my resume. To paraphrase, they more or less amount to: “I love building things, I love building useful things for real people, and I love growing.” Those, in a nutshell, are what I’d hoped for at UGA. And, to be completely fair, I did a good amount of all three.</p>
<p>I also believe I’ve gotten most of what I can out of UGA, so the path to continuing to do these things is elsewhere.</p>
<p>But there are still plenty of meaningful and important and critical things to be done at UGA, and universities everywhere. They need serious, thoughtful people to do them. It is my sincerest hope that these institutions, and the people who make them what they are, continue to grow and develop their strengths and talents in the best interest of the greater collective humanity.</p>
</section>
<section id="three-people" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="three-people">Three people</h3>
<p>I don’t remember now where I came across this, but it struck me at the time as important enough to write down:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>List 3 people that got you where you are today in your career. Then, list 3 people where you may have been that person for them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>For the first part, this is easy:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>My Dad</strong>. He’s been one of my role models for decades; in this case, someone I got to talk science with (both informally, and on actual projects), and who also helped me navigate the trenches of tenure track at UGA. I wouldn’t have even known what questions to ask or to whom without him.</li>
<li><strong>Merrick Furst</strong>, a <a href="https://www.cc.gatech.edu/people/merrick-furst">professor at Georgia Tech</a>. He’s been a mentor and friend ever since he and I were on the same summer 2007 study abroad in Barcelona, Spain. His experiences with and insights into the overlap of industry and academia really helped me to cut through the crap when it came to figuring out what I wanted.</li>
<li><strong>Chakra Chennubhotla</strong>, my PhD advisor and the co-founder of PredxBio. He created an incredibly rich environment for me to work as a graduate student, encouraging my interests and keeping me engaged through sheer joy. At PredxBio, <a href="https://www.csb.pitt.edu/2025/09/23/chief-of-ai-at-predxbio-explains-how-to-launch-a-career-in-bioimaging/">he built a company</a> that was my most enjoyable work experience in a decade.</li>
</ol>
<p>I truly do not know where my career would be, or what kind of person I would be, without any one of these individuals. I certainly would never have even had the opportunity to work for UGA, or anything that has since followed.</p>
<p>As for the second part, I’m not going to speculate publicly. But I’d like to think I’ve been that person for at least one of my former students; that’s the singular joy of any faculty.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/boyd.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>This was the first sight that greeted me every morning for a decade.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/boyd_office.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A lot of good work happened here: this was my office until May 2025.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/last_day.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>And this is the last look I had of my STEM office before closing the door for the last time on August 15, 2025.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next">“What’s next?”</h3>
<p>On a meta note: the precise timing of this blog post isn’t coincidental. As of today, I’ve 1) fully paid off my student loans that I started taking for grad school in 2008 and which topped out at over $100k<sup>4</sup>, and 2) submitted the final, closing report for my NSF CAREER grant, officially the last UGA and academic obligation I had remaining. So this post <em>really is</em> “the end.”</p>
<p>In case there are any <em>West Wing</em> fans here:</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jy8_lYNAKbU" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Will I ever come back to UGA, or academia in general? I don’t know! I do already have a guest speaker talk scheduled at UGA for Monday, October 13: I’ll be talking to a group of undergraduate neuroscience students about career paths! So I suppose, in some sense, I’ll be returning shortly! If only for an hour :)</p>
<p><em>Would</em> I ever come back? I don’t know that, either. I do know that I am <em>loving</em> my current role with Valo and don’t foresee making any changes for some time; the rhythms and routines of this new position are exactly what I need, and the environment is precisely what I was looking for when I listed out those objectives in my resume.</p>
<p>So! With all that, I’d simply like to say: thank you for 10+ years, UGA. Here’s where we part ways, but hopefully we’re both leaving richer and more fulfilled for having spent that time together. I know I am.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/fiercesky1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>What’s next?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Like <a href="https://blueypedia.fandom.com/wiki/Maynard">Maynard</a> said: “I used to have a phone, but people kept ringing me!”↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Insofar as it won’t be, colloquially, an “airing of grievances.”↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I don’t want to sully this post with perceived slights, so if you’re curious feel free to ask.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>There’s a slight caveat here: I <em>should</em> have been eligible for roughly $15k of that to be forgiven through the PSLF program. Of course I didn’t get my act together soon enough, and the, ah, <em>current administration</em> disqualified me on a technicality. So I just paid the fucker off. Bootstraps and all that, isn’t that right?↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2025,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {An {Ode} to {UGA}},
  date = {2025-10-01},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2025. <span>“An Ode to UGA.”</span> October 1, 2025. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga">https://magsol.github.io/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>academia</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>mentoring</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 10:55:13 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-10-01-an-ode-to-uga/pix/nameplate.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>“We’ll do our best.”</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/firefly_sunrise.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="The sun rising from the Athens Firefly trail."></p>
<p>I’m on track this calendar to read only a single Brandon Sanderson book—Secret Project 5, aka <em>Isles of the Emberdark</em> (and it was wonderful)—but with everything that has been going on this year, some of my favorite quotes, motifs, and character arcs from his books have been sticking in my neurons.</p>
<p>“Journey before destination” is certainly the biggest one, and not only because it’s the one I’ve said—many years before I’d even heard of Sanderson—should be my epitaph: <em>holy geez</em> it’s hard for me.</p>
<section id="everday-im-changin" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="everday-im-changin">Ever’day I’m changin’</h3>
<p>I’ll be honest: I’ve wanted to write this blog post for weeks but just couldn’t find a way to dislodge it from my skull. I’ve made the announcements, emptied the offices, boarded the ons, and bluntly have just been trying to keep putting one foot in front of the other while moving at about a thousand miles per hour.</p>
<p>Then NPR posted this gem: “<a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/09/12/nx-s1-5403630/signs-its-time-to-quit">7 signs it’s time to quit.</a>” (it’s a great read, and I’d highly recommend it regardless of your career circumstances)</p>
<p>Being a month removed from a full career pivot is an interesting perspective. Suffice to say, I felt intimately familiar with each of the seven signs.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Yep, been thinking of quitting since late 2020.</li>
<li>Yep, definitely wasn’t what I wanted, even though it <em>theoretically</em> was. And maybe, at one time, truly was.</li>
<li>Oh, any number of reasons here. Relevant info: I’m a recovering people-pleaser! Not hard to concoct reasons to stick around.</li>
<li>YUUUUUP.</li>
<li>Chances of success were always tiny. Felt like I’d won the lottery several times in a row up until that point; how much longer could that luck hold, really?</li>
<li>This was much more subtle than the others, but it was there, especially from my wonderful wife.</li>
<li>More than I was willing to pay, I’d realized.</li>
</ol>
<p>And while it took most of the next 5 years to make the change happen, it’s not like I fell into business-as-usual for that whole interval. Progress isn’t linear and sometimes involves backtracking.</p>
<p>But good luck convincing my head the truth of that <em>for ME</em>. Because at times I felt as though I actually <em>was</em> just settling into the status quo. Objectively, career changes involve a lot of hurry-up-and-wait<sup>1</sup>, which my brain just refuses to accept.</p>
<p>The waiting part was hard enough: waiting for relevant job postings, waiting for a response to applications, waiting for interview schedules, waiting for feedback on the interview. And then came the changes.</p>
</section>
<section id="well-folks-were-being-diverted-to-alabama" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="well-folks-were-being-diverted-to-alabama">“Well folks, we’re being diverted to Alabama”<sup>2</sup></h3>
<p>For some reason, I decided four plane trips in eight weeks was a good plan.</p>
<p>For a little context, this easily surpasses my personal records for both total flight count within a single year AND flight frequency since the pandemic, and it also rivals some of my busiest years as a graduate student (when we traveled to 3-4 out of town half and full marathons, visited both our families over holidays, and took our own trips sans kids; not to mention conferences).</p>
<p>There was SciPy 2025 in early July, which was fantastic as always. It was my first SciPy since they moved from their previous Austin, TX location to the current Tacoma, WA spot.</p>
<p>Then there was a 1-week family vacation to Colorado. Ostensibly, the purpose of the trip was to attend the wedding of one of my wife’s cousins, and that indeed was a beautiful and joyous event. But we also took a few extra days to stick around and be tourists, see the sights, hike, and even swim. A heat wave in the second half of the trip put a damper on things, but we otherwise enjoyed getting out to the mountains.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/mountains.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The Colorado mountains never disappoint.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Following that, in mid-August I took a trip to Boston for an off-site / on-site work event at my new gig’s HQ. That’s right: I got to meet folks at my new job in-person! The first day was a series of icebreakers followed by some pretty in-depth discussion of goals and strategy for the Engineering team. The second day was an actual on-site visit to the headquarters building, where we participated in “Science Day”, which entailed an informal hackathon as well as presentations by some folks on what they’ve been working on. Frankly, an incredible few days.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/valo.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Inside HQ!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/braves.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>We took a tour of nearby Fenway Park. Included in its on-site museum were original baseballs signed by every single World Series winning team. Obviously, I went straight for the 1995 ball.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/baberuth.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>But I also glanced at what might be the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1927_New_York_Yankees_season">single most famous World Series team</a> of all time.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And over Labor Day weekend, my family and I journeyed to Ohio to visit my wife’s family. It was a blast, but it was wall-to-wall activities. I recall telling my wife at the Cleveland Air Show, as the F-15 was coming around to buzz us a second time: “I’m enjoying this! But if it was up to me I’d be home right now.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/thunderbirds.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Air_Force_Thunderbirds">The Thunderbirds</a> headlined this year’s air show.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="flipping-the-table-setting-it-on-fire-and-blowing-it-up" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="flipping-the-table-setting-it-on-fire-and-blowing-it-up">Flipping the table, setting it on fire, and blowing it up</h3>
<p>We may have bitten off more than we could chew from globetrotting alone. Other major life events made sure we paid dearly for our decisions.</p>
<p>In May, I attended what will very likely be my last UGA graduation to hood my final graduating doctoral student. It was definitely bittersweet… but honestly, I was mostly proud of my students, and thrilled that it really could be my final graduation ceremony.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/uga_graduation.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Someone in my dad’s department was in attendance and was kind enough to snap this for me.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In March, I turned 40. Like a dad at the playground who just turned 40 the day before Z’s birthday said to me: “My brain thinks I’m 25, but my body thinks I’m 55.” Can’t bend down and pick something my kiddo has dropped without making all the appropriate over-30 noises.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/happy40th.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Birthday party for 1, please.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In January, we got the first decent snowfall in Athens that we’ve had in since we moved here, and first snow of any kind in Athens since 2021. It was beautiful; Z loved playing in it, and it even canceled a few days of school. And a few days of daycare. So I now <em>really</em> understand how my parents must have felt on the occasional snow day when I was a kid.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/snow.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>An increasingly rare event in the southeastern US.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Let’s see, what else… oh! <strong>I officially began my new job at Valo on July 16, and my last official day at UGA was August 15. And Z left daycare and started public pre-K at the start of August.</strong><sup>3</sup></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/resignation.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>10.5 years. Pretty incredible.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="permanent-impermenance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="permanent-impermenance">Permanent impermenance</h3>
<p>So far, 2025 has been a visceral lesson on the impermanence of life. It’s something I conceptually understood, and often associated it negatively (ie death). But this year has given me a taste of its positive side. It’s a theme that has also come up in speaking with my therapist lately: that even bad situations are temporary. Life is a series of seasons, and if I’m frustrated with where I am now, I can probably do at least a little something to change it.</p>
<p>Like the final slide of the NPR comic: if nothing else, you can allow yourself to daydream of something better.</p>
<p>It’s somehow already mid-September and, while travel and major life transitions <em>should</em> be in the rearview mirror for at least a few months<sup>4</sup>, I’m still finding it difficult to catch my breath. A big part of that is simply: jfc, I’m trying to find what our new daily equilibrium even is! I’m a creature of habit, and I feel like I really nailed 2024. But the playing field has changed <em>dramatically</em> since then and I’m still recalibrating.</p>
<p>I <em>love</em> my new job (even though I feel about 10 slippery steps behind on everything): the work is exciting, the schedule is sustainable, and the people are <strong>just. lovely.</strong> I went on a 5-mile run with my direct supervisor during the Boston on-site. I’m sure there’s a rose-tinted sheen over everything right now, but even watching other folks interact—in the Slack, at the office—I’m humbled by how compassion and empathy underlie it all. They care about the work, sure, but they care even more about the people.</p>
<p>I also… don’t really miss UGA? I’ve visited campus a few times lately, both since submitting my letter of resignation in mid-June, and even since my employment officially ended August 15. There are <em>parts</em> of it I miss: the sense of physical community, some really awesome folks, working with my Dad. But I kept expecting I’d be bowled over at some point with mourning, and it just hasn’t happened. It still could! And even if it doesn’t, those parts I mentioned will probably pop up in waves from time to time.</p>
<p>But every day at this new job has been replete with parallel experiences: where something that, for the past 10 years, had always gone one particular way, <em>instead went this other awesome way</em>. And it’s just… normal. It’s not special, not exceptional, not a one-off; it’s just how this company does business.</p>
<p>Mindblowing. Sometimes, the grass really <em>is</em> greener.</p>
<p>I’m sure this new job will have its grinds. I’m sure, even once I find my footing with these new routines, stuff will hit the fan. And I’m sure that when that happens, I’ll fail miserably to embrace the journey and instead just wish it away. But like my recently-5yo<sup>5</sup> daughter has taken to saying lately: “We’ll do our best.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/superstardestroyer.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Would anyone be up for a round of Star Wars Armada?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Much like air travel, which I’ll get to.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Yes this actually happened: on a flight home to ATL, already delayed 2+ hours on the tarmac in Colorado due to lightning, was then diverted to Birmingham because of lightning over Atlanta. I think we got home at 2am?↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I don’t know whether it’d have been more painful to have spaced these transitions out, but I can definitely say having them hit at once was also painful.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>A tentative trip over the holidays in December is the only thing on the horizon.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>As an “elder millennial” whose brain is still jammed somewhere in the middle of 2020… HOW 5YO 😭↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2025,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {“{We’ll} Do Our Best.”},
  date = {2025-09-12},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2025. <span>“<span>‘We’ll Do Our Best.’</span>”</span>
September 12, 2025. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best">https://magsol.github.io/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 13:57:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-09-12-well-do-our-best/pix/firefly_sunrise.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Nothing Is Certain</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/portal.png" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="A Playground-generated image of a portal that very closely resembles an artificial wormhole from Stargate but is sufficiently different.."></p>
<figcaption>Where does this path lead? Only one way to find out.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>…except death and taxes. Yeah, I know the quote. I just wish I knew what came next.</p>
<section id="hunt-for-the-red-october-perfect-role" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hunt-for-the-red-october-perfect-role">Hunt for the <del>Red October</del> perfect role</h3>
<p>In case you don’t follow me on Mastodon, I recently posted this:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/toot.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A post of mine from Mastodon, detailing my acceptance of a job offer and subsequent departure from academia.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Almost exactly two years ago, <a href="../../posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/index.html">I wrote this post about burnout</a> and my then-current resolve to leave academia. A lot changed in that time: I intentionally cultivated agency, scored an incredibly productive sabbatical (both professionally and personally), and <a href="../../posts/2025-01-04-agency/index.html">set about creating a new faculty role for myself at UGA</a>. I was adament that I would make a decision about my career, and stand behind it. Set myself up to succeed. Commit.</p>
<p>I’ll admit that, in my more cynical moments, I doubted whether I was committing or simply continuing to avoid making a decision. Inspired by the work I did at PredxBio, I was pursuing multiple interlocking federal grants that would not only jumpstart the next phase of my academic career, but catapult it in a relatively new direction. I was reaching out to faculty at in new departments to forge collaborations. I worked with the UGA Institute of Bioinformatics to move my role entirely out of Computer Science and into where it probably should have been all along. I even got a new office to reflect my changed role.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/stem_office.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>By the time I leave UGA, I’ll have been in this office for 4 months.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>At the same time, I was applying for industry jobs like a fiend; since January 1, I submitted 95 job applications. Only half of those I heard back from; most of these were what I took to calling “desk rejects,” i.e.: “thanks but no thanks.” But there were a handful that wanted to interview me. A couple halted the interview process when I said I had no interest in relocating. Another ended the process after a coding question. Yet another flew me out to their on-site HQ (after <em>five</em> rounds of remote interviews), told me after I “basically had the job,” and then rescinded the soft offer a few days later on the vague notion that I wasn’t committed enough to start-up life<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<p>Cynicism aside, the objective truth is that I was going full-speed on both sides of the ball. But if I stopped to think about it, I still wondered: was I just putting off a decision?</p>
</section>
<section id="agency-agency-agency" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="agency-agency-agency">Agency agency agency</h3>
<p>Following a late May NIH grant deadline that got DOGE’d only three days before<sup>2</sup>, I went into June thinking I’d take a couple weeks off. The Spring 2025 semester was <em>brutal</em>, unlike any teaching semester I’d had in my last 10 years, and between that and the DOGE’d deadline I desperately needed a breather.</p>
<p>Right around this time, another job opportunity hit my radar, right as I’d returned from that aforementioned whirlwind on-site interview. It also nearly ended just as quickly: after the initial intake, I was told that—because they “didn’t do business in Georgia”—I was no longer under consideration.</p>
<p>But in a very not-me move, I pushed back: I argued that, at the very least, we should keep talking to find out if it was even a problem that needed solving, and at most, whether the problem’s solution was a win-win for all involved.</p>
<p>This <em>actually</em> worked! They reached back out, put me on the interview calendar, and holy cow: it was easily the most enjoyable interview process of 2025. I really felt as though I was connecting with the people I met. And only a couple hours after a quick chat with their CTO, an offer came down the pipe that was, to put it simply, too good to pass up.</p>
<p>I spent the first 24 hours after receving the offer just letting it soak in<sup>3</sup>. For the subsequent 24-36 hours, I did my homework. I really did. I considered, first and foremost: <em>Is this the job I’d leave academia for?</em> Somewhat to my surprise, the answer to this from the start had been an emphatic “Yes” but the process had, if anything, only solidified it further. I also went through the pros-and-cons process<sup>4</sup>, structuring what it would look like to stay or leave UGA, respectively. And in every case, this new role won out.</p>
</section>
<section id="from-imaging-to-drug-discovery" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="from-imaging-to-drug-discovery">From imaging to drug discovery</h3>
<p>I’ll have more to say about this later, but quickly: the new role is with <a href="https://www.valohealth.com/">Valo Health</a>, a drug discovery “start-up” (it’s insanely successful and has at least 150 employees, so yes it’s <em>technically</em> a start-up). I’m joining the engineering team to work on the machine learning end with a focus on reproducibility. It’s definitely a step away from where I’ve been focusing the last decade, but during the interview it was made clear that after the first year they’ll be looking to leverage that expertise more into new areas.</p>
<p>An exciting role with room to grow. Can’t really ask for much more!</p>
</section>
<section id="never-a-black-and-white-scenario" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="never-a-black-and-white-scenario">Never a black-and-white scenario</h3>
<p>The decision itself may have been clear, but that did not make it <em>easy</em>, nor <em>painless</em>; quite the opposite on both counts, in fact. UGA was my first “real” job, outside of internships and assistantships. I made progress in my role, winning the proverbial Ivory Tower Pie Eating Contest<sup>5</sup>. And to be completely frank, the part I enjoyed the most—hands down—was getting to work with my dad. He’s always been a hero of mine for as long as I can remember, and <a href="https://news.uga.edu/father-son-faculty-members-team-up-on-nsf-grant/">working on a research team and publishing papers together was truly a dream come true</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/stem_office_2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>I’ve barely begun moving into this incredible new office, and pretty soon I’ll vacate it only four months after I was officially assigned it.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>More broadly, that’s where this decision is the hardest to accept: an aching feeling of <em>letting these people down</em>. Of abandoning good people in a fight that needs to be fought. Of walking away from obligations that others will have to scramble to handle in my absence. Of leaving behind something that others put time and energy into, and of betraying trust.</p>
<p>I’ve always been a “put the team first” sort of person, which I’ve had to unlearn in my adult years, at least to the extent where I can set and hold healthy boundaries. This has been especially true around work/life balance, something academia will take every inch you give and run a ten miles with. And that’s where at least part of the guilt comes from: obligations which I don’t necessarily <em>want</em> to do, but which I know need to be done, and which I know will fall more heavily on others.</p>
</section>
<section id="its-the-people" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="its-the-people">It’s the people</h3>
<p>But most of all, it’s the people I’ll miss.</p>
<p>Of course I’ll miss the research questions I never fully answered despite having no shortage of ideas for how to try. I’ll miss the teaching pedagogies and infrastructure I was never able to finish implementing. I’ll miss the crazier ideas for new research institutes (I’ve bounced around ideas for two distinct research centers), new Freshman Odyssey courses (buy everyone in the course a Raspberry Pi; how cool would that be?!), new Data Science Practicum projects (imagine: a tournament of StarCraft bots), and new open source software contributions (I’d really hoped <code>cilia2vec</code> would eventually be a thing).</p>
<p>But above all that, I’ll miss the colleagues I met and relationships I built. I’ll miss the students who responded positively to the <a href="https://www.17thshard.com/forums/topic/90272-mental-illness-in-the-cosmere/">everyone-is-a-Cosmere-protagonist</a> environment I seemed to cultivate from day 1. I’ll miss the people who had my back, especially in the past couple years. I’ll miss the people who were intentional about <em>lowering</em> the ladder as they climbed it, and the people who took a beat to check in with others around them. I’ll miss having a professional excuse to throw batshit ideas against the wall while having coffee with my Dad on the occasional calm work morning.</p>
<p>This is where it’s not so much a “decision” as a “process”.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/nameplate.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>I never really got used to this classical sign of authority. I never really got used to being addressed as “Professor,” either. To this day, “Dr.&nbsp;Quinn” and “Prof.&nbsp;Quinn” are and always will be my Dad.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="disentanglement" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="disentanglement">Disentanglement</h3>
<p>Logistically, there’s a lot to unravel and wind down in the next several weeks, the biggest of which is a brand new undergraduate degree program: an applied computational science degree. I had fever dreams of seeing just about every single Franklin unit involved, making it less a degree program and more a four-year fusion of undergraduate instruction and graduate research. That could still happen, but I need to accelerate my groundwork so the lovely folks working with me on it aren’t left to pick up the pieces.</p>
<p>Emotionally… it’s a lot more complicated.</p>
<p>I’ve made no secret<sup>6</sup> over the post-COVID years of my dissatisfaction with academia in general and my role in particular. As part of my “agency” resolution, I wanted to experiment with changing units at UGA: moving out of Computer Science and into the Institute of Bioinformatics. This move was predicated on the hypothesis that some of the aspects of my job that were most draining could be ameliorated, e.g.: a different and less intense instructional load; not only support for, but outright embrace of, interdisciplinary research; a cohesive and concrete vision for the unit broken down into actionable milestones; just to name a few.</p>
<p>And so far, this move had been everything I’d hoped it to be. Except for <em>expedient</em>: it’s been about a full year since I had that first meeting with the IOB, and at least on paper, that move won’t become official for another week (July 1).</p>
<p>Just in time for me to resign a month and a half later.</p>
<p>So another dimension of my mental gymnastics is the warped idea that I haven’t given this new self-direction enough time to mature. After all, didn’t I say I wanted to <em>commit</em>? How is leaving right before a new role kicks in “committing”?</p>
<p>Honestly, this is the hardest part of my decision. I know it’s the right call, but I can’t and won’t ever be completely certain that—had I decided to keep going down the academic route—I wouldn’t have found a way to make it everything I’d hoped. After 10 years, I can feel pretty confident about it, but it’s impossible to be certain. And, of course, there’s never a guarantee that the grass really is greener.</p>
<p>Nothing is certain. I’ve done the best I can; all that’s left is to hope.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/clouds.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Here goes everything!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Quite the galling thing to say when I flew out on a home-and-back-in-36-hours-flat trip on a mere 6 days’ notice, but hey, I got to see some dear friends I hadn’t seen since 2021 so as far as I’m concerned, it was their loss.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>I wish this was a joke. On May 25, it was announced that a bunch of NIH grants had been discontinued, including the one I was working on that was due May 28.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Ask Cathryn about the shit I pulled :)↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Thanks to the 5+ year in-progress blog post about academia that may never see the light of day, I already had this pretty well laid out.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>i.e., tenure, where the prize is more pie.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>At least, no secret <em>in private</em>.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2025,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Nothing {Is} {Certain}},
  date = {2025-06-25},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2025. <span>“Nothing Is Certain.”</span> June 25, 2025.
<a href="https://magsol.github.io/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain">https://magsol.github.io/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 22:17:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-06-25-nothing-is-certain/portal.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>From the ground up with self-hosting</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-04-06-from-the-ground-up-with-self-hosting/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-04-06-from-the-ground-up-with-self-hosting/light_tunnel.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A Playground-generated image of a walking path flanked by old-timey lights leading into what appears to be a castle (aka, the destination)."></p>
<p>On the evening of Thursday, January 16, I shut down all my self-hosted servers and services in preparation for one final home renovation project (which, thankfully, would take only the next day and be done after that). In my head, I figured it’d take a day or two to clean the rooms involved and put all the furniture back, after which I’d need another day or two to get my home services up and running again. After all, a year ago I’d reorganized all the upstairs networking hardware and servers into a handy little mini-rack, so everything was nicely contained! Shouldn’t be too hard, right?</p>
<p>…here we are, almost <em>three full months later</em>, and I’m starting to see the light at the end of the tunnel. Granted, it hasn’t been all-or-nothing: we were able to clean the rooms involved within 48 hours, and at least in terms of vital home networking, I was indeed able to get that back up and running within the subsequent 24 hours or so.</p>
<p>But our Quinnwitz Mastodon instance has been down this whole time. Some internal Unraid services have been working for awhile now, but even those took a few days longer than I’d expected. Mastodon has easily been the worst casualty of them all: I had a series of structural improvements I wanted to make to how I configured my kubernetes cluster, stretching both its (and my) capabilities in that regard; this has not only been time-consuming by virtue of its novelty, but also because my return to UGA this semester has been <em>brutal</em> and draining, and I simply haven’t had the bandwidth for experimenting with kubernetes.</p>
<p>“Experimenting with kubernetes.” Gods, what a euphemism.</p>
<p>Anyway. But yes, I am starting to see the light at the end of this long tunnel. And while there’s still a ways to go, I’m far enough along that I’ve decided to take all the notes I’ve been making along the way and turn them into a series of blog posts (because there’s simply too much to do in a single post). Plus, it’s been over three months since my last post here, so I suppose I have some catching up to do.</p>
<p>Hopefully, the end of this series will coincide with—or even follow up on—the return of our Mastodon instance. There are a bunch of other little improvements I’ve made (or will soon make) that I’m pretty excited about, so I’m looking forward to sharing those here in case anyone else finds them useful.</p>
<p>Stay tuned!</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2025,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {From the Ground up with Self-Hosting},
  date = {2025-04-06},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2025-04-06-from-the-ground-up-with-self-hosting},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2025. <span>“From the Ground up with
Self-Hosting.”</span> April 6, 2025. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2025-04-06-from-the-ground-up-with-self-hosting">https://magsol.github.io/2025-04-06-from-the-ground-up-with-self-hosting</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>self hosting</category>
  <category>kubernetes</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <category>unraid</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-04-06-from-the-ground-up-with-self-hosting/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 14:54:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-04-06-from-the-ground-up-with-self-hosting/light_tunnel.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Agency</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-04-agency/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-04-agency/sky.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Clouds forming an incredible pattern with what looks like a crevasse down the middle, through which sun rays can be seen."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Content warning: language, discussion of mental health struggles, and pet death.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>I’ve been thinking a lot about “agency” this year, and how the lack thereof underlies <em>so much</em> of what I’ve been struggling with the past several years. Arguably it’s been my singular source of burnout, and is my focus for 2025.</p>
<section id="work" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="work">Work</h3>
<p>I realize I haven’t really posted much work stuff here, despite saying I would in previous posts. Work has easily been the single greatest source of stress for me over the past decade, in no small part because it has <em>embodied</em> my lack of agency, starting—frankly—all the way back when I was initially offered the position at UGA.</p>
<p>This past year, I worked as a “Principal AI/ML Scientist” with a small, Pittsburgh-based biotech startup called <a href="https://predxbio.com/">PredxBio</a>. I was officially on sabbatical with UGA, though my intention at the time was to leave UGA entirely sometime during 2024. Unfortunately, 2023-2024 have been extremely rough years for not-FAANG tech companies, startups in particular. Sometime in the summer, the CTO informed me that things were looking bleak funding-wise. So I started laying some other groundwork (I’ll come back to this in a minute).</p>
<p>PredxBio is, professionally, <em>hands-down the most fun I’ve had in the last 10 years</em>. I worked with a small but incredibly talented and dedicated team on both the science and engineering around a niche but fast-growing area called “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spatial_biology">spatial biology</a>.” In practice, I helped bring some industry-standard development practices to their existing spatial proteomics pipeline, refactoring some years-old code which led to (I kid you not) a 1000% increase in performance—an operation which took two days was reduced to <em>30 seconds</em>. I also dove into the (very cool) <a href="https://scverse.org/">scverse</a> ecosystem and created the company’s first spatial transcriptomics pipeline. I was in the middle of working on a project for a client that would actually <em>combine</em> the proteomics and transcriptomics pipelines—become truly multiomics—when the year ended. It’s an incredible project, with incredible people, and I’ve been mourning having to leave since November.</p>
<p>Now, enter said groundwork. For most of the summer, I spoke with the unit heads of both the UGA Institute of Bioinformatics (IOB) and Department of Cellular Biology, the latter of which is already one of my home units. I pitched, and was eventually able to land, a change in my “home unit” assignment: rather than being split between Computer Science and Cellular Biology, I will zero out Computer Science and move that affiliation over to IOB. There are <em>a lot</em> of reasons for this, both personal and professional, but it boils down to <em>agency</em>: I wanted to build a role that I could get excited about, where I could pursue computational biology questions that excited me, both in the classroom and the laboratory, while working with colleagues and students who were likewise excited and supportive.</p>
<p>I’ve gotten everything out of Computer Science that I can, and it’s gotten more than its fair share out of me. This is an opportunity of <em>my own making</em>—of course, done in collaboration with people I couldn’t have done it without, and with whom I hope to continue collaborating as fruitfully for years to come. But unlike when I first accepted the CS position over a decade ago, I not only voiced my concerns and requests, but <em>stood by them</em> until we reached a consensus based on mutual understanding.</p>
<p>Even better: I’m planning to continue consulting one day per week with PredxBio (as per my right as faculty), with the plan/hope that, if all goes well financially over the next few months, I’ll return to full-time over the summer. In my dream scenario, I’m also planning to submit an R01 grant that names PredxBio as a chief collaborator; if funded, this would solidify our professional relationship for at least the next five years, and give both of us the financial and logistical flexibility to continue working together. It’d even open up a recruiting avenue if PredxBio needs to start hiring (definitely a longer term plan!), so I’m really crossing my fingers here.</p>
<p>Suffice to say, I’m trying to create something that actually gets me out of bed in the mornings. The perfect antidote to burnout, or at least the next step in healing. Rather than stumbling from one five-alarm fire to the next, I’m trying to be intentional.</p>
<p>Time will tell. But for now, I’m cautiously optimistic.</p>
<p>There is still <em>A LOT</em> I find problematic with academia in general, UGA specifically, and my units in particular. A couple weeks ago I was invited out of the blue to apply for an NIH early career reviewer program, only to have my application desk-rejected after I’d put in a few hours to assemble everything. This past summer, UGA committed the third accounting error in as many years whereby someone up the chain fucked up my financials, but in order to fix it, needed to either nuke my indirect accounts or, in this case, withhold subsequent paychecks to cover the difference (the total amount UGA has fucked me over is now in excess of $130,000, I should add). I just had a conference paper rejected, and the two reviewers’ feedback I received totaled three sentences, all of which were addressed in the paper itself.</p>
<p>These are things I have no control over; raging against them is certainly what I’d like to do, but would ultimately be a waste of time and energy. Like the design of my new role, I need to focus on what I can control in order to create opportunities. So for the time being, I’m keeping one foot in academia.</p>
</section>
<section id="running" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="running">Running</h3>
<p>I’ll go into this more on my running blog (<strong>EDIT</strong>: <a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2025/01/06/return-to-some-kind-of-form/">here’s the 2024-in-running post</a>, if you’re curious), but since I mentioned it in my <a href="../../posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/index.html">2023 retrospective post</a>, I wanted to say here: not only did I hit 1000 miles this year, I piled on another 70 for good measure. I also hit a week of over 30 miles (once, but still), and the Chickamauga Battlefield half marathon for the first time since 2018 (I ran the full marathon in 2019, so it’d been only five years since going to the actual location for a race).</p>
<p>There’s still a lot to do here—I’m still feeling as though long COVID has its claws in me and I’d really like to get some answers; I’m also frustrated with how I don’t feel as though I’ve gotten any faster this year; long runs in particular have been grueling, and I’m not sure if it’s because of the first item or something innocuous (e.g., I need a better fueling strategy)—but I’m proud of the routines and habits I’ve established, and the <em>space</em> I’ve created for running, and I finally feel as though running is truly part of who I am again.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-04-agency/chickamauga.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A post-race photo with Cathryn, our friend Laura, and her partner Zach.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="personal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal">Personal</h3>
<p>This year was… a lot. I go into it quite a bit in <a href="../../posts/2024-06-13-desolation/index.html">this post from the summer</a>: our 9+ year old bunny Clover dying, my parents’ house being broken into, the multiple bullshit accounting mistakes made by UGA which I had to bail them out of, starting back on SSRIs for the first time in several years, parenting a toddler-turned-young-kid, (inter)national politics. To this day, I cannot say which I find more repugnant: RG progressives who have no Middle East connections but suddenly became Middle East geopolitical experts on Oct 8, 2023, yet have been silent ever since; or TG progressives, likewise with no Middle East connections, who have since made the Middle East their entire personalities.</p>
<p>On that note, I’ve also wrestled with a lot of my own inner demons: one of my goals for 2024 to work on my deep-seated anger and resentment. This entailed coming to terms with prior working situations, re-evaluating relationships, and making a whole lot of decisions about what was important enough to continue to make space for, and what needed to be let go. This was as innocuous as deep cleaning our garage and its 10+ years of accumulated <em>stuff</em> when contractors came to install our solar panels + battery setup: a lot of it we could easily part with, but some had pretty deep sentimental value but was otherwise just taking up space. It was also as complicated as relationships that have changed for reasons unknown, and it’s that unknown part that is the most heartbreaking and makes it so difficult to decide one way or the other whether to keep sticking it out; in the end, we need to do what’s best for us.</p>
<p>My wife’s therapist put it nicely: we’re closing the door, but that doesn’t mean they can’t knock on it sometime later, at which point it’s up to us whether we answer.</p>
<p>I’m also working on a mindset shift, one that understands and embraces the truth that current situations are <em>temporary</em> by definition, and I can decide whether I want to tough it out or go try something else. This is a valuable perspective both personally, but also professionally—it underlies all my efforts to create something that excited me: if things are still miserable, I can try something else. Or leave.</p>
<p>I did set up a Signal group chat following the election, full of <em>absolutely wonderful</em> human beings who have easily been the most consistently bright point in the weeks since<sup>1</sup>. It’s not a large group, just 10 of us (some I haven’t met in person), but we’ve already had some wonderful discussions. It can be more or less summed up by the image I chose as the group avatar. National politics continues to be a shitshow and will likely only get worse over the next four years, but <a href="https://amyjko.medium.com/the-coming-storm-03a03750016b">this mindset shift should help</a>. My therapist has always said to lean into worse-case scenarios, not because they’ll necessarily become true, but because we may discover <a href="https://www.ncronline.org/opinion/editorial/editorial-hope-time-darkness">we’re more resilient than we initially thought</a>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-04-agency/log_cabin.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A cozy log cabin somewhere in Appalachia, with everything covered in snow.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I also <a href="../../posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/index.html">assembled the single most powerful desktop I’ve ever built</a>, organized the home upstairs office with a server rack, upgraded our home network with a <a href="https://firewalla.com/">Firewalla</a>, and have spent the last month making progress on <a href="../../posts/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition/index.html">more easily accessible homelab services</a>. We had our nearly-20-year-old roof replaced, had solar panels put on it and backup batteries installed, substantially improved the insulation in our attic space, and are epsilon-away from having a couple of windows replaced to really complete weather-ification.</p>
</section>
<section id="summary-of-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summary-of-2024">Summary of 2024</h3>
<p>The Good:</p>
<ul>
<li>Best professional work experience in 10 years, top to bottom, with PredxBio</li>
<li>Broke 1000 miles running for the first time since 2019</li>
<li>Forged a “new” position at UGA for myself starting in 2025</li>
<li>Set personal and professional boundaries and held them</li>
<li>Maintained phenomenal consistency with physical activities across the board</li>
<li>Built some really cool shit</li>
</ul>
<p>The Bad:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mental health struggles, back on medication</li>
<li>Running speed has not improved in a year</li>
<li>Still a lot of lingering resentment around some relationships</li>
<li>Losing our beloved bunny, Clover</li>
</ul>
<p>The Ugly:</p>
<ul>
<li>The fucking election</li>
<li>Continued fallout from Oct 7, 2023</li>
<li>Parents’ house being burglarized</li>
<li>Having contractors in our house sucks; them breaking shit is another level</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="plans-for-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans-for-2025">Plans for 2025</h3>
<p>I’m still not making “resolutions” in the traditional sense. As <a href="https://mastodon.social/@glyph/113755645565821731">a recent toot made very explicit</a>: “the structure of the exercise is practically designed to set you up for failure” (like some other things of the past few years<sup>2</sup>). As <a href="https://mastodon.social/@grimalkina/113754067707608423">someone I deeply admire</a> put it: “it is always a wonder how much this [time off] ultimately actually leads to things the world sees as productive….when you make that NOT the goal”.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, my biggest priorities this year are to focus on <strong>agency and intentionality</strong>: creating opportunities where I can, and walking away when I need to. I created this “new” role for myself at UGA; now I need to commit to doing everything I can to succeed in it. At the same time, I can always tweak things that aren’t working; alternatively, I can walk away entirely. My situation need not be permanent. Change, or choose.</p>
<p>My other plans, in no particular order:</p>
<ul>
<li>1000+ miles running (again), with an emphasis on 100+ mile months, and 30+ mile weeks</li>
<li>Finish cleaning out the garage, and start in earnest on cleaning out the upstairs</li>
<li>Keep cultivating new opportunities through consistency and intentionality</li>
<li>Set and hold boundaries, especially around work/life balance</li>
</ul>
<p>In my <a href="../../posts/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap/index.html"><code>#DecemberAdventure</code> wrap-up post</a>, I laid out the next steps for getting internal/homelab services up and running with their own DNS entries and SSL certificates. I feel reasonably confident about this approach, thanks to some of the groundwork I did last year and especially during <code>#DecemberAdventure</code>. The first step? Completely reformat my Pi cluster and start over!</p>
<p>Happy 2025, everyone. Much love to all.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-04-agency/clover.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Miss this sweet, sassy, beautiful girl every single day. We love you, Clover.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Not to mention learning all about how animals are classified!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p><em>shifty eyes</em>↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2025,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Agency},
  date = {2025-01-04},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2025-01-04-agency},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2025. <span>“Agency.”</span> January 4, 2025. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2025-01-04-agency">https://magsol.github.io/2025-01-04-agency</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>new years</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-04-agency/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2025 15:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-04-agency/sky.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="192" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure: That’s a wrap!</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap/zippy.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Picture of our black cat Zippy sitting in a chair intended for our 4yo, looking like she's the most relaxed any cat has ever been."></p>
<p>Welp.</p>
<p>Don’t know about you, but this December <em>flew</em> by for me. I should have anticipated that, come the week of Christmas, I would have approximately negative time with which to continue <code>#DecemberAdventure</code>. Still, it took me by surprise. So let me try to wrap up where things stand.</p>
<section id="cluster-wide-reverse-proxy" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cluster-wide-reverse-proxy">Cluster-wide reverse proxy</h4>
<p>Even if I haven’t implemented this yet (due to reasons I’ll get to), I think at this point I understand pretty well how to do it. It more or less boils down to:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Set my local DNS (i.e., my Firewalla router) to point some version of <code>local.my.domain</code> to my reverse proxy</li>
<li>Create local CNAME entries that point to various local services</li>
<li>Add a <code>*.local.my.domain</code> sans domain in my traefik configuration to get the SSL to work for these endpoints</li>
<li>Set up a kubernetes <code>Service</code> object for each local service I want traefik to be able to access</li>
</ol>
<p>That’s about it! I’m still a little iffy on step 2, mainly because I don’t know what will prevent any device on the network from skipping the top-level (local) domain pointing to the reverse proxy and going straight for the CNAME entry that is actually being requested. But I suppose, at this point, I just need to deploy it and see what happens.</p>
</section>
<section id="cat-magic-deck" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cat-magic-deck">Cat Magic deck</h4>
<p>I haven’t really made any changes to my <a href="https://tappedout.net/mtg-decks/04-12-24-cats/">Cat deck</a>—i.e., it’s still mostly a template—but I did receive a nice Amazon gift card for Christmas, so I used it to purchase some of the cards I’m quite sure I’ll need. Hopefully that will help me winnow this thing down to a standard 60-card deck.</p>
</section>
<section id="pi-cluster-next-steps" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pi-cluster-next-steps">Pi cluster next steps</h4>
<p>In doing all this research for the reverse proxy, it became increasingly clear that I need to overhaul the entire cluster—hence the reason why I stopped just short of implementing anything regarding the reverse proxy.</p>
<p>Right now, the cluster has no “local” storage (meaning, no storage connected directly to any of the Pi SBCs); everything instead goes over the network. This works, certainly, but it’s not ideal, particularly when the power goes out or I need to selectively shut things down: I have to be careful in what order I shut down 1) the Pi cluster, 2) the network file storage, and 3) the network hubs connecting everything. It would be <em>substantially</em> easier if I had storage connected directly to the Pi machines that the k3s cluster could use.</p>
<p>So I used some Christmas money to purchase a couple of SSDs. Meaning that I’ve also spent a lot of time looking into <a href="https://longhorn.io/">Longhorn</a> and <a href="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/">Garage</a> distributed block storage solutions for kubernetes clusters. I have everything ready to go there, but in so doing I need to prepare in case I’m not able to transfer everything over from the current network storage location.</p>
<p>Meaning I need to prepare to more or less start from scratch. Which will, frankly, simplify things. It’ll also give me opportunities to update the k3s clients, the base OSes (from Ubuntu 22 to 24), and the various helm charts (not to mention fixing the namespace issues I enumerated in an <a href="../../posts/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml/index.html">earlier post</a>).</p>
<p>Admittedly it does feel like every personal project ends up with some version of “re-do everything I’ve already done so this one tiny addition will work,” but hey, isn’t that what learning is all about?</p>
</section>
<section id="section" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="section">2025</h4>
<p>I’m working on a 2024 Retrospective post. It’s gonna be a doozy. Hopefully I’ll have it up in the next couple days.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2025,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure:} {That’s} a Wrap!},
  date = {2025-01-01},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2025. <span>“December Adventure: That’s a Wrap!”</span>
January 1, 2025. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap">https://magsol.github.io/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>magic the gathering</category>
  <category>reverse proxy</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 15:36:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2025-01-01-december-adventure-thats-a-wrap/zippy.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure: Oh that’s how DNS works</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-20-december-adventure-oh-thats-how-dns-works/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-20-december-adventure-oh-thats-how-dns-works/snowbun.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Picture of our white bunny Clover enjoying a rare snowfall, from back in 2018. She was our little snowshoe hare."></p>
<p>Ok, I’ve been barking up the wrong tree.</p>
<p>The wildcard subdomain I was referencing in my previous post? That’s only needed for <em>certificates</em>, not for actual subdomain resolution. Also, if one can resolve <code>domain.org</code>, then one can also resolve <code>test.subdomain.org</code> (thank you, Firewalla support; keep up the truly remarkable work, y’all). Furthermore, the only role my DNS registrar serves in this process is to validate that I own the root domain; after that, Let’s Encrypt does its thing, and all domain resolution happens within my home network.</p>
<p>I realize this is all probably obvious to everyone (and parts <em>have been</em> obvious to me, at some point previously), but for some reason it’s taken me reading lots of Reddit threads, watching YouTube videos, and contacting customer support to fully connect all these dots. The only <em>actual</em> place the wildcard domain exists (e.g., <code>*.local.domain.org</code>) is in the Traefik configuration under the “sans” header. That’s it! My DNS registrar has my root domain, and my internal DNS server has all the CNAME entries pointing to various services.</p>
<p>Seriously, DNS is so simple, it’s complicated.</p>
<hr>
<p>There’s been a LOT going on this week, as work stuff has wound down and holiday preparations have kicked into very, <em>very</em> high gear. I’ve been feeling a lot of different things—chief among them, sadness that my yearlong sabbatical with PredxBio is almost complete—and so I’ve been pretty distracted this week.</p>
<p>We also disassembled Clover’s old “condo” (the DIY home setup I built ~6 years ago), deep-cleaned the area around it, and had a bulk trash pickup for the spare items. It was more or less the final step to fully <em>seeing</em> that Clover was gone; even though she died back at the end of September, I swear I still saw flashes of white in the corners of my eyes when I glanced past the condo. Now, it’s impossible to refute, and it hurts all over again.</p>
<p>2024 has been such a mixed bag, something I’ll have to write more about later.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure:} {Oh} That’s How {DNS} Works},
  date = {2024-12-20},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-20-december-adventure-oh-thats-how-dns-works},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“December Adventure: Oh That’s How DNS
Works.”</span> December 20, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-20-december-adventure-oh-thats-how-dns-works">https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-20-december-adventure-oh-thats-how-dns-works</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>traefik</category>
  <category>dns</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-20-december-adventure-oh-thats-how-dns-works/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 16:26:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-20-december-adventure-oh-thats-how-dns-works/snowbun.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="153" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure: How does DNS work</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work/itwasdns.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Meme showing a haiku: 'It's not DNS / There's no way it's DNS / It was DNS.' Credit: https://www.reddit.com/r/sysadmin/comments/6qhih0/its_always_dns/"></p>
<p>I always feel like I have the dumbest questions, mostly because I cannot seem to find answers on the internet.</p>
<p>(either that, or my questions are so SMART, no one’s thought of them; or search engines have gotten SO BAD that they don’t really work anymore… equal odds, I’d say)</p>
<p>In my last post, I’d prototyped a way of reverse proxying a service that runs on a different physical machine than the reverse proxy itself (and which perhaps should be stated explicitly: the service is also NOT part of the kubernetes cluster that the reverse proxy is). However, I couldn’t actually access it… because I didn’t have a DNS entry for said external service. I could reach the reverse proxy, but it didn’t know where to go from there.</p>
<p>Which made me realize a conundrum: how do I actually configure DNS to do this?</p>
<p>I’m trying to set up a subdomain on a domain I already own (quinnwitz.house), except this subdomain is <strong>only accessible from my LAN.</strong> So anytime someone goes to, say, <code>jellyfin.home.quinnwitz.house</code>, it does nothing <em>unless</em> they’re on my home LAN, in which case they’ll go to my local JellyFin instance (and it’ll have an SSL cert).</p>
<p>It’s clear I need to create an A record for a wildcard domain… but it’s <em>not</em> clear 1) where this A record should reside (the base quinnwitz.house domain is on Cloudflare; is that where it should go, too?), and 2) what it should point to.</p>
<p>I did manage to find a single Reddit thread asking pretty much exactly this question: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/homelab/comments/17h16g7/cloudflare_dns_pointed_to_internal_ip_address_safe/">is it safe to put a wildcard subdomain on Cloudflare, pointing to an <em>internal</em> IP address</a>? The answer seems to be “yes”, but I can’t help but wonder if this is the “right” way of doing it.</p>
<p>After posting about my last update on Mastodon, I did get a couple of responses (thank you! and yes, <a href="https://doc.traefik.io/traefik-hub/api-management/external-api#create-an-externalname-service">traefik does indeed support <code>externalName</code></a>). But the crux of it all still <em>assumed</em> I had a wildcard A record set up somewhere, when… that is currently not the case, and is indeed the thing from the previous update where I mentioned that I knew what was wrong, but wasn’t sure how to fix it.</p>
<p>If anyone has any ideas, I’d love to hear it.</p>
<hr>
<p>As an aside, there are some great DNS memes out there. Here are two of my favorites.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work/historychannel.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Meme of the History Channel interviewee, saying 'I'm not saying it's DNS, but it's DNS.'"></p>
<figcaption>History Channel actually gets it right.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work/itsalwaysdns.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Meme showing a counter of 'Days since it was DNS', with the count set to 0."></p>
<figcaption>It’s always DNS.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure:} {How} Does {DNS} Work},
  date = {2024-12-17},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“December Adventure: How Does DNS
Work.”</span> December 17, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work">https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>reverse proxy</category>
  <category>traefik</category>
  <category>dns</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 21:06:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-17-december-adventure-how-does-dns-work/itwasdns.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="86" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure: Exploring YAML</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml/mark_yaml.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Two-paned meme image of Mark Hamill, with the first pane normal and the second pane showing indented blocks of Mark Hamill with the undertitle 'Mark Yaml'. Credit: https://www.reddit.com/r/ProgrammerHumor/comments/hwxsgi/ah_yes_mark_yaml/"></p>
<p>Whew, that week went by in a flash. I’ve actually been working on this <code>#DecemberAdventure</code> project these past few days and have made some strides; I just kept running out of time (and inclination) to post about it.</p>
<p>Part of the problem—as an aside—is that I had to close the YAML project space in my VS Code editor in order to <em>open</em> the project space for writing a blog post, which makes it difficult to cross-reference very specific issues and instead relies on “vibes” for writing the post. I’m sure it’s to the detriment of any readers, but I enjoy being as specific as I can. If anyone wants to tell me the magic key combination that allows me to open up multiple project spaces simultaneously in VS Code, please do drop me a line.</p>
<p>Anyway, I hit upon a couple of crucial resources this past week that have helped me make some progress. First, I identified some very specific changes I need to make:</p>
<ul>
<li>Traefik needs to be moved to a <code>traefik</code> namespace</li>
<li>Cert-manager needs to be moved to a <code>cert-manager</code> namespace</li>
<li>Upgrade cert-manager CRDs</li>
<li>Cloudflare API keys need to be moved to <code>cert-manager</code> namespace</li>
</ul>
<p>These are easy enough, only requiring some minor configuration tweaks to the yaml.</p>
<p>But I have <em>a lot</em> of deeper questions about the configuration involved in having Traefik route to external services.</p>
<ul>
<li>A big one: just about all the examples I can find entail doing this, but for Docker-Compose, not kubernetes. Why is that? <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n1vOfdz5Nm8">Here’s one</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-hfejNXqOzA">another one</a>, <a href="https://community.traefik.io/t/external-services-config-yml/24793">another one</a> (I think; it doesn’t actually specify), and <a href="https://community.traefik.io/t/how-to-forward-request-to-external-host/23932">another one</a> (same problem).</li>
<li>I did manage to find a <em>few</em> examples using kubernetes: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G4CmbYL9UPg">here’s one</a> (2+ years old), <a href="https://community.traefik.io/t/traefik-k8s-and-an-external-service/6305">another one</a> (4+ years old, bordering on useless), <a href="https://community.traefik.io/t/kubernetes-ingress-to-external-service/20001">another one</a> (the answer is not helpful), <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/72484227/traefik-ingress-for-external-service-troubleshooting">another one</a> (also with an unhelpful “answer”), <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/kubernetes/comments/13a2zy2/using_k3s_traefik_installation_to_reverse_proxy/">another one</a> (2+ years old), and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Traefik/comments/16eskh4/external_service_load_balancer_in_kubernetes/">another one</a> (this seems the most promising).</li>
<li>Why is my traefik <code>values.yaml</code> <a href="https://github.com/bplein/post-talos-setup/issues/2#issuecomment-2276603841">so much longer</a> than the <a href="https://github.com/techno-tim/launchpad/blob/master/kubernetes/traefik-cert-manager/traefik/values.yaml">one used in TechnoTim’s video</a>? Specifically, why is his traefik configuration devoid of <code>certResolver</code> and <code>env</code>? Is it because I’ve managed to incorrectly configure how much cluster obtains certificates?</li>
<li>Why isn’t there a domain under his <code>ports</code> section? Is this, again, because I seem to be doing certificates differently?</li>
<li>If I’m setting up both a <code>Service</code> and <code>Ingress</code> for each external server I want to reverse proxy behind traefik, what do I set for their ports? And names? And namespaces?</li>
<li>How do I match namespaces with certificates?</li>
</ul>
<p>But anyway. I tried to take a stab at it anyway, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Traefik/comments/16eskh4/comment/jzyc4vu/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button">using this</a>:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">---</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">apiVersion</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> v1</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">kind</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> Service</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">metadata</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> unraid</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">namespace</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> default</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">spec</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">type</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ExternalName</span></span>
<span id="cb1-9"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">externalName</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> unraid.my.local.domain</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ports</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-11"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">port</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">80</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12"><span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">---</span></span>
<span id="cb1-13"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">apiVersion</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> traefik.containo.us/v1alpha1</span></span>
<span id="cb1-14"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">kind</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> IngressRoute</span></span>
<span id="cb1-15"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">metadata</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-16"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> unraid</span></span>
<span id="cb1-17"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">namespace</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> default</span></span>
<span id="cb1-18"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">annotations</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span></span>
<span id="cb1-19"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">kubernetes.io/ingress.class</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> traefik</span></span>
<span id="cb1-20"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">spec</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-21"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">entryPoints</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-22"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> web</span></span>
<span id="cb1-23"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">routes</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-24"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">match</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> Host(`unraid.my.local.domain`)</span></span>
<span id="cb1-25"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">kind</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> Rule</span></span>
<span id="cb1-26"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">services</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-27"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> unraid</span></span>
<span id="cb1-28"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">          </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">namespace</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> default</span></span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>No HTTPS, just regular ol’ port 80. And it worked… kind of. I got a 404 error.</p>
<p>After thinking about it for a couple minutes, I realized: right now I have my local DNS pointing <code>unraid.my.local.domain</code> to the IP address of the <em>traefik proxy</em>, NOT the actual Unraid server. Which I guess would explain the 404, right?</p>
<p>So then, here’s my biggest question: <strong>if I want to route all internal traffic through this proxy, but need the proxy to check with the external DNS server for the right IP address for the server… howwwww does that happen???</strong></p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure:} {Exploring} {YAML}},
  date = {2024-12-13},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“December Adventure: Exploring YAML.”</span>
December 13, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml">https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>yaml</category>
  <category>reverse proxy</category>
  <category>traefik</category>
  <category>vs code</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2024 16:19:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-13-december-adventure-exploring-yaml/mark_yaml.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure: I have a bad feeling about this</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-december-adventure-i-have-a-bad-feeling/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-december-adventure-i-have-a-bad-feeling/bad_feeling.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Meme image of Obi-Wan Kenobi in a fighter from the Star Wars prequel trilogy, stating that he has a bad feeling about this."></p>
<p>Back from the weekend. In general I suspect weekends will be consistent blank spots in my <code>#DecemberAdventure</code>-ing, as activities and parenting and <em>napping</em> make it challenging to do much else. But who knows!</p>
<p>Anyway, today I eased back into things by doing some research into using Traefik as a reverse proxy for external services. Indeed, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/kubernetes/comments/1c0jjde/traefik_but_for_external_use_as_well/">it seems entirely possible</a>, even if that Reddit thread makes <a href="https://xkcd.com/979/">absolutely no mention of the solution</a>.</p>
<p>At this point, I need to figure out a good testing setup. I need a way to get rapid feedback that things are working at each step of the process, rather than flicking the switch at the very end and wondering which of the two dozen steps before it is the one with the problem. Here’s what I’m thinking:</p>
<ul>
<li>Pick a single external service to start with (e.g., JellyFin—it’s already running)</li>
<li>Design a Service and IngressRoute for JellyFin</li>
<li>Add the JellyFin entry to my Firewalla DNS</li>
<li>Do <em>NOT</em> use SSL, at least initially</li>
</ul>
<p>I figure SSL is going to be its own thing, since I need a wildcard DNS cert from Cloudflare and a whole configuration via cert-manager. So this might be more of a “part 2” once I get the above bullets working. Just proving that Traefik can manage reverse proxy requests for external services will be enough proof of concept to move forward with other parts, like SSL.</p>
<p>I guess I’m just apprehensive, since this will require modifying my current Traefik configuration that successfully serves up my Mastodon instance. Obviously I can always revert configurations if everything breaks, but… well, I hate messing with what already works. But I know it’ll be infinitely more flexible and maintainable going forward if I’m successful.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure:} {I} Have a Bad Feeling about This},
  date = {2024-12-09},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-09-december-adventure-i-have-a-bad-feeling},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“December Adventure: I Have a Bad Feeling
about This.”</span> December 9, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-09-december-adventure-i-have-a-bad-feeling">https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-09-december-adventure-i-have-a-bad-feeling</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>yaml</category>
  <category>helm chart</category>
  <category>reverse proxy</category>
  <category>traefik</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-december-adventure-i-have-a-bad-feeling/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 17:33:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-09-december-adventure-i-have-a-bad-feeling/bad_feeling.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure: Y yaml tho</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-december-adventure-y-yaml-tho/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-december-adventure-y-yaml-tho/busted_code.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="AI-generated image of a Python snake breaking out of a monitor that was previously showing broken Python code."></p>
<p>Today was also a pretty minor update, but what felt like a necessary one to making forward progress (and which reveals just how much of a kubernetes neophyte I am, despite now having a few years’ experience with it).</p>
<p>I successfully created a <code>traefik-values.yaml</code> file of my reverse proxy’s configuration. It’s more or less <a href="https://github.com/bplein/post-talos-setup/issues/2#issuecomment-2276603841">this post</a> from the repo I linked a few days ago. Yeah, that’s the extent of what I got done today.</p>
<p>But it speaks to a much greater problem I’ve been wrestling with for awhile: I set up this cluster two years ago with very little experience or guidance, and have only realized since how unsustainable my deployment is. For example, when installing via helm, I downloaded the <em>full helm charts</em> from the various repositories, then modified only the values I needed to change. Which means whenever changes come down the pipe, either from the org itself or because I need to reconfigure or update something, I need to parse through the hundred-line-plus YAML nonsense to find the exact line I need, rather than—what is apparently the standard practice—having a single YAML file that is essentially a “diff”.</p>
<p>So today was a small, but necessary, step toward making the deployment more sustainable. Also, I added <code>*.local.my.domain</code> to the list of URLs under <code>ports.websecure.tls.domains.sans</code>, which will (hopefully) allow for internal DNS routing <em>and</em> SSL certificates.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure:} {Y} Yaml Tho},
  date = {2024-12-06},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-06-december-adventure-y-yaml-tho},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“December Adventure: Y Yaml Tho.”</span>
December 6, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-06-december-adventure-y-yaml-tho">https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-06-december-adventure-y-yaml-tho</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>yaml</category>
  <category>helm chart</category>
  <category>reverse proxy</category>
  <category>traefik</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-december-adventure-y-yaml-tho/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 17:51:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-06-december-adventure-y-yaml-tho/busted_code.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure: Ajani Goldmane</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-05-december-adventure-ajani-goldmane/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-05-december-adventure-ajani-goldmane/ajani.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Artist rendition of the MtG planeswalker Ajani Goldmane. https://magic-the-gathring-lore.fandom.com/wiki/Ajani_Goldmane"></p>
<p>Not much of an update today: work was busy, and we’re still putting the house back together after having contractors here for the better part of the last three weeks.</p>
<p>But I was able to review <a href="https://tappedout.net/mtg-decks/15-11-24-cats/">this Cats deck</a> and <a href="https://edhrec.com/commanders/arahbo-the-first-fang/cats">this Commander suggestion</a> (courtesy of <a href="https://infosec.exchange/@merlin/113596273800710953">this toot</a>, thank you again!), and to start putting together my own version.</p>
<p>It’s quite rough, but what I have so far can be found <strong><a href="https://tappedout.net/mtg-decks/04-12-24-cats/">here</a></strong>. I’ve also gone through all my current MtG cards and pulled out the ones I have (I actually have a Mirror Box!). This process is pretty tedious—it’s one of my (many, lol) personal projects to get a “codex” set up for my collection, and a way of scanning all my cards so they can be automatically added and categorized, but it’s still in the design phase—but it’s done, so now I can start focusing on optimizing the build itself and then determining which cards I still need.</p>
<p>While keeping in mind the whole time that I’m aiming for a single empty spot in the deck for Snowflake to slot in :)</p>
<hr>
<p>Unrelated, but I think I’m just going to refer to the “day” number of December Adventure by the date itself going forward; e.g., today would be “day” 5, not day 2. Starting in the next update, that’s the convention I’ll use. It’s just easier to track it that way and identify which days I missed, than try to keep a running count every time I fire up a new blog post.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure:} {Ajani} {Goldmane}},
  date = {2024-12-05},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-05-december-adventure-ajani-goldmane},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“December Adventure: Ajani Goldmane.”</span>
December 5, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-05-december-adventure-ajani-goldmane">https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-05-december-adventure-ajani-goldmane</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>magic the gathering</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-05-december-adventure-ajani-goldmane/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 16:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-05-december-adventure-ajani-goldmane/ajani.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>December Adventure, 2024 edition</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition/decadv.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="AI-generated image of a snow-covered pine forest with a pathway of footprints leading into the distance, suggesting an adventure ahead."></p>
<p>Geez but I have a backlog of posts to write. Yeah, I’m back. Been a bit! I’m sorry for the radio silence over here these past nearly-six months; it’s been anything but dull, that’s for sure. While there is plenty of catching-up to do, for now that’ll have to wait: instead, I want to discuss this year’s December Adventure!</p>
<p>For those who don’t know, <a href="https://eli.li/december-adventure">December Adventure</a> is something cooked up as a more DIY alternative to <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">Advent of Code</a>. The spirit is the same—basically, work a little bit each day of December—except instead of following a coding and problem solving script, the goal is entirely up to you. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/">I took a stab at this last year and was marginally successful</a>, so I figured I’d take another stab at it this year.</p>
<p>Clearly, I’m off to a mediocre start, given that it’s December 4 and I’m only just posting about it now. But I’m hoping by kicking this snowball down the hill, it gives me some momentum. Or maybe I’m just off in fantasy land.</p>
<p>Fortunately, I have a project in mind: creating a LAN-wide reverse proxy for my homelab!</p>
<section id="motivation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="motivation">Motivation</h3>
<p>In the past couple years, I’ve really taken to the DIY homelab mentality. In addition to setting up and running <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/">my own Mastodon instance</a> for the past two years, I also set up an Unraid box after converting my old home desktop I built in 2015 (which was still perfectly functional!) to a decently powerful server. With endless news cycles about the death of privacy online, I wanted some corner of the internet to be fully under my own control.</p>
<p>However, between the external-facing Mastodon and a growing number of internal services (JellyFin, <a href="https://github.com/magsol/wildlife-cameras/">wildlife cameras</a>, photo albums, and an eventual <a href="https://nextcloud.com/">NextCloud</a> instance), it’d be really nice—if not outright essential, in the case of NextCloud—to not have to remember IP addresses and ports, and instead just type something like <code>https://jellyfin.local.our-home.domain</code>.</p>
<p>I already have a Traefik reverse proxy running on my 6-node Raspberry Pi k3s cluster, but all it does at the moment is serve up requests for the Mastodon instance (which it is also running). <strong>My goal this December Adventure is to reconfigure this reverse proxy to serve all my internal services</strong>.</p>
<p><a href="https://community.traefik.io/t/how-to-use-traefik-on-k3s-as-reverse-proxy-for-multiple-lan-services/25149">I even created a thread about this over at the Traefik forums, but it has yet to receive any kind of response</a>. So if you know anything about reverse proxies, feel free to drop a line there!</p>
<p>I’d also started collaborating with a fellow Mastodon user in the Discord over the summer, but he’s since dropped off and I haven’t been able to follow up. <a href="https://github.com/bplein/post-talos-setup">I posted a few issues on his config</a> so we could compare notes, but I’ve yet to hear anything from him, so it seems like I’m on my own.</p>
<p>Everything I’ve heard and seen so far seems to fall into one of two camps: 1. Here’s how to create a reverse proxy on Docker Compose! 2. Here’s how to create a reverse proxy for services that all run on your kubernetes cluster!</p>
<p>What I’m trying to do differs in that I want the reverse proxy to run on my kubernetes (k3s) cluster, but to <em>have it connect to services that may or may not run on the same cluster, and may in fact be running on physically separate machines</em> (the traefik community post has these details).</p>
<p>This would not only make my life easier as the number of internal LAN services grows, but would allow me to get NextCloud up and running (as it <em>requires</em> its own DNS entry).</p>
</section>
<section id="sub-goals" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sub-goals">Sub-goals</h3>
<p>In addition to the main objective of reconfiguring my Traefik instance as a reverse proxy for multiple internal services, there are a few other things I’d like to do.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Set up a wildcard DNS certificate for internal services</strong>. This will let me add SSL to everything! I already have Cloudflare as my DNS and certificate provider, so this shouldn’t be too much of a hassle.</li>
<li><strong>Install internal NextCloud</strong>. I’ll probably run this on my Unraid server since NextCloud seems to be a pretty beefy application (i.e., beyond what little Raspberry Pis might be able to handle). I don’t want it to be externally accessible, but it still needs a domain name, hence the dependency on the reverse proxy.</li>
<li><strong>Move kubernetes cluster configuration to a repo</strong>. This is a bit of a meta-goal, as it involves some additional subtasks. But the gist is that my kubernetes configuration is currently a glorified shell script, and that absolutely needs to change. I’ve toyed in the past with putting everything into Ansible, but I think to start I just need to separate out the helm charts for each application and put them under version control so they can be more easily updated and maintained. I already have an internal <a href="https://forgejo.org/">forgejo</a> repository running so I could even just use that, though once again the reverse proxy will dramatically simplify its use.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="other" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other">Other</h3>
<p>Oh, and I’d also really like to try and build a <em>Magic: The Gathering</em> deck around this card.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition/snowflake.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>A really neat unofficial Magic card created by the folks at GamersNexus after their “CEO”, Snowflake: a beautiful orange tabby. And yes, that is nail polish on my thumb; hashtag dad life.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If you’re interested in computer hardware you should absolutely follow GamersNexus on YouTube. But they’re also just good, decent people. They’re based in North Carolina and recently did a big fundraiser following Hurricane Helene for three of the local charities (including an animal rescue). One of their newest products is a box of gaming dice, and this particular model came with a custom-made Magic (-like) card (because Steve loves D&amp;D and Magic) of his cat Snowflake (the art was done by his mom! so cool!), and now I’m obsessed with building a Cat deck around this card.</p>
<p>I found <a href="https://tappedout.net/mtg-decks/15-11-24-cats/">this promising white-green Cat deck</a> that I might use to start out, but if anyone knows of any other TappedOut / <a href="https://www.mtggoldfish.com/">MtgGoldfish</a> builds along these lines, please send them my way!</p>
<p>Happy December Adventuring!</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {December {Adventure,} 2024 Edition},
  date = {2024-12-04},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“December Adventure, 2024 Edition.”</span>
December 4, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition">https://magsol.github.io/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>magic the gathering</category>
  <category>homelab</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 10:42:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-12-04-december-adventure-2024-edition/decadv.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Desolation</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/clover_treat.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="An adorable senior white bunny with dark shading on her ears enjoying a treat while sitting in human Mama's lap."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Content warning: discussion of mental health struggles, burglary, and profanity.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>While in a fugue this afternoon, I dug through the day’s mail and came across the latest biweekly edition of the <a href="https://www.ncronline.org/">National Catholic Reporter</a>, to which I have been a faithful subscriber for years; my wife affectionately calls it my “Jesuit rag.” I paged through it, not really paying much attention to the articles, but I stopped <a href="https://www.ncronline.org/culture/what-bluey-teaches-us-about-times-spiritual-desolation">when I hit this one</a>: “What ‘Bluey’ teaches us about times of spiritual desolation.”</p>
<p>I momentarily shook off my fuzziness and read it. It hit like a punch to the gut (no shortage of those today, for some reason). This paragraph rammed it home:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Desolation, as Ignatian spiritual director and writer Margaret Silf notes, is a spiritual state in which we turn in on ourselves, wallow in negative feelings and find ourselves cut off from community. We lose energy (Bandit spends the whole “TV Shop” episode looking for vitamins to give him an energy boost) and we lose sight of, and interest in, what’s important to us.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve always struggled with living in the present and it’s gotten a lot harder in the past decade. Having a kid has made it a mixed bag, though the guilt for realizing I was mentally elsewhere has dramatically increased.</p>
<p>The description for what I’ve been feeling is dead-on: <em>desolation</em>.</p>
<p>I’ve been teetering between professional realities to some extent for almost 3 years now, at times unwilling to commit to a decision, at other times physically incapable. But this year will likely prove definitive, and it’s <em>fucking terrifying</em>. I’ve identified pros and cons, benefits and pitfalls; but there’s <em>so much uncertainty</em> that it becomes this all-encompassing buzz of anxiety that doesn’t quite rise to the level of drowning out everything else, but it’s close. It’s a dull roar with a strong muting effect, exhausting to the point of being very easy to give in until the dull roar is everywhere: a “lights are on but no one’s home” feeling. In a way, committing fully and finally would probably help! And if I’m really honest, I’ve already made a decision—I made it awhile ago—I just haven’t executed on it, not yet.</p>
<p>Somehow, this professional waffling is only one dimension of the desolation that’s been buzzing in my ears.</p>
<p>Yesterday, I heard that while my mom was at home by herself recovering from foot surgery, someone broke into her home. Very fortunately, the intent didn’t seem to be violent; in fact, the person seemed like they were in the middle of a mental health crisis. In some twisted cosmic way, it was almost fortunate that my mom was home, as she is a trained social worker and trauma therapist; the police even commented on how well she’d handled herself. Meanwhile, I can’t help but think about how badly it could have gone; hearing my mom give me the blow-by-blow over the phone when I called her that evening filled me with an awful sense of violation, and a much bigger part of me than I’d like to admit would have preferred that she’d pressed charges.</p>
<p>I received that news via text message while sitting in our vet’s office, listening to the vet tech tell us about the myriad medications we would need to start giving our 9+ year-old senior bunny, Clover (shown in the header photo of this post), to help her stay comfortable as arthritis and other age-related issues takes hold. My wife and I found Clover about half a mile down our street around Memorial Day 2015 during a run together. At the time, we were barely 6 months into our new jobs and location, and we still felt very lost and lonely—finding Clover, getting her taken care of, and welcoming this sweet and sassy bun into our family was one of the few signs that we were where we were meant to be. Finding ourselves nearing the other end is crushing.</p>
<p>After getting home from the vet, I heard that UGA, through some mistake in its software or its processes (they’re always vague about things like this), overpaid me this past month and will be asking for some of the money back. This is the third time in three years that an administrative mistake has resulted in me either having to repay UGA out of my own pocket or never seeing promised money in the first place, and I am… well, I’m <em>fucking furious</em>. I have no recourse, because each of these failures happened somewhere in seventeen layers of bureaucracy, so no individual or group could ever take responsibility. Except for me, of course: since it was my budget mistakenly entered, or my grant mistakenly paid out, or my salary mistakenly given, it’s on me to make the university whole again.</p>
<p>I’m seeing COVID rates start to increase again. Raging antisemitism has a stranglehold with people I once thought were allies and friends. Polls ahead of the November election in the US paint a dire picture of the potential outcome. A longtime and deeply meaningful friendship seems to have changed sometime over the past three years and I don’t know why.</p>
<p>There’s so much noise, so much desolation; all I want to do is turn inward. I know it’s self-defeating—the indecision is paralyzing, which makes any decision completely overwhelming, perpetuating the cycle—but I don’t know how to find that radical acceptance: being completely rooted in the present, for all its faults and uncertainties.</p>
<hr>
<p>I feel an overriding desire to wrap this post up on a positive note but right now I can’t find one, and doing so would be disingenuous. It’d be giving into the desolation by painting a sunnier picture than what actually exists, and in doing so, conveying the subtle but critical message that I don’t need anyone’s help.</p>
<p>Which isn’t true at any level, but holy shit is it difficult to admit: I can’t do this on my own. Even the decision of where my professional life goes from here is not one I can make unilaterally. Maybe some people can; I’m just not one of them. Even if I didn’t have an amazing partner and equal to bounce ideas off of who can see through my every rationalization and weak-ass defense, I’d still seek out the advice of my family, friends, and mentors.</p>
<p>So if there’s any positive ending to this post, I suppose it’s this: I know what I need to do, but I absolutely need help doing it. I can’t beat back the desolation on my own. “We’re all in this together” is something I readily say to everyone—and I mean it!—but I carve out an exception for myself. I’m trying to end that, to reach out when I can tell I’m not only in over my head but am actively digging myself deeper.</p>
<p>Ok, speaking of digging a hole, I lied. <em>This</em> is the positive ending.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VM56KXM4y4c" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Desolation},
  date = {2024-06-13},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-06-13-desolation},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“Desolation.”</span> June 13, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-06-13-desolation">https://magsol.github.io/2024-06-13-desolation</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 22:03:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-06-13-desolation/clover_treat.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 23: Nearing the Finish</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>We’re at day 23 of <code>#WeblogPoMo2024</code>, and this is post number 7 for me—one every three-ish days, give or take. And in today’s post, I’m here to say: I’m not sure how many more posts there will be. I’m in and out of travel for most of the remaining month, and while there will be plenty of downtime (and, assuming, WiFi access), I’m not expecting joy-writing to be high on the priority list.</p>
<p>Simply put: between jet lag, phoning home, and a really nasty bee sting I picked up that’s taking its sweet time healing—not to mention said travel—I don’t really see much time for this.</p>
<p>I could be wrong! There might be another post, or two, or even THREE (gasp). Anything is possible! But given the stress of travel, I want to temper the expectations of my most important of readers: me.</p>
<p>So in possible lieu of any further <code>#WeblogPoMo2024</code> posts, please enjoy these <em>Homeworld 3</em> screenshots that were actually taken by yours truly.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/motherships.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Two Hiigaran motherships.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/warsage.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>This was a hard mission.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/noctuua27.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The atmosphere on this one was unreal.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/noctuua-fleet.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Gonna be tough for the enemy to break this line.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 23: {Nearing} the {Finish}},
  date = {2024-05-23},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 23: Nearing the
Finish.”</span> May 23, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-23-weblogpomo2024-day-23-nearing-the-finish/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 23 May 2024 18:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 16: Python Profiling Rocks</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I was digging through some code written by somebody else and trying to establish benchmarks against some new data we had just received. In doing so, I noticed the application was spending a <em>lot</em> of time at one particular stage. Upon inquiry, my coworkers said something to the effect of “oh yeah, that part always takes a long time to run.”</p>
<p>In looking through the code in question, some ideas began to form in my head, but I was missing data. So I turned to an old Python friend: <code>cProfile</code>!</p>
<p><code>cProfile</code> is a built-in package—as in, part of the default Python distribution—that performs code profiling and is dead-simple to use. Given that I was interested only in a small slice of the overall program, I did have to dig a bit to understand how to essentially “wrap” a certain part of the program in profiling, so that was new for me.</p>
<p>It basically amounted to:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> cProfile, pstats</span>
<span id="cb1-2"></span>
<span id="cb1-3">profiler <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> cProfile.Profile()</span>
<span id="cb1-4">profiler.enable()</span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">###</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># All the code you want to profile goes here!</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">###</span></span>
<span id="cb1-8">profiler.disable()</span>
<span id="cb1-9">stats <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pstats.Stats(profiler)</span>
<span id="cb1-10">stats.dump_stats(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"outputdir/outputfile.stats"</span>)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>That dumps out the profile information (in a binary format, sorry) to a file. From there, you can spin up something like IPython to read the binary and print out the stats:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb2-1">s <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pstats.Stats(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"outputdir/outputfile.stats"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-2">s.sort_stats(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"tottime"</span>).print_stats()</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>And then you have all the runtime stats of the code enclosed by your profiler! It even helped me identify a strange <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?O(n%5E2)"> search loop; easy to miss, because it was a 1-liner, but was responsible for <em>over 50%</em> of the observed runtime! I probably would never have found it on my own.</p>
<p>For more information, <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/profile.html">check out the docs on the built-in Python profilers</a>!</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 16: {Python} {Profiling} {Rocks}},
  date = {2024-05-16},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 16: Python Profiling
Rocks.”</span> May 16, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>programming</category>
  <category>python</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-16-weblogpomo2024-day-16-python-profiling-rocks/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 21:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 13: Return to Hiigara</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6ojRQyBqtOg"><em>Homeworld 3</em> went live</a>. I’ve actually been playing the game since Friday, May 10, when backers of its original kickstarter got early access.</p>
<p>I’ve been a fan of <em>Homeworld</em> ever since the first game came out in 1999 to little fanfare, despite garnering a much-coveted “Game of the Year” award for being among the first (or the actual first?) truly 3D real-time strategy games. Of course, that wasn’t its only credit: its beautiful and devastating story of an entire people who suddenly found themselves without a home, its haunting soundtrack (“Adagio for Strings” has always hit me differently, thanks to that game), and graphics that were remarkable for its time.</p>
<p>While I may be among the few who enjoyed the maligned expansion <em>Cataclysm</em> (2000), I very very VERY much loved its sequel, <em>Homeworld 2</em> (2003). Fast forward to the early stages of the pandemic lockdown in 2020 to the release of <em>Homeworld: Remastered</em>, which was among the best “remasters” of classic games (<em>Homeworlds</em> 1 and 2!) I have ever played. This came out around the same time as the <em>Homeworld 3</em> kickstarter announcement, which I eagerly backed.</p>
<p>Of course, at the time, the projected release date was Q4 2022. El oh el. Still, it’s clear from both official reviews and my own experience playing the finished game that the developers used the extra time to really lock down the polish.</p>
<p>As with every previous <em>Homeworld</em> game, it’s gorgeous. Jaw-droppingly beautiful. The soundtrack is, yet again, haunting, complete with modern “Adagio” renditions you can hear if you listen closely. And the story is gripping, always somehow managing to harness the vastness of space and imbue it with malign intent, and the only people you can rely on are your comrades-in-mothership.</p>
<p>I won’t spoil anything, but I will post a few screenshots. These aren’t mine—I took a few from a screenshots channel in the <em>Homeworld</em> Discord—as I haven’t finished the game and know for a fact that some depict missions I have not yet encountered.</p>
<p>It’s a wonderful game. Highly recommend.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/battle.PNG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Devs made good on promises to include actual megaliths.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/crash.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>It’s beautiful. Also, this mission is brutal.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/harvest.PNG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Resource collectors harvesting materials inside a giant megalith.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/ice.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>I have not reached this mission yet, but WOW does it look beautiful.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And what gaming session would be complete without a little <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/sidon.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Sidon, my best friend.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 13: {Return} to {Hiigara}},
  date = {2024-05-13},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 13: Return to
Hiigara.”</span> May 13, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>gaming</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-13-weblogpomo2024-day-13-return-to-hiigara/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 21:59:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 10: Homelab extravaganza</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>For today’s <code>#WeblogPomo2024</code>, I wanted to delve a little more into my current Homelab setup, which I’ve only alluded to previously. The <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/">series of blog posts I wrote over a year ago detailing my journey setting up a home Mastodon instance</a> was kind of the spark that started this whole homelab kick. I’ve since retrofitted an old desktop (after <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-25-the-legend-of-makar/">replacing it</a>) as an Unraid server, and have a whole collection of applications already humming along.</p>
<p>My latest efforts have involved getting self-hosted <a href="https://nextcloud.com/">Nextcloud</a>] up and running… which is highly non-trivial. I’ve wanted off Dropbox for quite awhile now (I don’t use anywhere <em>near</em> the 2TB allocated in the base paid plan, but I definitely use a lot more than the 2GB allowed in the free tier… oh yeah and numerous privacy issues), but getting Nextcloud running has been a whole thing unto itself. It highlighted an entire hierarchy of reconfigurations and upgrades I needed to undertake across the broader homelab to make Nextcloud possible.</p>
<p>It’s also brought to the forefront the biggest philosophical question I’ve had: <strong>do I allow external access to Nextcloud, or restrict it to local requests only?</strong> Nextcloud is arguably designed for the former, but allows for the latter <em>with some non-standard configuration changes</em>. Obviously I’d like to keep external access to any homelab resources to an absolute minimum—if Mastodon is the only thing that’s externally accessible, I’m fine with that. But a filesharing service with an entire ecosystem of applications is not exactly meant to be confined to a small home network. Hence, my waffling.</p>
<p>For now, I’m going down the path of: keep it internal, but look at ways of allowing selective external access, along the lines of the Tailscales and Twingates of the world, both of which are compatible with Unraid. We’ll see.</p>
<p>Stay tuned!</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 10: {Homelab} Extravaganza},
  date = {2024-05-10},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 10: Homelab
Extravaganza.”</span> May 10, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>homelab</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-10-weblogpomo2024-day-10-homelab-extravaganza/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 May 2024 16:32:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 7: The importance of personal projects</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I don’t think I’m alone in having a menagerie of personal projects. The constituents of said menagerie morph (some slowly, some quickly) as time passes, but it’s never empty. It hasn’t been empty since… high school? Earlier?</p>
<p>Yes, it’s sometimes disheartening to see how little progress I make on so many different fronts. Though, by simply writing out that sentence, I get just an inkling of how ridiculous it sounds.</p>
<p>But these projects, simply, keep me sane. I love creating things; I love building things; I love trying something out in the real world that is often outside the narrow purview of what my immediate employer is looking for. I like trying things for things’ sakes, though sometimes there is also a practical reason.</p>
<p>Lately I’ve been trying to get a new outdoor wildlife camera setup working. It’s a bit more technically complicated than <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/index.html">the one I posted about last year</a> so it’s taking me a bit longer to get things working. But I’m really enjoying doing it.</p>
<p>Personal projects are, after all, <a href="https://angelostavrow.blog/a-love-letter-to-personal-projects">all about delight</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Like most things, I think when it comes to <code>#WeblogPomo2024</code>, it’ll be a cadence of “when I can” as opposed to “EVERY F#$&amp;ING DAY OR DIAF”. After all, <a href="https://www.tumblr.com/rsingwriting/187070321479/i-saw-a-post-talking-about-how-terry-pratchett">if I’m writing a nontrivial fraction of the number of words Sir Terry Pratchett wrote on a daily basis during his illustrious career</a>, I’d say I’m doing pretty well.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 7: {The} Importance of Personal
    Projects},
  date = {2024-05-07},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 7: The Importance of
Personal Projects.”</span> May 7, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-07-weblogpomo2024-day-7-the-importance-of-personal-projects/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2024 16:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 3: mutter</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today, as I was getting back up to speed on work (just in time for the weekend, lol) following travel in the first half of the week, I noticed…something.</p>
<p>Occasionally, my command line would—for lack of a better term—“hitch”.</p>
<p>It became more noticeable as I would type faster; eventually I took to typing gibberish, and it became clear that there definitely was a hitch.</p>
<p>A few minutes of searching (read: tweaking the search parameters, and filtering out “AI”-generated fluff), I found exactly what I was looking for: what is apparently <a href="https://askubuntu.com/a/1509474">a known issue with Ubuntu 22.04.4</a>. The fix, aside from upgrading wholesale to 24.04 (not quite ready yet), was a new <code>mutter</code> install.</p>
<p>I installed it and rebooted, and the hitch is gone. Thank you, internet!</p>
<hr>
<p>Yeah, I missed <code>#WeblogPoMo2024</code> yesterday, so I’m already behind. I’ll continue to do the best I can!</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {\#WeblogPoMo2024, {Day} 3: Mutter},
  date = {2024-05-03},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“#WeblogPoMo2024, Day 3: Mutter.”</span> May
3, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter">https://magsol.github.io/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>writing</category>
  <category>weblogpomo</category>
  <category>open source</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-05-03-weblogpomo2024-day-3-mutter/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 20:24:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
