<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Stochastic Stenography</title>
<link>https://magsol.github.io/index.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://magsol.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Data, donuts, and detours</description>
<image>
<url>https://magsol.github.io/images/logo.png</url>
<title>Stochastic Stenography</title>
<link>https://magsol.github.io/index.html</link>
<height>144</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 19:45:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>2023: A year of extremes</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/landscape.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A picture of a forested landscape at sunset, the sun coming through the bare tree branches."></p>
<p>Where 2022 tried its hardest to kill me, 2023 merely put that killer instinct in neutral. A vast improvement to be sure, but it requires substantial context to fully appreciate.</p>
<p>Ok, maybe that’s not fair to 2023. It had some highs. It also had some lows. All told, 2023 was one of the most bimodal years in my recent memory, perhaps second only to 2020.</p>
<section id="the-good" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-good">The Good</h3>
<ul>
<li>Running (and health + fitness in general) was <em>huge</em> for both me and my wife in 2023. We both set annual running mileage records<sup>1</sup> that outpaced the last couple years by massive margins.</li>
<li>Burnout recovery was tangible. The difference is night and day. Even though I still have a long way to go, I can get through most typical weeks—even the occasional atypically strenuous week—without needing to aggressively power down.</li>
<li>Related to the previous point, I set and held some boundaries, especially around work.</li>
<li>I snagged myself a pretty sweet gig with <a href="https://predxbio.com/">PredxBio</a> as their Principal AI/ML Scientist, starting January 2024. It’s technically a sabbatical (I’ll post about this later in more detail), but I’m really excited for the change.</li>
<li>I’ve picked up a few at-home side projects that I’m really enjoying. This culminated in a <code>#DecemberAdventure</code> over on Mastodon that saw a lot of tinkering around building out a homelab. It’s still in the proof-of-concept stages but I’m really having fun with it!</li>
<li>My wife and I downloaded, played through, and beat <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>. It was pretty much <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_wxU3z9VxOY">the opposite of this, but just as beautiful</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>I cannot underscore enough how groundbreaking it was for us to find a stride<sup>2</sup> with our running and general activity levels.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/running_yearoveryear.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A screenshot from a Garmin Connect progress report, showing huge running mileage increases in 2023 relative to 2022 and 2021."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A Garmin Connect annual mileage summary. The second column is number of runs, third column is total annual mileage, and the last column is average milege per run.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>My own health improved dramatically over the course of the year (especially after being kicked while down by getting COVID on the evening of December 31, 2022): not only did my labs empirically show this improvement at my end-of-year physical, but my two half marathons this year were separated by 6 months (April and October) and by <em>20 minutes</em> (<a href="https://track.rtrt.me/e/DMP-SAVWHALF-2023#/tracker/RW4KTAP2">2:31</a> in April, <a href="https://results.raceroster.com/v2/en-US/results/cbqshhkjvt39snge/detail/egpe264973f6ynms">2:12</a> in October). Both still technically rank among my slowest half marathon finishing times, but the trend is so, so encouraging.</p>
<p>My burnout has also improved dramatically. Where I could barely make it through a work week in 2022, this past year—through careful planning, tracking of my activity and burnout levels, and changing course as needed—I could maintain relatively normal levels of work intensity, while still protecting time for things I needed and wanted (workouts, hobbies, socializing, sleeping).</p>
<p>Part of this burnout management culminated in seeking out an opportunity with PredxBio, a Pittsburgh-based startup in spatial biology. I started with them just this past Tuesday, and I’m thrilled to see where this change of pace takes me.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-bad" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-bad">The Bad</h3>
<ul>
<li>Despite my burnout recovery, I still had some weeks that fried me so badly I needed to clear my schedule to power down. Not often, but more than zero.</li>
<li>I can’t recall a time when I’ve muted, unfollowed, or blocked more people than after October 7. The sudden influx of middle east geopolitical “expertise” was unreal.</li>
<li>My frustration levels with professionals and their uncritical embrace of hype around AI are high. I’ll be the first to admit: AI does cool stuff, but putting everything else aside to build AI into our workflows without acknowledging its real, myriad weaknesses is really disheartening.</li>
</ul>
<p>I submitted a large grant application in late September, and three days later submitted a smaller seed grant application. This was one example of a week where I pushed myself too hard and needed an acute and immediate recovery period. Another example was mid-November: I was in charge of organizing and MCing a panel on “AI in Higher Education” at my department’s annual “Research Day”, and it just happened to coincide with several instructional milestones that same week. In both cases, I needed to clear my schedule for a couple days. I’m fortunate to be able to do that, but I was also completely non-functional those days.</p>
<p>Speaking of the seed grant: I heard back only weeks ago that our application was denied. Certainly not an unlikely outcome, but what really frustrated me was the following:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Due to the volume of proposals, reviewers were not asked to prepare written critiques.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is one of my biggest critiques of the academic system on a whole<sup>3</sup>: feedback either isn’t given, or it’s given too late to use, or—at its most destructive—it’s actively misleading.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-ugly" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-ugly">The Ugly</h3>
<ul>
<li>We started the year with COVID. I got the “long” version.</li>
<li>While burnout recovery has improved my overall bandwidth, it’s made room for long-simmering and unresolved resentment, frustration, and anger around a variety of things. This needlessly consumed a lot of spare cycles and left me run down.</li>
<li>Everything happening in the middle east since early October.</li>
<li>Nihilism crept in this year. <a href="https://infosec.town/notes/9nx5yvs2am7mdbcs">This toot</a> helped point it out to me, but charting a path out is proving difficult.</li>
</ul>
<p>After almost three years of avoiding COVID, my wife and I caught it just before leaving a holiday family reunion in Arizona (though didn’t show symptoms until days after returning home). Our infections were both relatively “minor”—the medical term, though I had a fever hovering just below 102F and she had the worst congestion of her life—but even after I tested negative (it took me almost two weeks to fully clear it), I developed new and lingering respiratory symptoms I’d never had previously. These symptoms lasted for months, nearly into the summer, and included exercise-induced asthma: I would start every run feeling like I was drowning. For the first 20 minutes of a run, my lungs wouldn’t open; I’d feel like I had an elephant sitting on my chest. Eventually my lungs would open, but I’d often be exhausted by that point, making my return to running <a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/10/05/return-of-the-100-mile-month/">very slow and very frustrating</a>. Even now, a year later, I still deal with occasional symptoms, though they have thankfully substantially decreased in intensity and frequency.</p>
<p>I’ve also noticed that my brain has spent a lot more time (and energy) spinning on people who and events that have left me angry or otherwise upset. This has always been a weakness of mine and a regular point of discussion and focused work with my therapists over the years, but in 2023 it got a lot worse.</p>
<p>Resentment was a big problem, especially since I’ve no way of knowing whether the resentment came from something real or because <a href="https://theness.com/neurologicablog/conspiracy-thinking-and-pattern-recognition/">my brain connected disparate events in a way that was completely fictitious</a>.</p>
<p>Combined with real-world events, an impending US Presidential elections with massive implications, and ongoing ambivalence or outright antipathy toward any kind of COVID countermeasures (<a href="https://covid.cdc.gov/covid-data-tracker/#maps_new-admissions-rate-county">despite the current wave that is second only to the massive Omicron wave of late 2021</a>), real nihilism crept in. What kind of world am I raising our daughter in? What kind of world am I handing off to her? What can I possibly do to change any of this? <a href="https://amyjko.medium.com/things-i-hope-for-in-2024-8688c4fbd959">Reading Amy Ko’s hopes for 2024</a> helped, as did the numerous reminders to “think global, act local”.</p>
</section>
<section id="plans-for-2024" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="plans-for-2024">Plans for 2024</h3>
<p>I gave up on resolutions years ago, but I still set goals and make plans for achieving those goals. I also try to prioritize and set my goals up for success.</p>
<p><strong>My biggest priority this year, I think, is to tackle the lingering resentment and default-to-anger</strong>. It drained me so needlessly last year, and there’s never going to be any shortage of things and people to be outraged about / at. I’ve seen a lot of memes with pithy reframings, and while I think those are valuable, they don’t quite hit the mark for me; “consider if a person is worth your anger” still feels too antagonistic, too “me-vs-them.”</p>
<p>Instead—and in line with what we teach our daughter!—I want to allow myself space to feel and observe these reactions, and then to inspect and interrogate them. This not only refocuses on me outside of a combative context, but also forges new neural pathways to make this process second-nature.</p>
<p>My other plans, in no particular order:</p>
<ul>
<li>1000+ miles running (will probably write about this on my running blog soon-ish)</li>
<li>Reorganize my upstairs office, complete with a home server rack to consolidate hardware</li>
<li>Donate donate donate! (there is SO MUCH STUFF around the house we just don’t use)</li>
<li>Set and hold boundaries, especially around work, but also around family and friends</li>
</ul>
<p>There are other smaller items in there too—I’ve learned a lot more about kubernetes networking and foresee an overhaul of my cluster configuration in the near future; I’m also toying with some yard improvement ideas to try and improve the drainage; and I cannot underscore how much I want to clear out the garage, since it’s about 1/3 full of stuff we literally never touch and most likely never will again—but those are on more of a “as time and energy allow” basis.</p>
<p>I wish everyone a wonderful 2024.</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Post-COVID lockdown mileage records. My insane all-time annual record set in 2014 still stands. For now.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>What can I say? The past few years have been a <em>marathon</em>.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>I have an entire draft written about my issues with academia at the institutional, state, and local levels, but I don’t know when, or even if, I’ll post it; if you want to talk about it though, I’m happy to.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2024,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {2023: {A} Year of Extremes},
  date = {2024-01-05},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2024. <span>“2023: A Year of Extremes.”</span> January
5, 2024. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes">https://magsol.github.io/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <category>new year</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2024 19:45:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2024-01-05-a-year-of-extremes/landscape.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Advent of Adventure</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_mordor_full.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A gritty image from behind a small group of heroes, facing down a massive robotic army, in a shattered land that looks a lot like Mordor (generated by DALL-E)."></p>
<p>This past Monday evening, from a tiny cabin in Dahlonega, GA, I turned to my wife and said: <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/what-a-week-huh">“What a week, huh?”</a></p>
<p>We had a much-needed mini-vacation in the middle of the week to recoup and relax. It wasn’t nearly long enough to fully come down from the cortisol high but it at least jump-started the process. We even got a hike in, and did some stargazing. Even as relatively small as Athens is, there’s still a lot of light pollution, the lack of which is breathtaking if you can get a little further out.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/milky_way.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A nighttime shot of the stars, including a faintly-visible Milky Way."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">It’s tough to see, not the least of which because of iPhone 15’s aggressive low-light compensation, but the Milky Way is visible from the left-middle almost to the branches of the tree.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’ve felt guilty—for many reasons; there’s never a shortage, but in this case because I’d originally wanted to participate in this year’s <a href="https://adventofcode.com/">Advent of Code</a>. I was introduced to it two years ago, too late to finish it completely, but at the time I enjoyed it. Last year I was too burned out to get more than a few days in, so I was feeling particularly motivated this year.</p>
<p>But then the end-of-semester shenanigans were an order of magnitude worse than expected, and December entered with a bang and from the mountains I lamented not having logged a single activity.</p>
<p>Then I came across <a href="https://eli.li/december-adventure">December Adventure</a>.</p>
<p>I <em>loved</em> the main idea: the goal is just to write a little bit of code, every day, in the month of December. Or, really, to make progress on any project or projects, a little bit each day.</p>
<p>So consider this not only my inaugural <code>#DecemberAdventure</code> post, but a bit of a catch-up on the things I’ve been doing that have brought me a tiny bit of joy in the dismally oversaturated realities of the past couple months.</p>
<section id="retropie-redux" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="retropie-redux">RetroPie, redux</h3>
<p>Astute readers here may recall that this is <a href="../../posts/2017-01-06-gameify-your-raspberry-pi/index.html">something I’d already done a few years back</a> (ok, <em>several</em> years back, geez). However, that was a Pi 3B+, which did ok with NES and SNES games, but ground to a complete standstill on any 3D games—N64 was beyond it.</p>
<p>Armed with a Pi 4B with 4GB of RAM, I sought to bring RetroPie back! I’d also seen in the documentation that the Nintendo Switch Pro controllers were supported, so getting that working was another goal of mine (rather than the generic USB controllers I’d used last time).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/retropie_open.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">An open view of the Pi inside the SNES enclosure, complete with a fan.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>A few other minor changes from last time: now I had a <a href="https://www.canakit.com/raspberry-pi4-retro-gaming-case.html">cool mini-SNES enclosure</a> for the Pi, which came with room for a single fan to help keep things cool. I was pretty sure the fan was overkill, but I figured, what the heck. I also actually wired the Pi to ethernet, rather than relying on wifi like last time. It took a little bit of adjusting, but it was a change I’d wanted to make to our home network backbone anyway.</p>
<p>The result: a snazzy new RetroPie!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/retropie.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The SNES enclosure, with power and ethernet cables plugged in.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I did still run into some issues with getting the <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/docs/Nintendo-Switch-Controllers/">Nintendo Switch Pro controller</a> working. Specifically, the Bluetooth: <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/forum/topic/34226/cannot-pair-nintendo-switch-pro-controller/7">this issue in the discussion forum</a> mirrored my problems exactly. I could turn on diagnostics for the Pi and see that it was detecting every single button press and stick movement, but for some reason those changes weren’t being propagated to the <a href="https://retropie.org.uk/docs/Controller-Configuration/">emulator software</a>.</p>
<p>In the end, I plugged the Pro controllers into the back of the Pi, and they worked beautifully. It just meant I had to sit on the floor, feet from my TV, in order to play. Like the days of Yore, I suppose.</p>
</section>
<section id="chatgpt-and-dall-e-for-science" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chatgpt-and-dall-e-for-science">ChatGPT and DALL-E, for “science”</h3>
<p>I recently started a new collaboration investigating the utility of commercial LLMs—specifically, <a href="https://platform.openai.com/docs/guides/vision">the new GPT 4 with vision</a>—in understanding, deciphering, and analyzing biomedical image data.</p>
<p>I’ve thrown a little bit of my [OPENLY AVAILABLE] data at it. To use the academic lingo: the performance to date has been decidedly unimpressive. But work continues.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, it’s also given me the opportunity to play around again with image generators (I stopped paying Midjourney a long time ago). In particular, I’ve been keen to see if ChatGPT’s integration with DALL-E has allowed for better <em>iteration</em> on images—carrying over context from previous image prompts to iterate on and improve subsequent images.</p>
<p>With Midjourney, iteration often entailed copy/pasting the previous prompt and making subtle changes that I thought would give me what I was looking for. Here, I was hopeful that, given the conversational interface with ChatGPT, I could now just tweak the things I wanted to change by “having a chat.”</p>
<p>Yet again, I was disappointed. But I did come up with some interesting mash-ups. Inspired by a <a href="ai_symposium_keynote.jpg">recent keynote speech</a> at our Institute of AI Symposium, I wanted to see what favorite universes of mine I could combine.</p>
<p>If anyone has read any of Brandon Sanderson’s Stormlight Archive, they will immediately recognize <a href="https://coppermind.net/wiki/Herald">the ten Heralds</a>. For those who haven’t: think of the Heralds as <em>deeply flawed and damaged, likely insane</em> superheroes. Maybe not “The Boys” level awful, but certainly not your aw-shucks-go-team plucky Avengers.</p>
<p>Well, I tried putting them in different situations. First I tried oil paintings in the medieval ages.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_medieval.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The 10 Heralds, depicted in a medieval oil painting style.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_medieval2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A second attempt at the same image.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In both cases, you may notice… there are more than 10 individuals. I couldn’t find a way to <em>guarantee</em> the number I was asking for, as you’ll see.</p>
<p>Next I tried the Heralds in the Lego universe.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_lego.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The 10 Heralds as LEGO heroes.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Again, it <em>seems</em> as though there are 11 people? And what’s with the bird motif, suddenly? I said nothing about birds.</p>
<p>This continues when I tried putting the Heralds in the Marvel Avengers universe.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_avengers.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The 10 Heralds as the Avengers.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Again, I count 11 individuals, with no fewer than three wearing Iron Man-like powered suits. You can’t <em>all</em> be Iron Man!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_avengers2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The 10 Heralds as the Avengers, again.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Once more, the weird bird motif shows up, despite no mention of birds in the prompt (or any part of the ChatGPT discussion thread). There also only seem to be 9? And Captain America’s shield is just… floating there. I do love that Iron Spider suit, though; I wonder which Herald that is.</p>
<p>From here I tried pitting the Heralds against <em>Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</em> enemies, but set in <em>The Expanse</em> universe.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_mordor.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The 10 Heralds fighting demonic robots on a shattered landscape in a gritty world.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As far as I can tell, there are only 5 Heralds, but otherwise this picture is pretty cool. I love how Mordor-esque the landscape is, and even though the robot army bears no resemblance to anything in <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>, it’s still pretty neat.</p>
<p>The second attempt was a lot closer to what I was looking for:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_vs_guardians.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The 10 Heralds fighting demonic spider-like robots on a shattered landscape in a gritty world.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Still only 9 Heralds as far as I can tell, and again the humanoid robots aren’t recognizable, BUT I <em>love</em> the giant arachnid enemies. I can definitely see that as an <em>Expanse</em>-ification of the classic <em>Breath of the Wild</em> <a href="https://zelda.fandom.com/wiki/Guardian">Guardians</a>.</p>
<p>From here I tried a smattering of other things.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/jez_as_pres.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A United States Presidential headshot of Jezrien, the leader of the Heralds.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/kaladin_botw.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A picture of Kaladin, one of the Knights Radiant, in the art style of Breath of the Wild.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/roci_as_zonai.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A depiction of the Rocinante, the Martian gunship from The Expanse, if it were engineered as a Zonai construct from Tears of the Kingdom.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/roci_in_hateno.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Another depiction of the Rocinante, this time showing it having landed in Hateno Village, in the art style of Breath of the Wild.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Each one of these deviates significantly from what I would have expected, which is not a problem per se. I would say that they do seem to have a tendency to gravitate toward certain modes, and it’s <em>really hard</em> to pull the image generators off those modes.</p>
</section>
<section id="rae-rae-rae-your-robot" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="rae-rae-rae-your-robot">Rae rae rae your robot</h3>
<p>I backed the Luxonis kickstarter last year for the <a href="https://shop.luxonis.com/collections/oak-cameras-1/products/rae">rae robots</a> (Robotics Access for Everyone), and since getting them, they’ve been… tricky.</p>
<p>The forums are full of folks just <a href="https://discuss.luxonis.com/t/rae">trying to get them working</a>, and the associated documentation is extremely sparse to entirely nonexistent. It’s a brand-new product, but the team definitely hasn’t had a chance to catch up on the documentation side.</p>
<p>I ended up getting things working, but it required multiple lines of advice combined in different ways.</p>
<p>Firstly, I started with the <a href="https://docs-beta.luxonis.com/hardware/rae/get-started/?v=Advanced+%28manual%29">Advanced (manual) setup</a>, and this… ended up being impossible, at least if you want your rae to show up on Robothub (which, currently, is the only way to install and run apps). I’ll write a later post documenting this side, but suffice to say, it just doesn’t work.</p>
<p>Secondly, I couldn’t get the hard reset button on the bottom of the rae to work. I may have been doing it wrong. But I found <a href="https://discuss.luxonis.com/d/2328-newbee-quick-starter-to-get-code/3">this excellent post outlining a “soft reset”</a> that worked perfectly.</p>
<p>Thirdly, from the moment I pushed the power button on the rae, I just pointed it at the QR code from Robothub (linked from the <a href="https://docs-beta.luxonis.com/hardware/rae/get-started/?v=RobotHub+Cloud">Cloud setup instructions</a>) and held it there for several minutes. Eventually, the lights started flashing blue at regular intervals and the screen indicated it was connecting to my local wifi network. The rest worked as advertised (even if the lights turn red, apparently this is a known bug).</p>
<p>I haven’t done anything else with them yet, except name them.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/rae.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Two rae robots, with name tags on their tops: one says 'koume', the other says 'kotake'."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Zelda fans, unite.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next">What’s next?</h3>
<p>Consider this my first official entry into <code>#DecemberAdventure</code>, and maybe retroactively through the whole month of December so far.</p>
<p>After today, I’ll try to post regular updates on Mastodon about my <code>#DecemberAdventure</code> activities. Now the semester is <em>largely</em> over—there are still some outstanding obligations, but without class there should be more time for tinkering.</p>
<p>And relaxing.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/coffee_shop_fireplace.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="First-person perspective of the interior of a warm and cozy coffee shop, with a fireplace at one end. There's a coffee table in the middle, a decorated Christmas tree on the right, and other decorations are hung on the mantle. A painting of a reindeer is on the wall above the fireplace."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">More of this, please.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Advent of {Adventure}},
  date = {2023-12-08},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Advent of Adventure.”</span> December 8,
2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure">https://magsol.github.io/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>advent of code</category>
  <category>december adventure</category>
  <category>rae</category>
  <category>retropie</category>
  <category>dall-e</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 15:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-12-08-advent-of-adventure/heralds_mordor_full.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rebuilding</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/athhalf_2023_finish.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="A photo of me crossing the finish line at Ath Half 2023 this past October, holding up my arms in exhausted triumph."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Content warning: discussions of body image, eating habits, diet culture, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_COVID">long COVID</a>. Also, language.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>It has been a very long road back from long COVID.</p>
<p>I can vividly remember where I was a year ago: in the depths of burnout, taking naps almost every day just to get by; weekly migraines; running in place yet accomplishing nothing; maybe getting in a few miles of running per week, and <em>years</em> since I could string together more than about 10 push-ups at once.</p>
<p>And <em>then</em> COVID hit, and even though the active infection was relatively mild, some symptoms stuck around for months after: exercise-induced asthma and sleep apnea being the two most disruptive and frustrating. When I started running again in late January, every single outing was, frankly, infuriating: the first couple miles were agonizing. My lungs wouldn’t open; it felt like drowning. My heart would race. And by the time my lungs finally opened up, I was usually exhausted by then anyway. The Savannah Women’s Half in April rolled around, and <a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/04/03/three-years-later/">even though I finished</a>, it was a 1-minute improvement over the previous October’s Ath Half.</p>
<p>Six months, 1-minute improvement, for my <em>second</em>-slowest half marathon time ever.</p>
<p>This was also when I started seeing a specialist for my breathing. I experienced a brief reprieve in January from the migraines that had been plaguing me for the past several months—burnout recovery!—but they started back up again in late January and through all of February before I realized they were due to my other new long COVID symptom, sleep apnea; an at-home sleep study later confirmed it.</p>
<p>Additionally, I started seeing a dietician. Not an influencer or “lifestyle coach”, someone with an actual fucking degree in nutrition—and someone who came recommended for athletes. I figured if I really wanted to manage these symptoms, I was going to need to hit them from every angle: medical interventions, dietary changes, and a regular workout regimen.</p>
<ul>
<li>The <strong>medical interventions</strong> front has been, by far, the most disappointing. Despite seeing highly recommended pulomnary and sleep specialists, their treatment options have been severely limited by insurance companies refusing to reimburse them. I’ve also been disappointed by their unwillingness to “work the system”, forcing me to advocate for myself despite seeking these people out <em>specifically because I lack specialist knowledge</em>. I’ve had to rely on data from a pulse oximeter I purchased myself to monitor and adjust my nighttime sleep habits, and have incorporated my own series of stretches and pre-run exercises to open up my lungs. It’s all helped, but it’s been <em>in spite of</em> seeing a specialist rather than <em>because of it</em>. tl;dr welcome to healthcare in America.</li>
<li>The <strong>dietician</strong>, conversely, has been an incredible success. We instantly found an amazing rapport and have had monthly check-ups since to evaluate how things have been going to make tweaks as needed. She helped identify how lacking my protein intake was and gave me lots of options for increasing it, many of which my wife and I have seamlessly integrated. She’s also helped improve my fueling <em>before</em> runs and workouts, and best of all she <em>soundly</em> rejects diet culture which I <em>deeply</em> appreciate. Restriction simply doesn’t work; instead, we found a menu rotation that is working for me, and for everything else I try to approach it with mindfulness and intention (that helps a lot with the “oops I just ate an entire bag of chips while standing over my sink” incidents).</li>
<li>The <strong>physical exercise</strong> has also been incredibly successful, though it took a long time and was probably the most consistently frustrating. Exercise takes time and extended commitment, neither of which I had much of in April when work ate up a lot of my energy and every run was guaranteed to start with 15-20 minutes of simulated drowning. But around this time my wife and I started <em>regularly</em> incorporating 2x/week weightlifting sessions, the first time either of us had even entered a weightroom in <em>years</em>, to say nothing of multiple sessions each week. By August I’d added a third weekly session for my own areas of focus, and by September I was experimenting with a <em>fourth</em> (though that was very, very difficult to maintain consistently and so would tend to be “schedule permitting”). It took a LOT of intentional planning—and commitment to saying “no!”—to guard and protect my 3x/week weightlifting sessions AND 4x/week runs.</li>
</ul>
<p>Strava was able to see the consistency, starting in April.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/strava_fitness.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A line plot showing Strava's proprietary fitness indicator over the last calendary year. It increases sharply in March and April and remains there through the rest of the  year."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Strava’s fitness proxy. Note the sustained levels for the past 6 months.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s taken a long time, but:</p>
<ul>
<li>I stopped wearing my pulse oximeter back in August and haven’t had sleep apnea episodes since July.</li>
<li>The migraines also disappeared entirely around July.</li>
<li>By July, I’d started clocking longer runs than any in the previous 3 years.</li>
<li>In August, I could run 9 miles without walking.</li>
<li>In September, I could run 12 miles without walking, and at a faster pace than I ran 9 back in August.</li>
<li>Also in September, I could bench press multiple reps of over 200lbs in the middle of a larger superset.</li>
<li>In October, I ran Ath Half. While technically it is now my <em>third</em>-slowest half marathon time, I beat my April Savannah Women’s Half time by <em>18 minutes</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>I was deep in the middle of one of my longest weight sessions in years when I took this picture.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/me_gym.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A picture of me in the middle of a weightlifting session, looking sweaty and tired and strong and self-conscious."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Mid lift session photo.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Normally, I <em>hate</em> photos like this. Further, I don’t particularly like how I look. But I wanted to take this picture because, in the moment, I felt <em>strong</em> and <em>powerful</em>, sentiments I hadn’t felt toward myself in quite some time. It was one of the first times in years where I felt like I actually belonged in the weight room. I’ve only just started feeling like I belong with the other local runners, too.</p>
<p>I still have bad days. My breath still occasionally catches and, for a moment, my lungs feel like they’re closing back up; maybe it’s some last vestiges of long COVID, maybe I inhaled some pollutant in the air (plenty to choose from), or maybe it’s in my head. I still get headaches that knock out entire swathes of a given day, though now they’re almost exclusively because of burnout recovery (a very “two steps forward, one step back” process), rather than apnea. Some days I just… push myself too hard, too fast, and I need to back off. My recovery periods are still longer than they used to be—whether this is long COVID related, burnout related, age related, or some combination of all of the above, I don’t know. I still get frustrated with how much slower I still am running than I used to be, in spite of the <em>incredible</em> progress I’ve made over the past 6 months. I still eat tortilla chips straight out of the bag while standing over the sink. I still look at my body in the mirror and critique it.</p>
<p>But even if I don’t get back to running 1:40 half marathons, I’m already back to sub-10 minute/mile half marathons. I’m already back to benching 220lbs. I’m consistently running 20+ miles/week. I’ve run <strong>almost 700 miles this year</strong> (on track for 800+!), complete with <a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/10/05/return-of-the-100-mile-month/">my first 100-mile month in years</a>, after running 308 and 377 miles in each of the last two years. I’m stronger and healthier and happier than I’ve been in such a long time, and I’m so, so grateful for it.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Rebuilding},
  date = {2023-11-09},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-11-09-rebuilding},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Rebuilding.”</span> November 9, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-11-09-rebuilding">https://magsol.github.io/2023-11-09-rebuilding</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>covid</category>
  <category>running</category>
  <category>weightlifting</category>
  <category>food</category>
  <category>health</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Nov 2023 13:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-11-09-rebuilding/athhalf_2023_finish.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="216" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Hero Of Everything</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/link_cece_hat.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="An in-game picture of Link from _Tears of the Kingdom_ with pink hair and dark lipstick, and wearing the Cece hat. Picture from this Polygon article: https://www.polygon.com/legend-zelda-tears-kingdom/23725926/tears-of-the-kingdom-totk-best-hat-outfit-cece-mushroom-hat-how-to-get-slay ."></p>
<p>This is the first of two <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> related blog posts I’ll be making. Don’t worry—there won’t be any story spoilers in either one. But <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/@magsol/110792987901449157">my wife did just beat the game this past week</a> (my game isn’t anywhere near the end), so I did want to put down some spoiler-free thoughts on the topic, as well as more detail surrounding <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/@magsol/110776842879244818">recent discoveries on hybrid-powered flight</a> I’ve been posting about on Mastodon.</p>
<p>In the meantime, I just wanted to put in writing something my wife and I hit on very quickly after starting <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>: the many hats Link wears. Sure, he has a Big Bad he needs to put down—the whole “Hero of hyrule/time/twilight/the skies/winds/dreams/etc” thing—but this is about the <em>side quests</em>. In games prior to, oh I don’t know, 2017, these always included a few non-warrior talents: escorting people places, fetching an item, taking care of animals, and so on.</p>
<p>But <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> (and to an only slightly lesser extent, <em>Breath of the Wild</em>) took this to a whole new level. Just focusing on the main story quest is starting to feel like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_ChQK8j6so8">only doing the bare minimum</a>.</p>
<p>Without further adieu, I give you (this list is most likely incomplete, so please feel free to contribute!):</p>
<p><strong>The List of Roles Link Is “Hired” (Willingly…?) Into Aside From, You Know, Actual Hero-ing in <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>.</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Farmer</li>
<li>Gardener</li>
<li>Construction worker</li>
<li>Lumberjack</li>
<li>Babysitter</li>
<li>Cook</li>
<li>(Electrical / Mechanical) Engineer</li>
<li>Elementary School Teacher</li>
<li>Chauffeur</li>
<li>Journalist</li>
<li>Photographer</li>
<li>Research Assistant</li>
<li>Cartographer</li>
<li>Test driver</li>
<li>Undercover secret agent</li>
<li>Uncle</li>
<li>Historian</li>
<li>Election Official / Campaign Worker</li>
<li>Equestrian</li>
<li>Spelunker</li>
<li>Blacksmith</li>
<li>Miner</li>
<li>General</li>
<li>Privateer</li>
</ul>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {The {Hero} {Of} {Everything}},
  date = {2023-07-30},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“The Hero Of Everything.”</span> July 30,
2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything">https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>video games</category>
  <category>zelda</category>
  <category>tears of the kingdom</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2023 14:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-30-hero-of-everything/link_cece_hat.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Upgrading the Raspberry Pi Cluster</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/setup.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="My home office desk, with the GamersNexus rubber mat, along with all the hardware materials for the cluster upgrade, including: a stack of PoE HAT boxes, a Netgear 8-port PoE switch, a small power brick from Anker with two 2-port USB-to-outlet adapters, and my laptop."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
An ode to time zones
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>As I write this up, I’m sitting in my SciPy hotel room. It’s a nice way to relax and unwind after a <em>long</em> day of travel and tutorials, but I also apologize for any timezone weirdness or general grammar or syntax errors.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>In the seven months since <a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">standing up my own Mastodon instance</a>, the Mastodon team has made quite a few releases. Up until last week, I was running <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/tree/v4.0.2">4.0.2</a>, which had originally been released back in November 2022 when I started this crazy journey.</p>
<p>I’d also been wanting to perform a hardware upgrade of the Pi cluster. The server rack I built back in mid-2022, while effective at protecting the cluster from toddlers, was a mess of cables on the inside: turns out, five stacked Raspberry Pi boards have a lot of associated cabling!</p>
<p>My plan for hardware updates included:</p>
<ul>
<li>installing <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.com/products/poe-plus-hat/">power-over-ethernet (PoE) hardware-attached-on-top (HAT)s</a> on each Raspberry Pi, so I could supply both power and networking through the ethernet cable</li>
<li>rewiring the 3x Raspberry Pi case fans to be USB-powered, rather than depending on connections to the GPIO boards of each Pi</li>
<li>downsizing the power brick inside the server case</li>
</ul>
<p>This all took quite a bit of work. And, oddly enough, the software was the <em>easy</em> part.</p>
<section id="upgrading-mastodon" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="upgrading-mastodon">Upgrading Mastodon</h3>
<p>This was “merely” a matter of running an upgrade using the latest Helm chart from Mastodon’s repository. There was a minor wrinkle: the chart had been <em>substantially</em> updated from the one I used to install Mastodon back in December 2022. It <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart">has its own repository now</a>!</p>
<p>I had to carefully go through the chart I used to originally install Mastodon, and the new chart, to make sure I was correctly transferring old configuration values to the new chart. I really only made two mistakes in this process:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>I forgot to fill in the mailer configuration</li>
<li>When specifying the tag, I first put “4.1.3”, instead of “v4.1.3” 🤦‍♂️</li>
</ol>
<p>Fortunately, both were easy fixes. What was a bit trickier was the re-emergence of a <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/73">well-known race condition</a> in the database migration process. It took three separate re-starts of the upgrade process, but it eventually ran to successful completion, and my instance is now running 4.1.3!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Note
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Of course, <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/releases/tag/v4.1.4">4.1.4</a> was just released 3 days ago as of this writing. Of course.</p>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="hardware-upgrades" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hardware-upgrades">Hardware Upgrades</h3>
<p>If the software upgrades took a day, the hardware upgrades took a week.</p>
<p>I mentioned I wanted to install PoE HATs on each Raspberry Pi so they could draw both their power and network connectivity from a single ethernet connection.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/poe_hat.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A stack of 6 PoE HAT boxes, waiting to be unboxed and installed, one per Raspberry Pi."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">How many HATs does one person need?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>What I didn’t mention is: there’s more to it than that. To power devices using PoE, you also need networking hardware that is PoE-compatible. This meant replacing my standard 6-port unmanaged switch with a PoE-compatible switch.</p>
<p>It also meant upgrading from 6 ports to 8, since I also wanted to add a 6th Pi to the cluster—which, when you include the necessary port for connecting the switch to the <em>rest</em> of the network, means a minimum of 7 ports.</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/poe_switch.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="A Netgear 8-port unmanaged PoE+ switch. Officially, its product number is GS308P."></p>
<p>To start, I had to shut down and disassemble the Raspberry Pi cluster (which you can see in <a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">this post back in January</a>). Here was the result, along with the 6th Pi I wanted to add:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/rpis.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Six Raspberry Pi boards, all on the desk."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">So much pi(e).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>With the Pi cluster itself out of the homemade rack, you can see the interior with all the rest of the cabling:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/rack_interior.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Interior shot of my homemade server rack, which is really just a wooden crate with some cut-outs for intake/exhaust fans and a clear plexiglass side for viewing. Inside the Raspberry Pi cluster has been removed, leaving the original 6-port switch, power brick, ethernet cables, power cables, and fan cables. So many cables."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Cables cables everywhere but not an ounce of space.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Yeah. It was pretty crowded, even without the little stack of 5 Raspberry Pi boards. Clearing some of that out via PoE sounded really, really good.</p>
<p>The first step was to install the PoE HAT on each Raspberry Pi. Here’s a before shot:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/single_pi.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A single Raspberry Pi 4B board, unmodified."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A standard Raspberry Pi 4B.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And here’s what it looks like when I’ve installed a PoE HAT on it:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/pi_hat.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A single Raspberry Pi 4B board, now with a PoE HAT on it."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">A standard Raspberry Pi 4B, now with a PoE HAT on it.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As an aside: this adds a surprising amount of weight to the Pi! By itself it wasn’t all that noticeable, but once I’d re-stacked the Pi cluster, I was more than a little shocked by how much heavier it was! Something to keep in mind.</p>
<p>The server rack I built has three Pi case fans as intake, and previously these were powered by literally hooking them into the 5V GPIO pins of three of the Pi boards. Now that all the Pi boards had HATs on, their GPIO pins were entirely inaccessible. Which was fine, because I’d wanted to convert the intake fans to USB power anyway—I’d done this already for the two exhaust fans, which I had cannibalized from an old desktop RAM cooler.</p>
<p>Fun fact: these old RAM cooler fans were the same size as the Pi case fans, but for some reason were 12V fans (and USB is, by default, 5V), so I needed to leverage <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ohm%27s_law">Ohm’s Law</a> and buy a converter that upped the resistence in order to increase the voltage.</p>
<p>Fortunately, this was not the case for the Pi case fans: they needed 5V, and 5V is what any standard USB plug provides. All that was needed was some minor rewiring so the fan leads connected to the corresponding wires inside a USB cable. The end result looked something like this:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/rewired_fan.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A standard 5V Raspberry Pi case fan with its two cables connected to the corresponding power/ground wires inside a USB cable that has been cut open."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Some minor surgery later and we have a USB powered fan!</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I could now plug all five rack fans (three intake, two exhaust) directly into a new and smaller power brick, courtesy of some USB-to-outlet adapters to help further compress the size.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/power_brick.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A small Anker power brick with three standard outlets on the front, two of which have USB-to-outlet adapters plugged in, and each adapter has two USB ports. With two additional USB ports in the back, there are six USB outlets on the brick to power the five USB fans, and one standard outlet to power the PoE 8-port switch."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">There are two more USB outlets in the back of the brick.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>All that was left at this point was to reassemble the Pi cluster. As I said, I was surprised by the sturdiness of six Pi boards with PoE HATs:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/full_cluster.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="The reassembled Pi cluster, with six Raspberry Pi boards stacked up, each with a PoE HAT."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Behold this fully armed and operational Pi cluster.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It took several days’ worth of spare time to get everything together, but I’m proud to say that when I plugged the power brick into the wall, <em>every</em> single light and fan turned on all at once.</p>
<p>It was beautiful.</p>
<p>And mere minutes after, our Mastodon instance was back up and running, too! No commands or instructions needed on my part. Which is, frankly, impressive: as complex as kubernetes is, and as difficult as it can be to stand up applications in it, it’s remarkably robust once you’ve got it up and running.</p>
</section>
<section id="next-steps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="next-steps">Next Steps</h3>
<p>I’ll probably just enjoy this for a bit 😀</p>
<p>But later, I’ll upgrade Mastodon again. On the hardware end, I don’t really have any additional ideas for the moment! Longer term, though, I have plans to move the Pi cluster into an <em>actual</em> homelab server rack (along with our home NAS, a full-sized home server, and all the networking equipment we have currently lying on the floor).</p>
<p>But that’s for another time 👋</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Upgrading the {Raspberry} {Pi} {Cluster}},
  date = {2023-07-10},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Upgrading the Raspberry Pi Cluster.”</span>
July 10, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster">https://magsol.github.io/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>kubernetes</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <category>hardware</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 21:52:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-07-10-upgrading-the-pi-cluster/setup.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>This post is about burnout</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/burnout.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Midjourney-generated image of an art easel with a picture of a raging fire, anthropomorphized with a giant smile on its face. Meant to convey a ham-fisted 'this is fine' metaphor."></p>
<p>…but before I get to that, I want to talk about a movie I saw recently and a book I read recently.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Caution
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The following section contains some minor character spoilers from the 2023 film <em>Spider-Man: Across the Spider-Verse</em>. No major plot reveals.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>My wife and I were recently able to see an evening showing of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spider-Man%3A_Across_the_Spider-Verse"><em>Across the Spider-Verse</em></a>. It was phenomenal; we loved it. As someone who stuck with the MCU movies a little longer than most of my friends, I’ve been feeling “meh” toward superhero flicks for about a year now. We haven’t seen the newest <em>Black Panther</em>, <em>Ant-Man</em>, nor <em>Guardians</em> movies, nor have we felt an overriding urge to watch them even when they hit streaming (though I’ve heard the <em>Guardians</em> movie is pretty solid, so that may be the exception. Maybe).</p>
<p>The <em>Spider-Verse</em> movies, even though solidly in the superhero genre, have been universally incredible. Possibly helped by the fact that there’s only two of them, with the third due out in March 2024. The animation is beautiful, the writing is top-notch, the humor is subtle and perfectly timed, and the characters are <em>fantastic</em>. I loved how this movie dove more into Gwen’s own background, and I was particularly pulled in by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spider-Man_2099">Spider-Man 2099</a>.</p>
<p>He’s a relectant hero (like all the Spiders), doing what he thinks is right, ultimately trying to prevent what happened to him (which was terrible, even by the generic Spider-Trauma Barometer™️) from happening to anyone else.</p>
<p>Except… he fought too hard for too long. Even surrounded by others, he isolated himself. He made hard decisions, and bit by bit the consequences of those decisions ate him up. He stared into the abyss, and the abyss eventually took up residence. He lost sight of <em>why</em> he started his work in the first place—when you have to repeat “We’re the good guys!” twice in a row, practically shouting it at your subordinates, one has to ask who it is you’re trying to convince—and became the very thing he ostensibly started out fighting against.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Caution
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The following section contains some minor character spoilers from the 2023 novel <em>The Frugal Wizard’s Handbook For Surviving Medieval England</em>. No major plot reveals.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>I also just devoured the latest Brandon Sanderson book, <em>The Frugal Wizard’s Handbook For Surviving Medieval England</em>, which was officially called “Secret Project #2” for most of the past 12 months since his big 2022 Kickstarter. It’s not part of any of Sanderson’s other established universes, so it’s a wonderful standalone novel about a near-future dimension-hopping guy who loses his memories upon arriving in an unknown dimension set in Medieval England. He has to figure out who he is and why he’s in that dimension, as others—both natives of the dimension, and people from his own—are trying to kill him.</p>
<p>I loved the story because, while it had many familiar beats storytelling beats around a journey of self-discovery, its final conceit and ultimate reveal about the character had a surprising amount of depth.</p>
<p>Ultimately, it was a story of a character who’d had a lot of bad breaks in his life, coupled with a few poor decisions, which culminated in internalizing the belief that <em>he was not deserving</em>. When he inevitably failed, he believed he deserved it. His well-meaning “friends” gave him the usual “you need to try harder, good things come to those who try.” Which of course is strictly true, but leaves out important context: when you’ve had a string of failures, either from bad decisions OR simple bad luck—or most realistically, some ugly combination of both—you start internalizing those failures <em>as the default mode</em>.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>You lose a little—and that makes you wonder if you deserve to lose. So you lose some more. And it all compounds. You’re behind, no matter how you scramble to stop it. You’re too far gone.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The memory loss ends up being a godsend, because by the end—when the main character has regained his memories—he can compare himself to someone who, just days before, took action he believed was right <em>without the mental baggage of failure as the default</em>, and for that very reason ended up winning more often than he lost.</p>
<p>But the critial discovery, to me at least, was that belief in oneself does not exist in vacuum. You don’t necessarily believe in yourself because you woke up one morning and made the decision. You also look (through the lens of your own experience) at your wins and losses in the past, and use that assessment to decide <em>whether or not you’re worth believing in</em>. And that self-assessment can be brutal; it can end up digging a hole that is nigh impossible to get out of, perpetuating failure.</p>
<section id="where-theres-smoke" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="where-theres-smoke">Where there’s smoke…</h3>
<p>In January 2015, I started a tenure-track position at the University of Georgia. In August 2021, I was officially promoted to Associate Professor, with tenure. And by early 2022, I was convinced that I needed to leave academia entirely, a sentiment that has not changed since then.</p>
<p>Why leave? For those reasons and all the parts of that thinking that led here, I’ll have a post later. Maybe. I’ve been working on a version of it for nearly two years now, but I’m not yet sure if it will see the light of day. It may just be for me.</p>
<p>For now, the reason is simple: I’m completely and utterly, spiritually and physically and emotionally, so-far-beyond-the-abyss, <strong>burned out</strong>.</p>
<p>Of course, the reasons why the burnout got so bad are legion, and I will concede that many of those reasons are my own fault:</p>
<ul>
<li>I have a hard time asking for help</li>
<li>I enjoy what I do to the extent of saying “yes” to things that sound exciting (everything sounds exciting!) without considering how it will get done</li>
<li>I’ve always been somewhat of a people-pleaser, and so setting hard boundaries is difficult and exhausting, and it’s easier (in the short-term) to give people what they want</li>
</ul>
<p>This has led to a situation where I’ve begun to expect failure as a rule. Not with scientific experiments or with code development—that’s wholly different (at least in my brain), and that’s not what I’m talking about here; if anything, my lab’s science has been one of the bright spots in all this—but rather, interacting with people: I expect that I’ll disappoint them somehow, which becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy because it’s happened <em>so often</em> in the last few years.</p>
<p>And it happened because I was so severely burned out that I could barely function. I mentioned this in my <a href="../../posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/index.html">new year’s post</a>, though not really the full extent of it. Honestly, I’m not sure what its full extent is. If I take a really close look at the contours, I may have been burned out since early 2019, shortly after receiving my NSF CAREER award notice. I’ve been hobbling along ever since.</p>
<p>This burnout led to anger and resentment, and a feeling of having to single-handedly hold things together: that I was the only one competent enough to do what needed to be done. Inevitably, balls were dropped—because this is not a sustainable approach to literally anything—and the failures mounted, leading to feelings of nihilism and anhedonia.</p>
<p>This went on for years. I stared into the abyss for far too long, and when I had a chance to step back, I did not like the person I was becoming. We’re so far beyond schedule tweaks, productivity hacks, and “write for 30 minutes each day”; we’re well into “I need an entire semester, possibly an entire academic year, off, just to begin the healing process in earnest.”</p>
<p>And yes, that’s ostensibly what sabbaticals are there for. But in a final might-be-hilarious-in-10-years power move, I’ve been denied to even submit a <em>request</em> for a sabbatical because “there’s no one else to teach the class you’ve been assigned for the fall, and there are already 40+ students registered.”</p>
<p>Somewhere around this time in 2022, while I was working for Quansight, I was given the opportunity to do a 3-day online training in PyTorch for a client. In classic “me” fashion, I enthusiastically volunteered. But when the day came, I was so stressed out by the idea of teaching—a primary source of my burnout—that I broke out in <em>full-body hives</em>. That has happened to me only once before, though in that case we traced it to what was most likely improperly cooked shellfish.</p>
</section>
<section id="embrace-the-process" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="embrace-the-process">Embrace the process</h3>
<p><em>Recognizing</em> burnout is important. <em>Counteracting</em> burnout is important. Both of these steps are difficult to ascertain and implement. This blog post about <a href="https://pyfound.blogspot.com/2023/05/the-python-language-summit-2023-burnout.html">burnout among core Python package maintainers</a> addresses some of that. But there’s a third burnout thread I have to constantly remind myself of:</p>
<p>Burnout decimates your physical and mental capabilities, and they don’t return overnight. It’s such a kick in the teeth when just recognizing burnout is so challenging, and moreso to stem the tide, but just because these have been done does not mean life immediately snaps back to normal.</p>
<p>I’ve spent the last couple years wondering why running seems so much harder than it used to be, while running so much slower than I used to. I spent the day after the SciPy 2023 paper submission deadline (just this past Friday evening) kicking myself for not getting the paper done and feeling like a failure because of it. Years ago, debugging Python and PyTorch errors was straightforward, and prototyping machine learning models was relatively easy for me; while writing this paper, every error message was a multi-hour-long block on my progress. Working through them was like wading through molassess, and at the time I couldn’t understand why.</p>
<p>It’s because burnout doesn’t vanish overnight. It impedes your faculties, like sand in joints, simultaneously slowing things down and increasing the resistence. The knee-jerk reaction is to push harder, which flares the burnout and ultimately undoes forward progress. Which feeds into the failure mindset, and thus perpetuates the cycle.</p>
</section>
<section id="not-just-surviving-but-thriving" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-just-surviving-but-thriving">Not just surviving, but thriving</h3>
<p>I’ve been in survival mode for years now, just trying to get through each day and not really seeing more than a week or two ahead. It’s a good way to stay alive, but a terrible way to live. I’ve gone through long stretches where I have no motivation to create, or to learn, or to grow; instead, all my energy is focused exclusively on getting from one day to the next.</p>
<p>I don’t want to simply survive, I want to <em>thrive</em>. I want to build, I want to learn, I want to grow. And as has become very clear over the past few years: <em>that won’t happen for me if I stay in academia</em>. I haven’t been able to make it work, and I’ve been at this for almost 9 years now. I’ve said it jokingly for years, but it’s also the hard truth: academia is a pie-eating contest where the prize is more pie.</p>
<p><strong>So, I’m leaving</strong>. It suffices to say that by prioritizing healing from my burnout, and by extension prioritizing my family and friends and personal interests and hobbies, it is clear beyond any doubt that there is simply no viable universe in which these priorities can be met while remaining in academia. Of course, I’m existentially terrified—who leaves a tenured position for industry?!—but I’m also excited by the mere possibility of thriving.</p>
<p>Burnout recovery is going to take awhile; after all, I spent years getting to this point. But I’ve also spent the better part of the last few months starting the recovery process, and there’s already been noticeable improvement. I have sustainable routines in place that are clearly doing me good, but I can’t make some of the biggest changes while I’m still in academia.</p>
<p>I’ve recognized my burnout, and I’m taking every step I can to make the changes I need to thrive. But I have to keep reminding myself that things won’t improve overnight, even when I’m doing everything right. It’ll take some time for the pea soup in my brain to clear out, and it’s been an agonizingly slow process of rebuiding my physical body (not helped by potential long COVID symptoms, but that’s a post for another day).</p>
<p>But I at least want the <em>chance</em> to thrive. So I’m taking it. Wish me luck.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {This Post Is about Burnout},
  date = {2023-06-06},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-06-05-this-post-is-about-burnout},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“This Post Is about Burnout.”</span> June 6,
2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-06-05-this-post-is-about-burnout">https://magsol.github.io/2023-06-05-this-post-is-about-burnout</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>burnout</category>
  <category>movies</category>
  <category>books</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 22:05:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-06-06-this-post-is-about-burnout/burnout.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My thoughts ahead of Tears of the Kingdom</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/totk_poster.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Official Nintendo poster for The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom."></p>
<p>For those who aren’t following the <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/@daysuntil">increasingly unhinged ravings of my countdown bot on Mastodon</a>, <em>The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</em> is coming out on Friday, May 12.</p>
<p>And for those who’ve only heard in passing–or who have perhaps never heard–of the Zelda video game franchise: its latest installment is coming out this Friday, May 12, and the Zelda community is absolutely <em>giddy</em> with anticipation.</p>
<p>I could wax historical over its 35 years and 20 different games spanning nearly a dozen (more than a dozen?!) different Nintendo consoles; I could swoon over its cultural impact, influencing other genres and changing, perhaps even unknowingly to many people, how game and puzzle creators approach their design; I could go on about the record-shattering success of its predecessor from 2017, <em>Breath of the Wild</em>, and how this is only the second time in the history of the franchise that Nintendo has made a direct sequel to a previous game; and I could blather on <strong>for.ev.er.</strong> on the established Zelda lore and all the branching theories that its rich storytelling has spawned.</p>
<p>But instead of doing any of that, I just want to put forward one small hope for the game: <strong>I really hope that the game opens with a playable Link getting the absolute snot beat out of him by Ganondorf.</strong></p>
<section id="personally-guide-link-to-his-near-demise" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personally-guide-link-to-his-near-demise">Personally guide Link to his near-demise</h3>
<p>From the trailers, we know the game starts with our eponymous heroes stumbling upon Ganondorf, and something happens where they get separated, Link is grievously injured, and the Master Sword is damaged; <a href="https://youtu.be/uHGShqcAHlQ?t=177">here’s the part of the latest trailer where it happens</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s the relevant screenshot of it happening:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/link_injured.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Screen capture from the latest trailer where Ganondorf's malice is damaging the Master Sword and injuring Link."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">This should literally not be possible.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s horrifying on multiple fronts. We know it happens sometime near the very beginning of the game (setting the stage for the whole thing), and we also know—one small tidbit of Zelda lore—that it <em>should not be in any way possible for the Master Sword to be damaged by evil. It just shouldn’t.</em> So the fact that it <em>is</em>, is truly terrifying on its own.</p>
<p>But here’s where I’m hoping the game takes it up one more notch: I’m hoping that part at the beginning, where the questing heroes find Ganondorf and get their asses kicked, is <strong>fully playable</strong>.</p>
<p>There’s precedent for this, in fact it’s happened in at least a few games I’ve played, going back almost 20 years!</p>
<section id="quake-4-2005" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="quake-4-2005">Quake 4 (2005)</h4>
<p>You play the part of a space marine from Earth tasked with helping push back an alien invasion. For most of the first part of the game, you’re working with your unit to sabotage one of the main “conduits” of the alien military that allows them to communicate and coordinate with each other. You’re eventually successful, but right after, a big bad thought killed in Quake 2 suddenly appears—very clearly alive—and you have to fight him.</p>
<p>You lose. You’re guaranteed to lose. But you still have to fight him. Not only that, but you have to stay alive just long enough to see how every strategy you’ve deployed up until this point fails in spectacular fashion. You can’t even dent the guy’s armor.</p>
<p>Of course, what follows is a long cutscene involving a partial assimilation… it’s a neat sequence, but it requires a bit of a, uh, “constitution” for gore.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/quake4_makron.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="First-person screenshot of the first Makron fight from Quake 4."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">The Makron, from the player’s perspective.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="jedi-outcast-2003" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="jedi-outcast-2003">Jedi Outcast (2003)</h4>
<p>You play the role of Kyle Katarn, a mercenary-turned-jedi-turned-mercenary-again. In the pre-sequel-trilogy world, he’s actually the guy who stole the Death Star plans and got them to the Rebellion (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars%3A_Dark_Forces"><em>Dark Forces</em></a>). In the next game (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars_Jedi_Knight:_Dark_Forces_II"><em>Dark Forces II: Jedi Knight</em></a>), Kyle discovers he’s force-sensitive and trains to become a Jedi. In doing so, he brushes so close to the dark side that he instead chooses to cut himself off from the Force entirely.</p>
<p>That’s where 2003’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars_Jedi_Knight_II:_Jedi_Outcast"><em>Jedi Outcast</em></a> picks up: he’s back to being a mercenary. One of his missions puts him in an Imperial research lab that appears to be trying to infuse objects with Force energy (think Force batteries). At the end of the mission, he runs headfirst into the Dark Jedi masterminding the whole thing, Desann.</p>
<p>Desann promptly takes his partner hostage, and when Kyle threatens him with a blaster, Desann fires up his lightsaber and dares Kyle to take his partner back. That cues up a fully-playable fight.</p>
<p>I mean, Kyle is a tried-and-true mercenary and at this point in the game has a pretty decent arsenal, too. But the fight is an absolute joke. Energy weapons? Desann just deflects with his lightsaber. Projectile weapons? He Force Pushes backwards and away from him. And explosives? He levitates back towards you. I don’t think it’s actually possible to land a single hit, but you still have to try, just so you can see how woefully inadequate you are when you bring a blaster to a fight with a fully-trained Dark Jedi.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/jedioutcast_kylevdesann.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Kyle versus Desann digital art, both characters locking lightsabers. Credit to [DeviantArt user wienernose](https://www.deviantart.com/wienernose/art/Kyle-Katarn-vs-Desann-758186366)."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">An artist’s depiction of the fight at the end of the game, where you actually stand a chance of winning.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="all-i-ask" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="all-i-ask">All I ask</h3>
<p>That’s what I’m hoping for from <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em>: a chance to bring everything we stocked up from <em>Breath of the Wild</em> to the opening fight against Ganondorf, and to lose badly in spite of it all, driving home just how much badder this baddie is than the one we faced at the end of the previous game.</p>
<p>It’s hard to oversell just how overpowered Link was by the very end of <em>Breath of the Wild</em> (assuming your play style leans more toward Completionist than Speedrunner, of course); bringing all that might to bear as <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> kicks off and seeing it just break like waves on the surf would be one hell of an opener.</p>
<p>It’d also be a cool bonus if our last completed <em>Breath of the Wild</em> game slotted into a new <em>Tears of the Kingdom</em> game so we started with exactly the same equipment, but I’m not married to that one.</p>
</section>
<section id="oh-and" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="oh-and">Oh, and</h3>
<p>Speaking just for myself: <em>Breath of the Wild</em> was a singularly amazing game, reminding me how much I love to explore and create just for the sake of exploring and creating (not just in video games, either). At the end of the day, I truly don’t care if the opening fight is playable or not. If the Nintendo team can bring that same wonder, that same reward for simple curiosity—kicking over that last rock just for the sake of seeing what’s underneath—then I’ll happily sink another [REDACTED] hours into it.</p>
<p>THREE. MORE. DAYS.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {My Thoughts Ahead of {\_Tears} of the {Kingdom\_}},
  date = {2023-05-09},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“My Thoughts Ahead of _Tears of the
Kingdom_.”</span> May 9, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk">https://magsol.github.io/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>gaming</category>
  <category>zelda</category>
  <category>totk</category>
  <category>tears of the kingdom</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 16:25:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-05-09-thoughts-ahead-of-totk/totk_poster.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Three years later</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/forsyth_park.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Head-on view of the middle of Forsyth Park in Savannah, GA, including the fountain in the middle and trees along both sides of the main walkway."></p>
<p>Oh by the way, I have a second blog.</p>
<p>Like this one, it fell into disuse over the past few years. And like this one, I’ve been trying to revive it recently. I’d always intended for that blog and this one to be completely non-overlapping in their respective content, but life, as they say, finds a way.</p>
<p>(Me. I’m talking about me, here. Of course the blog isn’t alive, jeez.)</p>
<p>At any rate, you most likely won’t see me advertise that blog here ever again, but just this once, I wanted to point to a post I made detailing my half marathon this past weekend in Savannah, GA, and the three-year history that particular event has.</p>
<p><a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2023/04/03/three-years-later/">Here’s the link</a>. Enjoy.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Three Years Later},
  date = {2023-04-04},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-04-04-three-years-later},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Three Years Later.”</span> April 4, 2023.
<a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-04-04-three-years-later">https://magsol.github.io/2023-04-04-three-years-later</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>running</category>
  <category>covid</category>
  <category>pandemic</category>
  <category>getaway</category>
  <category>travel</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2023 16:10:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-04-04-three-years-later/forsyth_park.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon: Conclusions, musings, ramblings, ravings</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/numenor.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Aerial view of an ancient but advanced civilization, an island-nation (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html">Part V: Actually installing Mastodon</a></li>
<li>Conclusions <em>(this post)</em></li>
</ol>
<p>I know what you’re thinking:</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-36347"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/dexhorthy\/status\/856639005462417409","author_name":"dex","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/dexhorthy","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EDeployed my blog on Kubernetes \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/t.co\/XHXWLrmYO4\"\u003Epic.twitter.com\/XHXWLrmYO4\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; dex (@dexhorthy) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/dexhorthy\/status\/856639005462417409?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EApril 24, 2017\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-36347").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>And honestly… you’re not wrong.</p>
<section id="running-mastodon-has-gotten-easier" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="running-mastodon-has-gotten-easier">Running Mastodon has gotten easier</h3>
<p>In the time I spent planning and writing this blog post series, many of the issues and bugs I ran into already have official fixes (I’ve tried to note PRs, whether merged or still open, where relevant throughout the series). The biggest news of note came down just late last week: <a href="https://blog.bitnami.com/2023/02/bitnami-arm-containers-available-at.html">Bitnami’s images on DockerHub now universally support ARM</a>, making practically the entirety of <a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III</a> obsolete.</p>
<p>There are also discussions (perhaps only internally?) around refactoring the Helm chart to pull the prerequisites out entirely, refocusing instead on Mastodon itself.</p>
</section>
<section id="joining-mastodon-has-gotten-easier" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="joining-mastodon-has-gotten-easier">Joining Mastodon has gotten easier</h3>
<p>And honestly, it’s not like there’s a huge crowd of folks looking to run their own Mastodon instances, especially not with such a rich landscape of instances already up and running.</p>
<p>Granted, there doesn’t really seem to be a unified way of <em>finding</em> an interesting instance; that particular aspect of diving into Mastodon still feels very “cannot be found except by those who already know where it is.” That’s a bit orthogonal to the blog series—especially since I set up my own instance not because I couldn’t find what I was looking for, but because I just wanted to see if I could—but still an ongoing consideration.</p>
</section>
<section id="other-notes-on-the-process" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-notes-on-the-process">Other notes on the process</h3>
<p>I do want to strongly underscore <strong>how grateful I am to the Mastodon dev team for all their help through this process</strong>. I would very likely still be mired in getting search up and running without their knowledgeable, kind, and patient assistance. <a href="https://www.patreon.com/mastodon/">Go support Mastodon’s open source work and, as a bonus, receive access to their dev Discord</a>.</p>
<p>The official GitHub repository is also a wealth of information, and I cannot enumerate just how helpful it’s been since they moved the helm chart maintenance and development <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/">into its own repository</a>, separate from the <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/">main Mastodon application</a>.</p>
<p>My biggest gripe with this whole process really just boils down to the complexity of kubernetes and its ecosystem. There is <em>so. much. stuff.</em> to understand to get even the most basic kubernetes applications up and running. Helm is helpful—in a way—because it hides so much of this complexity, but this becomes a double-edged sword when <em>invariably</em> something isn’t working quite right. Frankly, with the lone exception of the <a href="https://github.com/kubernetes-sigs/nfs-subdir-external-provisioner">NFS provisioner</a> I use for storage in kubernetes applications, I have yet to install an application via Helm that <em>didn’t</em> also require diving into the <code>values.yaml</code> and backend templates to figure out what was <em>really</em> going on.</p>
<p>Unfortunately I don’t have an easy answer, either. For someone well-versed in kubernetes and its ecosystem, this whole process probably would have taken a day; for me, it took a month. I’m ok with that, because I learned a lot from the process of doing it myself, but I’m also more cognizant now of just how much I still don’t know about kubernetes.</p>
<p>Until this unfathomably steep learning curve is smoothed out a little, I feel that it’s incumbent upon us who’ve dabbled somewhat in kubernetes to help lift up the folks coming behind us. Hence this blog series!</p>
</section>
<section id="final-final-notes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-final-notes">Final, final notes</h3>
<p>Is there anything I missed? Anything that isn’t clear? Please feel free to drop a comment on this post or any of the previous ones if you have some additional thoughts on the topics.</p>
<p>I’ve also gone back and added links to all the posts in the series to all the other posts in this series, so you won’t have to click through sequentially to see them all.</p>
<p>I really enjoyed putting this series together, and I already have some ideas for similar undertakings, both within and without the world of kubernetes (perhaps I’ll finally have a blog series around something ML and/or CV related, zomg). Until then!</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon: {Conclusions,} Musings, Ramblings, Ravings},
  date = {2023-02-28},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon: Conclusions, Musings, Ramblings,
Ravings.”</span> February 28, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions">https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 28 Feb 2023 09:52:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/numenor.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon, Part V: Installing and configuring Mastodon</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/mastodon_crew.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Close-up of two Mastodon-like sailors on the deck of a ship at sea (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li>Part V: Actually installing Mastodon <em>(this post)</em></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">Conclusions</a></li>
</ol>
<p>Heyyy, we’ve finally arrived! Months and multiple blog posts later, here’s how to actually install a Mastodon instance on your k3s cluster of Raspberry Pi computers!</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">helm</span> dep update</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">helm</span> install mastodon ./ <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--create-namespace</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--namespace</span> mastodon <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-f</span> path/to/custom/values.yaml</span></code></pre></div>
<p>The <code>dep update</code> will pull down any new versions of the Bitnami charts needed to install the prerequisites we went over in <a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III</a>.</p>
<p>The <code>install</code> command creates an application called <code>mastodon</code>, using the templates in the current directory (hence <code>./</code>), creates a new k3s namespace named <code>mastodon</code> for all the pods to occupy, and then the <code>-f</code> flag provides a path to the <code>values.yaml</code> file we customized back in <a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II</a>.</p>
<section id="is-that-it" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="is-that-it">Is that it?</h3>
<p>A lot of things are going to happen at this point.</p>
<p>First, there a couple of pods that will appear as one-time “jobs”, the most notable (to me) of which is the <code>precompile</code> pod. This one in particular <em>can take awhile</em>… or maybe it was just because it was running on little Raspberry Pi SBCs; the 4Bs are certainly fast, but they’re still pretty resource-constrained by workstation or server standards, so be patient here. Just because it’s taking awhile for anything to show up doesn’t mean something is wrong.</p>
<p>Second, there is a db-migrate job that kicks off. Despite the name, this actually happens both if you’re migrating <em>and</em> if you’re installing Mastodon for the first time. For some reason, there’s a race condition among these initial one-time pods, and if the db-migrate job doesn’t kick off right when it’s supposed to, it may never happen; there’s <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/18">an open ticket looking at this problem</a> and a <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/pull/37">PR with a proposed fix that hasn’t yet been merged</a>. It’s something to keep an eye on; there are manual fixes specified in the open issue (basically the pod equivalent of turn-off-and-back-on) that I had to employ at least a couple of times.</p>
<p>Finally, there was an issue with sidekiq not properly registering the ingress task–kind of important for an application that relies heavily on ingress activity! But it required a very simple one-line addition to the <code>values.yaml</code> file, and it’s not even an issue anymore since <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/pull/1">this PR was merged</a> back in early December 2022.</p>
</section>
<section id="yep-thats-it" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="yep-thats-it">Yep, that’s it</h3>
<p>And that’s pretty much it! You should have a shiny new Mastodon instance up and running at this point (hit the ingress endpoint to check it out)! Your work as instance administrator is only just beginning, though–you need to check out all the options you have available in terms of setting up and configuring your instance (creating its welcome message and purpose, setting up how new accounts register, and importing any new emojis you might want), but in terms of command line kubernetes, with the exception of continued maintenance and occasional updates, that’s it!</p>
<p>I’ll have a wrap-up post coming soon with more of my own thoughts on the whole process.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon, {Part} {V:} {Installing} and Configuring
    {Mastodon}},
  date = {2023-02-24},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon, Part V: Installing and
Configuring Mastodon.”</span> February 24, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon">https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2023 17:01:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/mastodon_crew.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon, Part IV: SSL with Let’s Encrypt</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/https_meme.jpeg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Sean Bean LOTR meme, stating: 'One does not simply use HTTPS when it doesn't work' (obtained from imgflip)."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li>Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt <em>(this post)</em></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html">Part V: Actually installing Mastodon</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">Conclusions</a></li>
</ol>
<p>I want to start by saying: I am no expert here. As such, it is not only possible, but is in fact likely, that I was missing something so painfully obvious as to be worthy of derision for the rest of my natural life.</p>
<p>To be fair, that’d be mean, but still very possibly deserved.</p>
<p>When I started the whole Mastodon installation process, I loosely followed the <a href="https://geek-cookbook.funkypenguin.co.nz/recipes/kubernetes/mastodon/">recipe outlined here at Geek Cookbook</a>, which—until this series of blog posts!—was the only resource I could find anywhere on the world wide interwubs on installing Mastodon on kubernetes (thank you again, funkypenguin; <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/funkypenguin">go sponsor him!</a>).</p>
<p>Of course, I could only follow it to a point; I didn’t make use of <a href="https://geek-cookbook.funkypenguin.co.nz/kubernetes/deployment/flux/">flux</a> (though I know I really, really should; that’s a blog series for another time, methinks) so a lot of the constructs weren’t precisely relevant to me. As such there was a lot I had to infer. <a href="https://geek-cookbook.funkypenguin.co.nz/kubernetes/ingress/">Ingress was no exception</a>.</p>
<section id="so-much-traeffik" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="so-much-traeffik">So much tra[e|f]fik</h3>
<p>This bit is actually entirely separate from Mastodon; it just <em>felt</em> like it was part of Mastodon, since it was Mastodon that I couldn’t reach. When SSL is misconfigured, your experience is strictly browser-dependent: in my case, Chrome<sup>1</sup> would throw up myriad warnings and, in regular mode, wouldn’t let me navigate to the page at all. In incognito mode, it would allow me to navigate there provided I clicked a link to acknowledge I was doing something “unsafe”.</p>
<p>So let’s back up a bit. I’m using <a href="https://traefik.io/">traefik</a> as my ingress controller. Not, I should add, because it’s packaged with k3s; I actually disabled that because it’s an old version. Rather, I installed traefik via <a href="https://github.com/traefik/traefik-helm-chart">its official helm chart</a>.</p>
<p>Now. In keeping with my philosophy of doing the simplest thing that gets results, I tried for the http-01 option when it came to <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/docs/challenge-types/">Let’s Encrypt challenge modes</a>, as it’s by far the most straightforward, at least when it comes to configuring the ingress. I had to make only very minor modifications to the traefik helm chart; it ended up looking something like this:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ports</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">websecure</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tls</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">certResolver</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"leresolver"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">domains</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">main</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"quinnwitz.house"</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">certResolvers</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-9"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">leresolver</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">email</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my email&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-11"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">httpChallenge</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">entryPoint</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"web"</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>That’s pretty much it! I made a few other modifications around debugging and logging, and a small addition around load balancing (to account for metallb), but simplicity won the day.</p>
<p>…and lo, did the problems come thence <em>unceasingly</em>.</p>
</section>
<section id="get-problems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="get-problems">GET problems</h3>
<p>Here’s the part that drove me absolutely insane.</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-overflow-wrap code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">E1129</span> 00:45:08.092782       1 sync.go:190] cert-manager/challenges <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"msg"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"propagation check failed"</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"error"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"failed to perform self check GET request 'http://quinnwitz.house/.well-known/acme-challenge/jVKFmi_ulnESi0pCj-KnVC5mPt0RouNcfUOEKcYe9ro': Get </span><span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\"</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">http://quinnwitz.house/.well-known/acme-challenge/jVKFmi_ulnESi0pCj-KnVC5mPt0RouNcfUOEKcYe9ro</span><span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\"</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">: context deadline exceeded (Client.Timeout exceeded while awaiting headers)"</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"dnsName"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"quinnwitz.house"</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"resource_kind"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Challenge"</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"resource_name"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"mastodon-tls-lzwbv-1403372365-523260434"</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"resource_namespace"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"mastodon"</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"resource_version"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"v1"</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"type"</span>=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"HTTP-01"</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>This is what I saw appear over and over on <a href="https://letsdebug.net/">Let’s Debug</a> (thank you for that website, by the way!). No matter what (http-01) configuration I tried, this was what came back: timeouts.</p>
<p>As best I can tell, <a href="https://github.com/cert-manager/cert-manager/issues/3238#issuecomment-1384438850">this recent comment on GitHub</a> miiight identify the source of the problem and how to fix it:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>So basically, your node cannot access http://1.2.3.4/.well-known/whatever and http://your-page.com/.well-known/whatever, but computers on the internet (such as letsencrypt) can.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>though I’m still not certain, because the method for testing this eventuality (<code>dig</code> or <code>curl</code>ing the URL from the kubernetes nodes themselves) worked fine for me.</p>
<p>After (I kid you not) an entire <strong>week</strong> of this, I gave up. It was time to switch to dns-01.</p>
</section>
<section id="its-always-dns" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="its-always-dns">It’s always DNS</h3>
<p>This took more doing. First, I moved my DNS nameservers from Google over to Cloudflare (Google was and continues to be my domain name provider, so initially that’s where my nameservers were, too). The reason for this move was because Google charges for DNS API access (which we’re going to need in a minute), whereas Cloudflare does not<sup>2</sup>.</p>
<p>Second, I created API keys with Cloudflare specifically for modifying DNS entries. The cert-manager documentation has a whole page on dns-01 verification steps <a href="https://cert-manager.io/docs/configuration/acme/dns01/cloudflare/">and uses Cloudflare as its examplar</a>.</p>
<p>FUN LITTLE FACTOID: Using the method outlined in the cert-manager documentation, I still encountered weird errors involving “invalid request headers.” <em>For whatever bloody reason</em>, when creating the <code>Secret</code> that stores the Cloudflare API tokens, I had to use <code>data</code> rather than <code>stringData</code> otherwise it simply wouldn’t work. <a href="https://github.com/cert-manager/cert-manager/issues/3021#issuecomment-861894010">Here’s the solution</a>. It also needs to be in the same namespace as Mastodon. Also also, I needed to use <code>api-key</code>, <code>api-token</code>, and <code>email</code> fields, <a href="https://go-acme.github.io/lego/dns/cloudflare/">since these are specific to the permissions LE will need</a>.</p>
<p>Third, I had to make more modifications to the traefik helm chart. These included flipping the <code>certResolver.leresolver</code> from <code>httpChallenge</code> to <code>dnsChallenge</code>, and also included adding environment variables for each of the <code>data</code> fields in the cloudflare API secret. Here’s what those changes looked like:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">certResolvers</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-2"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">leresolver</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-3"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">email</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my email&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-4"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">dnsChallenge</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-5"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">provider</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> cloudflare</span></span>
<span id="cb3-6"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">resolvers</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-7"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1.1.1.1</span></span>
<span id="cb3-8"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">8.8.8.8</span></span>
<span id="cb3-9"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">env</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-10"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> CF_API_EMAIL</span></span>
<span id="cb3-11"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">valueFrom</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-12"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">secretKeyRef</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-13"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my secret&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-14"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">key</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> email</span></span>
<span id="cb3-15"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> CF_API_KEY</span></span>
<span id="cb3-16"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">valueFrom</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-17"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">secretKeyRef</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-18"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my secret&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-19"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">key</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> api-key</span></span>
<span id="cb3-20"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> CF_DNS_API_TOKEN</span></span>
<span id="cb3-21"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">valueFrom</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-22"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">secretKeyRef</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb3-23"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my secret&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb3-24"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">key</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> api-token</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>The final step was to create a new <code>ClusterIssuer</code>, one that specifically used dns-01 verification. Here’s what it looked like:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb4-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">apiVersion</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> cert-manager.io/v1</span></span>
<span id="cb4-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">kind</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ClusterIssuer</span></span>
<span id="cb4-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">metadata</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-4"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> letsencrypt-prod-dns</span></span>
<span id="cb4-5"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">spec</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-6"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">acme</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-7"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">email</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my email&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb4-8"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">server</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> https://acme-v02.api.letsencrypt.org/directory</span></span>
<span id="cb4-9"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">privateKeySecretRef</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-10"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;cert key&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb4-11"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">solvers</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-12"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">dns01</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-13"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">cloudflare</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-14"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">          </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">apiTokenSecretRef</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-15"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">            </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my secret&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb4-16"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">            </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">key</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> api-token</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>I wouldn’t call this super-complicated, but it definitely wasn’t the ease of http-01 configuration. But unlike http-01, this actually worked!</p>
</section>
<section id="other-musings" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="other-musings">Other musings</h3>
<p>Oddly enough, this was the part that took the longest on the road to getting my own Mastodon instance running. Not the <a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">obfuscated and undocumented network topology hiccups</a>, not the <a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">literally incompatible and also required prerequisites</a>; no, we got to bang our heads against a 9-year old technology that took nearly a week to find a working configuration.</p>
<p>I’ve had some folks suggest <a href="https://github.com/nabsul/kcert">kcert</a> as a drop-in replacement for cert-manager. For specific use-cases it certainly seems as though its simplicity could grease the skids of development; personally, I did not have a chance to try it out before landing on a working dns-01 setup, but I wanted to mention it as others have spoken positively about it.</p>
<p>Another promising bit of technology the Mastodon devs pointed me to was <a href="https://tailscale.com/">Tailscale</a>, which recently released their own implementation of <a href="https://tailscale.com/kb/1153/enabling-https/">HTTPS certificates</a> for nodes on a tailscale network. Traefik has even started working on <a href="https://traefik.io/blog/exploring-the-tailscale-traefik-proxy-integration/">integrating tailscale network overlays into its proxy configuration</a>, so this could be worth looking at instead of LE in the very near future.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Oh hey!
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>As of traefik 3.0 beta 1, <a href="https://tailscale.com/kb/1234/traefik-certificates/">the integration is already present!</a>. Here’s the <a href="https://tailscale.com/blog/traefik-certificate-resolver/">official announcement from Tailscale</a>.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Until next time!</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Yeah yeah yeah I know I need to switch to Brave or Firefox, IN MY SPARE TIME FOLKS.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>At least, not at the rates I’d be using it.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon, {Part} {IV:} {SSL} with {Let’s} {Encrypt}},
  date = {2023-02-16},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon, Part IV: SSL with Let’s
Encrypt.”</span> February 16, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt">https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <category>ssl</category>
  <category>dns</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2023 10:30:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/https_meme.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Setting up a wildlife camera</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/wildlifegen.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Midjourney-generated image of a rabbit in a nightvision style, as if pictured by an infrared camera at night (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<p>For <em>years</em>, I’ve been wanting to set up an outdoor wildlife camera. Somewhere in the <a href="https://pyimagesearch.com/pyimagesearch-gurus/">PyImageSearch forums</a><sup>1</sup> there’s a post from 2017-me remarking on how excited I am to have finally gotten my hands on an Nvidia 1080 Ti and, therefore, sufficient horsepower to chew up streaming video from outdoors.</p>
<p>In case some readers are unaware: <a href="https://www.visitathensga.com/">Athens</a> is a quintessential college town where, even if starting from the middle of downtown, you’re only ever at most 15 minutes from literal cow pastures. As such, encounters with wildlife are frequent and to be expected if you’re spending any decent amount of time here.</p>
<section id="its-always-the-year-of-the-rabbit" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="its-always-the-year-of-the-rabbit">It’s always the year of the rabbit</h3>
<p>There was a stretch of time, also back around 2017 I think, where our bunny Clover would occasionally<sup>2</sup> wake us up in the middle of the night by thumping. Again, for those who may not know, <a href="https://www.rabbitcaretips.com/why-do-rabbits-thump-their-feet/">rabbits will thump if they sense danger</a> as a way of warning those around them. Clover in particular is also known to thump when she’s having fun, but these few times when we woke up and checked, she was doing her best statue imitation in between thumps, strongly suggesting she really was scared of… something.</p>
<p>We never figured out what, exactly. Best guess: her super-sensitive rabbit ears + eyes picked up something prowling outside in the dark that our duller human senses just couldn’t perceive. Which also gave me a specific application for night cameras beyond simple curiosity: to try and figure out what, if anything, was making Clover nervous (I even had an idea to include some kind of seismometer so I could sync up the offline video analysis with Clover’s thumps, but it’s been years since she last woke us up with thumping so I figure I missed the moment).</p>
</section>
<section id="i-normally-like-deer" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="i-normally-like-deer">I normally like deer</h3>
<p>But I was still curious about the nearby wildlife. This only intensified in the summer of 2021: unusually ravenous deer<sup>3</sup> ate all the lilies in our front yard before they even bloomed. An idea formed to sync a night camera up with a programmable drone that could, after identifying the deer in the yard, harass them away from the lilies. Oddly, summer 2022 was a return to normal: only one flower was eaten early on in the season; the other few dozen went through their full lifecycle, never getting eaten.</p>
<p>But even so, I still wanted to see what was cruising around our neighborhood.</p>
</section>
<section id="bring-on-the-over-engineered-solution" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bring-on-the-over-engineered-solution">Bring on the over-engineered solution</h3>
<p>Yes, dear reader–years have passed in this retelling with little to no progress on the wildlife front. I will readily admit this project suffered what most personal projects do. I will say this, though: in my defense, 2018 through 2021 was the back half of my tenure-track appointment. Couple that with welcoming my daughter, and the onset of a global pandemic… yeah. A liiiiittle bit of burnout<sup>4</sup>, plus a LOT of higher-priority items to worry about than a wildlife camera for the sake of curiosity.</p>
<p>But by summer 2022, I finally had something physically taking shape–<a href="../../posts/2022-07-13-the-raspberry-pi-cluster/index.html">head over to my July 2022 blog post to check it out, complete with photos</a>! I even mounted the birdhouse outside, calibrated the camera’s field of view, and wired it all up… but then left it for several more months.</p>
<p>Now I’m <em>finally</em> getting some hard, empirical data on how it’s all working. And man, it’s going to be a challenge to have this work well.</p>
</section>
<section id="technical-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="technical-challenges">Technical challenges</h3>
<p>Legion.</p>
<p>By far the biggest challenge I’m dealing with is <strong>how resource-constrained the Raspberry Pi 3B+ is</strong>. I’m working with 1GB of RAM, though the effective memory available at any given moment is maaaybe 75% of that; as such, <strong>66%</strong> is the safe margin I operate with. Another limitation is the SD card size (effectively the hard drive of the Pi): at least when I purchased it, the limit was 32GB. That’s now no longer the case, but I haven’t gotten around to reformatting it, so it’s still a 32GB limit for now.</p>
<p>This effectively means that capturing lots of video for testing purposes is difficult. Even reasonable resolutions like 1280x720 at 30fps will exhaust the little Pi’s memory after a mere <strong>4 minutes</strong> of video capture, assuming all the buffering was happening in RAM.</p>
<p>I looked into streaming the video directly as it’s captured; that was, after all, the idea I had behind purchasing the 1080 Ti back in 2017. However, the 3B+ wifi operates only on the 2.4GHz band, which… is unfortunately shared by our baby monitor. Thus, whenever the Pi is transferring data over the air, the baby monitor becomes completely unusable.</p>
<p>So the upshot here is</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>I need to dramatically downsample the incoming video feed, and</li>
<li>any real-time processing I want to do (including downsampling) has to be done on the Pi itself</li>
</ol>
<p>I have been looking into things like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_over_Ethernet">power-over-ethernet</a> to try and solve #2 (though it would require running an ethernet cable outside, which has its own challenges), and I’ve been running some experiments on the most effective downsampling methods for #1. I’ve also been strongly considering simply upgrading the Pi to a 4B when they become available again, as they can operate on the 5GHz wifi band, and can go up to 8GB of memory. Together, these two immediate fixes would dramatically simplify the situation. But Pi 4s most likely won’t be readily available again until Q2 this year (a few months from now, at least).</p>
</section>
<section id="logistical-challenges" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="logistical-challenges">Logistical challenges</h3>
<p>There are a ton of unknowns when it comes to what <em>kind</em> of data I can expect. Already the few experiments I’ve run have shown a wide variability in the video I capture in the context of trying to decide on-the-fly what to keep and what to discard.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/raspberrypi/picamera2">Picamera2 library</a> also recently entered “beta” (from “alpha”). While that’s most certainly a positive development, it still means the library is undergoing substantial changes, and so not only may functionality change very suddenly, but–as I’ve already been encountering–existing functionality is often poorly documented, if at all. It took me some time to piece together how to configure both high-res and low-res video streams to capture the <em>full</em> field of view of the camera (relative to the camera’s native resolution), rather than cropping out a section, as is what would happen with most of the configurations in the <a href="https://github.com/raspberrypi/picamera2/tree/main/examples"><code>examples</code> folder</a>.</p>
<p>Oh, yeah: I also have a full-time job, and a toddler. So those are definitely logistics to be considered.</p>
</section>
<section id="experiments" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="experiments">Experiments</h3>
<p>I have run a few experiments to get a feel for what to expect. The <a href="https://github.com/magsol/wildlife-cameras/blob/0881bf2043a0c5e97177105894508e3dfebacee6/src/noir.py">latest commit</a> (as of writing this post) shows what the experiments more or less look like. Here are the highlights:</p>
<ul>
<li>A dual-stream video recording configuration, where the high-res is set to 1640x1232 and the low-res is 410x308.</li>
<li>The camera runs for a fixed period of time (in the script, it’s 8 hours).</li>
<li>During that time, a continuous loop does the following:
<ol type="1">
<li>Grab a frame from the low-res stream.</li>
<li>Convert this frame from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YUV">YUV</a> to grayscale (Picamera2 requires low-res feeds to be in YUV; fortunately, this step doesn’t seem too arduous).</li>
<li>Compare this frame to the <em>previous</em> frame by way of calculating <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mean_squared_error">mean squared error</a> (MSE). This provides some measure of how much has changed from one sequential frame to the next.</li>
<li>If MSE exceeds some threshold, start recording a video with the high-res stream. Continue recording so long as MSE exceeds that threshold.</li>
<li>If MSE drops below that threshold <em>and stays there for a certain length of time</em>, stop the high-res stream.</li>
<li>Hang onto all MSE measurements.</li>
</ol></li>
</ul>
<p>That’s the basic gist. It’s functional, if blunt. Fortunately, I’ve already collected some interesting data. For instance, here’s an MSE plot from one 8-hour experiment I ran. Important to note: these MSE measurements are <em>only</em> from the events that <em>exceeded</em> the MSE threshold (I’m running separate experiments to try and determine what a baseline MSE looks like).</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/detected_motion_mse.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Matplotlib line plot showing multiple variable-length plots of MSE along the y-axis versus time on the x-axis."></p>
<p>One’s first reaction to this plot might be “Huh, there’s a wide variability in the things that can trigger MSE to exceed the threshold!”. And that would most certainly be correct. But even more complicating is the fact <em>ALL of these events are of the same thing</em>: a car driving by on the street. Not only is it not really something I’m interested in–it’s a wildlife camera, after all–but clearly MSE is ill-suited as a method for identifying the <em>kind</em> of event behind it.</p>
<p>I ran a second experiment over 10 minutes to investigate what MSE baselines might look like (and I’m currently running a longer one; results TBD), but basically you have something that looks like this:</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/10min_test.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Matplotlib line plot showing a single plot of MSE along the y-axis versus time on the x-axis."></p>
<p>My take-away from this plot is: given the 30fps capture rate (or very close to it; at least, depending on how much real-time processing I try to cram in), very little changes from one frame to the next. Empirically, it’s a little more than a single pixel. However, there’s a lot this plot <em>doesn’t</em> tell me, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>What are the effects of weather, such as wind or rain, on the baseline MSE? (not a clue)</li>
<li>How does absolute MSE change with respect to resolution, fps, or other camera settings? (in theory, MSE should scale with resolution; fps could at least be simulated by systematically downsampling, though upsampling would be more difficult)</li>
<li>What are the effects of night vs day on MSE? (again, in theory this shouldn’t be a huge deal, as I only plan to operate the camera at night)</li>
<li>How can MSE identify two separate events vs something like a person who stands still long enough to make it <em>seem</em> like two separate events? (it probably can’t)</li>
</ul>
<p>Anyway, I’m running a 24-hour test right now that will hopefully provide at least a little more intuition into the role of MSE vs the real world, if not any outright answers to the above questions.</p>
<p>Finally, I did want to get some feel for the overall performance of the code itself. I wanted to try and understand what I was working with in terms of options for real-time processing. So I ran a profiler on the same 10-minute experiment I ran above, and this is what came back:</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/profiling.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Output of the top `cumtime` hits from running cProfile on the 10-minute MSE experiment. Main take-away is that Picamera2 internals are by far the biggest time sink, by at least an order of magnitude."></p>
<p>This was comforting to see, as I had been worried the real-time conversion of YUV to grayscale may have been a bigger performance hit; turns out, it’s over two orders of magnitude less problematic than Picamera2 internals, and an order of magnitude less so than the <code>numpy.mean</code> function call for calculating MSE (and this is something I might be able to optimize a bit with some clever leveraging of in-memory data structures).</p>
<p>I was even able to look at the timestamping of the MSE calculations themselves to see that, by far, I was very close to the 30fps sampling rate of the camera itself, meaning I definitely have some head room for additional real-time operations. Granted, this concern has always been secondary to memory constraints, but still: it’s good to know where the hard limits are, and where we have some room to operate.</p>
</section>
<section id="ongoing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ongoing">Ongoing</h3>
<p>It’s clear that, if there are animals prowling around at night, they don’t elicit much of a reaction from MSE, meaning I’m going to need smarter methods of teasing them out. One thought I had was considering both MSE magnitude <em>and</em> duration, but for that I’d need a much more thorough understanding of the role of the baseline MSE (hence the 24-hour experiment). Another thought I had was combining this with a <em>window</em> of frames, rather than just instantaneous MSE over a pair of frames. Finally, I also wanted to look into some basic (non-DL) object detection in OpenCV, since considering first-order image features like edges and corners might be more sensitive to small animals walking around while also keeping added computationl and memory demands at a minimum.</p>
<p>Stay tuned!</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>RIP.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Every few months, so not very often. The impressive bit here is that a 4.5lb <em>rabbit</em> could wake up two snoring humans through multiple walls and a closed door.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>We assume. We didn’t have the camera in place to confirm, but we did hear numerous anecdotes from folks also suggesting the deer were weirdly ravenous and less fearful of humans that year.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Hopefully obvious understatement.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Setting up a Wildlife Camera},
  date = {2023-02-15},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Setting up a Wildlife Camera.”</span>
February 15, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera">https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>wildlife</category>
  <category>ir</category>
  <category>camera</category>
  <category>video processing</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 15:57:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-15-calibrating-a-wildlife-camera/wildlifegen.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon, Part III: Configuring and installing the prerequisites</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/https:/imgs.xkcd.com/comics/tech_loops.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="XKCD comic #1579, Tech Loops."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li>Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites <em>(this post)</em></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html">Part V: Actually installing Mastodon</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">Conclusions</a></li>
</ol>
<section id="preamble" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="preamble">Preamble</h3>
<p>As stated previously, the Mastodon image is fully arm64-compatible. However, if and until the dev team chooses to unbundle Mastodon from its dependencies in the Helm chart, we have to worry about multiple applications Mastodon relies on which themselves rely on images that are <em>not</em> arm64-compatible.</p>
<p>This isn’t exactly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dependency_hell">dependency hell</a>, but it did bring to mind a recent blog post by <a href="https://vickiboykis.com/">Vicki Boykis</a>–who you should absolutely follow if you don’t already–about <a href="https://vickiboykis.com/2022/12/05/the-cloudy-layers-of-modern-day-programming/">how layered modern software engineering and programming have become</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Modern software is hard to develop locally, hard to build the internal logic for, and intrinsically hard to deploy, especially so in the case of machine learning. Just take a look at <a href="https://arxiv.org/ftp/arxiv/papers/2205/2205.02302.pdf">the MLOps paper</a>, which I have nightmares about occasionally.</p>
<p>The problem has gotten so bad that you can usually no longer start from scratch and develop and test <a href="https://twitter.com/vboykis/status/1592576567305474049">a single piece of software in a single, preferably local environment</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As someone in the data science and machine learning space for the past decade+, I can definitely say that this is true. So I hope this post provides some clarity so you can proceed with installing arm64-compatible Mastodon without spending as much time as I did getting it to run.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-short-version" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-short-version">The short version</h3>
<p>The upshot is that the three major dependencies of Mastodon–redis, postgres, and elasticsearch–are all <a href="https://bitnami.com/">bitnami</a> images, and <strong>none of bitnami’s images are arm64-compatible</strong>.</p>
<p>(<a href="https://github.com/bitnami/charts/issues/7305">there is a mega-thread open</a> discussing bitnami’s <em>eventual</em> migration to arm64-compatible images, but they’ve made it very clear that it just isn’t a priority for them right now)</p>
<p>In mid-November 2022, <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/22">this issue</a> was posted. I was still working on getting my own Mastodon instance up and running, so it wasn’t until <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/22#issuecomment-1350081697">Dec 1 that I was finally able to respond</a> with something concrete (though by no means a complete picture–I still couldn’t figure out what to do about elasticsearch).</p>
<p>My response should have some familiar notes from the previous post, specifically regarding the modifications that needed to be made to <code>Chart.yaml</code>.</p>
<p>Another user in the issue mentioned the <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/22#issuecomment-1363930695">“bitnami-compat” project</a>, which I highly recommend checking out, but which I didn’t end up using, for reasons I’ll get into later in this post.</p>
<p>The OP on the issue <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/discussions/22319">opened up a Discussion</a>, where I answered with the <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/discussions/22319#discussioncomment-4410612">short version</a> of what this post will contain (along with, again, some content from the last post). You can read that if you like, or continue here! Or both!</p>
<p>The key approach I took: rather than swapping out entire charts, I stuck with the bitnami charts referenced in the Mastodon chart, but modified the <em>images</em> each of the bitnami charts referred to. In this way, I could minimize the amount of yaml reconfiguration I was doing to keep things at a reasonable amount of crazy.</p>
</section>
<section id="postgresql" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="postgresql">postgresql</h3>
<p>PostgreSQL was the easiest change, at least if minimizing “number of switches I needed to flip” is our metric of choice here for determining easy versus difficult.</p>
<p>The only real change I needed to make was how I performed the <code>helm install</code> process of the bitnami chart for postgres. Here’s the command I used:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">helm</span> install postgres bitnami/postgresql <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> global.postgresql.auth.postgresPassword=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"my_postgres_password"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> global.postgresql.auth.username=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"my_postgres_username"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> global.postgresql.auth.password=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"my_postgres_password"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> global.postgresql.auth.database=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"my_postgres_database"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> image.repository=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"postgres"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> image.tag=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"15.0"</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>That’s it. The only <em>real</em> change of note is the <code>image.repository</code> target: it’s pointing to the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/postgres">official PostgreSQL image on DockerHub</a>, which has arm64-compatible images. The other items related to username, password, and database are items that need to be filled in anyway (here or in the <code>values.yaml</code> file), and the tag just ensures I’m using the same version that the bitnami image would have used, again to minimize any downstream conflicts.</p>
<p>And that was it! I used the bitnami <em>chart</em> with the postgres <em>image</em>, and it worked!</p>
</section>
<section id="redis" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="redis">redis</h3>
<p>Next up, our in-memory data broker.</p>
<p>This process was largely the same as with PostgreSQL, with one notable deviation: I also set the flag to put redis in <code>standalone</code> mode, given that my Pi cluster is resource-constrained and couldn’t afford to have the HA version that, I believe, is the default for the bitnami chart.</p>
<p>Here’s the helm command:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">helm</span> install redis bitnami/redis <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> global.redis.password=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"my_redis_password"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> architecture=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"standalone"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb2-4">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> image.repository=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"redis"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb2-5">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> image.tag=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"7.0"</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Again, the password is something we need to set up anyway, the architecture is set to <code>standalone</code> to minimize its in-memory footprint, tag is meant to match with the bitnami version, and finally the <code>image.repository</code> points to the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/redis">official redis image on DockerHub</a> which, like PostgreSQL, has an arm64-compatible version.</p>
</section>
<section id="elasticsearch-opensearch" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="elasticsearch-opensearch"><del>elasticsearch</del> OpenSearch</h3>
<p>I tried to get elasticsearch to work. I really did.</p>
<p>I started off the same way as with postgres and redis: like the first two, there are <a href="https://github.com/bitnami/charts/tree/main/bitnami/elasticsearch#global-parameters">only a few critical global parameters</a> that need to be set, and they’re the usual suspects–change the image registry to point to the official image on DockerHub, change the image tag to match the bitnami image version, and… that’s really about it.</p>
<p>The hang-ups, crashes, and reboots started immediately. Turns out, elasticsearch is <em>incredibly resource-intensive</em>. So I set about trying to set absolutely minimal overheads: setting master and data replicas to 1, constraining the java heap size, and disabling ingest… none of which worked.</p>
<p>Even aside from the resource constraints, there was a second problem. For whatever reason, the bitnami chart for elasticsearch has a <em>second</em> container–the “kernel settings modifier”–that is part of the pod, and which also has an image that, by default, is not compatible with ARM. So in theory, to get elasticsearch to work with the same technique, the following fields would also have to be changed in the helm chart:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode bash code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode bash"><span id="cb3-1">    <span class="ex" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> sysctlImage.registry=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"ghcr.io"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb3-2">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> sysctlImage.repository=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"zcube/bitnami-compat/bitnami-shell"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span>
<span id="cb3-3">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">--set</span> sysctlImage.tag=<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"11.0.0-debian-11-r39"</span> <span class="dt" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>This is a bit different from the changes made with postgres and redis. There is no “official” distribution of the “kernel settings modifier” image, as this is exclusive to bitnami. Instead, we needed to go to the <a href="https://github.com/ZCube/bitnami-compat">bitnami-compat project</a> which is attempting to make bitnami-compatible arm64 images for all the major charts, and which could feasibly serve as drop-in replacements for redis and postgres as well (I just didn’t try them because I got them working before discovering bitnami-compat). But it’s perfect for this situation.</p>
<p>Suffice to say, this completely solved the architectural compatibility issues, but I still could not fix the resourcing problems without fundamentally hobbling elasticsearch to the point of futility.</p>
<p>Instead, I followed some advice from the Mastodon devs who have, unofficially, been able to get <a href="https://opensearch.org/docs/latest/about/">OpenSearch to work as a drop-in elasticsearch replacement</a> in Mastodon.</p>
<p>(Side note: OpenSearch is based on Apache Lucene, which was the progenitor project to <a href="https://mahout.apache.org/">Apache Mahout</a>, for which I’m a member of its PMC! Small world. I love open source &lt;3 )</p>
<p>Turns out, OpenSearch is <em>remarkable</em>, both in its minimal resource usage <em>and</em> with its ease of dropping right in where elasticsearch would go. My only complaint was the chart’s use of a multi-line yaml string in its settings, which–to my limited knowledge and experience, at least–precluded its exclusive command-line use, and forced me instead to modify the <code>values.yaml</code> and pass that directly to helm. Still, there were very few modifications I needed to make–here’s an indicator with line numbers corresponding to <a href="https://github.com/opensearch-project/helm-charts/blob/c6ebc864c92e6d64cb2097269290193b3844a8e7/charts/opensearch/values.yaml">what is <em>currently</em> the latest version of the chart</a> (committed Jan 3, 2023):</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb4-1"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Line 8: again, needed to keep things minimal</span></span>
<span id="cb4-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">singleNode</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="ch" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">true</span></span>
<span id="cb4-3"></span>
<span id="cb4-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Line 22: just to be obnoxiously consistent</span></span>
<span id="cb4-5"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">replicas</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb4-6"></span>
<span id="cb4-7"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># config.opensearch.yml | plugins.security</span></span>
<span id="cb4-8"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Insert the following line just below Line 61</span></span>
<span id="cb4-9"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># *** This might be the single most important change! ***</span></span>
<span id="cb4-10"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">disabled</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="ch" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">true</span></span>
<span id="cb4-11"></span>
<span id="cb4-12"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Added somewhere under persistence, after Line 187</span></span>
<span id="cb4-13"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">storageClass</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;my storage class&gt;</span></span>
<span id="cb4-14"></span>
<span id="cb4-15"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Line 299</span></span>
<span id="cb4-16"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">securityConfig.enabled</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="ch" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">false</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>That’s all I needed. Then by passing the edited <code>values.yaml</code> to <code>helm install</code>, it ran just fine.</p>
</section>
<section id="postamble" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="postamble">Postamble</h3>
<p>That’s it for the prerequisites! At this point, you could pretty much spin up a Mastodon instance as configured. However, before getting to how I went about that process, I wanted to touch on one final problem I ran into, which–despite the nit-picky-ness of getting these arm64-compatible dependencies working–is where I <em>actually</em> spent most of my time trying to get Mastodon up and running: obtaining an SSL certificate through Let’s Encrypt.</p>
<p>Until next time!</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Update: Feb 24, 2023
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Very recently, <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/issues/22#issuecomment-1443232440">this post showed up</a> on a closed Mastodon helm chart ticket: it looks like Bitnami is now <strong>fully supporting ARM-compatible images on their DockerHub</strong> (I checked Postgres and it <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/bitnami/postgresql/tags">does indeed have ARM tags on the builds</a>). I haven’t tried them out as of this update, but in theory it should more or less obviate the need for this entire post! Hooray, progress!</p>
</div>
</div>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon, {Part} {III:} {Configuring} and Installing the
    Prerequisites},
  date = {2023-02-09},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon, Part III: Configuring and
Installing the Prerequisites.”</span> February 9, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs">https://magsol.github.io/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <category>dependencies</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2023 14:39:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/tech_loops.png" medium="image" type="image/png"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon, Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/helmsperson.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Dramatic image of a galleon sailing on stormy seas (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li>Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart <em>(this post)</em></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html">Part V: Actually installing Mastodon</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">Conclusions</a></li>
</ol>
<p>I don’t know about you, dear reader, but when I first started this journey into teaching myself kubernetes, I was elated at the prospect of Helm: a “package manager for kubernetes”, it said! Thank the cloudless heavens; I was getting so bogged down with managing separate yaml files, I was thrilled at the prospect of someone just setting some reasonable defaults and packaging it all together.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/take-this-helmchart.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Spongebob meme base, with text reading 'Take this helm chart they said, everything will work they said.'"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Such a cruel realization.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="introducing-the-mastodon-chart" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introducing-the-mastodon-chart">Introducing the Mastodon chart</h3>
<p>You can find the latest version of the Mastodon chart <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart">here</a>.</p>
<p>I should mention: when I started working on this in early December, the chart was actually still part of the main Mastodon repo! This meant that changes were much slower to be merged, and as a result I had to implement some workarounds that have since been fixed in the newest chart. Even so, I’ll point out 1) any changes I made, 2) whether those changes still need to be made now, and 3) relevant PRs.</p>
<p>The chart repo’s README linked above provides pretty good instructions for getting up and running. Or, in my case, to get some initial error messages that pointed me where I needed to go next.</p>
<p>At the bare minimum, <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart#configuration"><em>everyone</em> has to fill in</a>:</p>
<ul>
<li>the whole <code>mastodon.secrets</code> section (four keys)</li>
<li>the <code>postgres</code> and <code>redis</code> sections (whether or not they’re enabled in the chart)</li>
<li>the <code>mastodon.stmp</code> section for the mailer’s SMTP settings (not <em>technically</em> required, but nobody will be able to register with your instance or reset their passwords without them)</li>
</ul>
<p>Because of my circumstances, I also had to modify the <code>elasticsearch</code> section (that’s another bitnami image that wasn’t ARM-compatible, like redis and postgres; but I’m leaving all three of these for the next post!), the <code>ingress</code> section (because I was running <a href="https://github.com/traefik/traefik-helm-chart">traefik</a> instead of the default nginx), and the <code>mastodon.persistence</code> section (because I was using a local NAS for storage–I know, not recommended for production, but for a two-user instance? no problem).</p>
<p>So with that lengthy introduction and background out of the way, the salient points here and the primary guiding principles in diving into the chart are:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Disabling</em> the dependencies (elasticsearch, redis, postgres) so I could install them myself later (next post!)</li>
<li><em>Adding</em> NAS storage as the primary storage mechanism (I was using <a href="https://github.com/kubernetes-sigs/nfs-subdir-external-provisioner">nfs subdir external provisioner</a>)</li>
<li><em>Configuring</em> ingress to work with traefik instead of nginx</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-easy-stuff-storage-and-ingress" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-easy-stuff-storage-and-ingress">The “easy” stuff: storage and ingress</h3>
<p>Probably the easiest modification to make was the storage. Under <code>mastodon.persistence</code>, there are two main groups: <code>assets</code> and <code>system</code>. They both have their own persistent volumes in case you need to dramatically alter their respective configurations, but I went with the default, adding only one line to each subsection (since <code>storageClassName</code> wasn’t even listed in the default chart, but has templates in the backend that will handle the key-values if provided):</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">persistence</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">assets</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      # -- ReadWriteOnce is more widely supported than ReadWriteMany, but limits</span></span>
<span id="cb1-4"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      # scalability, since it requires the Rails and Sidekiq pods to run on the</span></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      # same node.</span></span>
<span id="cb1-6"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">accessMode</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ReadWriteOnce</span></span>
<span id="cb1-7"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">storageClassName</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> my-nfs-storage-class</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ### ADDED THIS LINE</span></span>
<span id="cb1-8"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">resources</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-9"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">requests</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-10"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">          </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">storage</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> 10Gi</span></span>
<span id="cb1-11"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">system</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">accessMode</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ReadWriteOnce</span></span>
<span id="cb1-13"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">storageClassName</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> my-nfs-storage-class</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ### ADDED THIS LINE</span></span>
<span id="cb1-14"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">resources</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-15"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">requests</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb1-16"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">          </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">storage</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> 100Gi</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>That’s it! Mischief managed.</p>
<p>For ingress, things were a little more complicated. Not because it required more configuration in the chart itself, but because it required more configuration <em>ahead of using the chart at all</em>. The ingress configuration in the Mastodon chart itself masks the hours spent getting traefik set up exactly the way I wanted. Sadly, this is beyond the scope of the Mastodon instance setup (it will definitely appear in a blog post about just getting my k3s cluster off the ground!), but I <em>will</em> discuss configuring the TLS support / SSL certificates in a later post in this series, so stay tuned.</p>
<p>Here was my configuration (changes from the current default are marked, and comments are deleted for brevity):</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ingress</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb2-2"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">enabled</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="ch" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">true</span></span>
<span id="cb2-3"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">annotations</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb2-4"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">cert-manager.io/cluster-issuer</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"letsencrypt-prod-dns"</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ### ADDED - will go over in detail in a future post in this series</span></span>
<span id="cb2-5"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ingressClassName</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> traefik</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  ### MODIFIED - added the ingress class name I used</span></span>
<span id="cb2-6"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">hosts</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb2-7"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">host</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> quinnwitz.house</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  ### MODIFIED - my instance domain name</span></span>
<span id="cb2-8"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paths</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb2-9"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">path</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'/'</span></span>
<span id="cb2-10"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tls</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb2-11"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">    </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">secretName</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> mastodon-tls</span></span>
<span id="cb2-12"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">      </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">hosts</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb2-13"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">        </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> quinnwitz.house</span><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> ### MODIFIED - my instance domain name</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>That’s it! Relatively tame modifications, but belie a groundswell of configuration and wrangling that had already happened. In particular, note the <code>tls.secretName</code> field: I may not have modified it, but I did have to create a Secret named <code>mastodon-tls</code> ahead of deploying the chart! That was part of the magic of cert-manager behind the scenes, communicating with Let’s Encrypt and getting an SSL certificate set up (again, a future post–stay tuned).</p>
</section>
<section id="the-harder-stuff-disabling-dependencies-and-modifying-templates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-harder-stuff-disabling-dependencies-and-modifying-templates">The harder stuff: disabling dependencies and modifying templates</h3>
<p>Ok, disabling the dependencies was actually easy. Here’s all it took:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Go to <code>redis</code>, <code>postgresql</code>, and <code>elasticsearch</code> sections</li>
<li>Each one has an <code>enabled:</code> key–set it to <code>false</code></li>
</ol>
<p>That’s it! They’re disabled. <strong>Your Helm chart is now fully ARM-compatible!</strong></p>
<p>…except by disabling all the bitnami charts, you’ve introduced an insidious bug where, for some reason, the <a href="https://artifacthub.io/packages/helm/bitnami/common">Bitnami Common Library chart</a> can no longer be found. Fortunately, the fix is easy.</p>
<p>Go to the <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/blob/main/Chart.yaml">Chart.yaml file</a> and add a new entry under the <code>dependencies:</code> list:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> common</span></span>
<span id="cb3-2"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">   </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">version</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> 1.x.x</span></span>
<span id="cb3-3"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">   </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">repository</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> https://charts.bitnami.com/bitnami</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Now when you run <code>helm dep update</code> before installing the chart, the Common chart will still be downloaded and everything will work, even with the other bitnami dependencies disabled.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, this leaves us with the trickiest part of the Helm chart modifications: actually tweaking the redis, postgres, and elasticsearch sections (and, in some cases, templates!) to work with the separate instances we’ll spin up later.</p>
<p><strong>Elasticsearch</strong> doesn’t require any extra tweaking, so we can leave that alone for now.</p>
<p><strong>Postgres</strong> needs the following fields:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>postgresqlHostname</code>: postgres automatically spits this out when you succesfully install it for the first time, so just copy/paste from that</li>
<li><code>postgresqlPort</code>: this is almost always 5432, to the point where that’s the default in the helm chart’s backend template</li>
<li><code>auth.database</code>, <code>auth.username</code>, and <code>auth.password</code> / <code>auth.postgresPassword</code> are set <strong>by you, the user</strong> when you install postgres separately; we’ll go over this in the following blog post</li>
<li>it’s very important to note that <code>auth.password</code> and <code>auth.postgresPassword</code> <strong>should have the same value</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>Finally, <strong>redis</strong> needs the following fields:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>hostname</code>: like postgres, this is spit out automatically when you successfully spin up redis for the first time, so take note of it and copy/paste it here</li>
<li><code>password</code>: this is set <strong>by you, the user</strong> when you install redis separately; we’ll go over this in the following blog post</li>
<li>weirdly, I needed to set <code>auth.existingSecret</code> too</li>
</ul>
<p>To the last point, I created the following <code>redis-password.yaml</code> file:</p>
<div class="sourceCode" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode yaml code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode yaml"><span id="cb4-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">apiVersion</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> v1</span></span>
<span id="cb4-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">kind</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> Secret</span></span>
<span id="cb4-3"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">metadata</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-4"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">name</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> mastodon-redis</span></span>
<span id="cb4-5"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">namespace</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> mastodon</span></span>
<span id="cb4-6"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">type</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> Opaque</span></span>
<span id="cb4-7"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">stringData</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span></span>
<span id="cb4-8"><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">  </span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">redis-password</span><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:</span><span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> &lt;same value as password&gt;</span></span></code></pre></div>
<p>Running <code>kubectl apply -f redis-password.yaml</code> into the Mastodon namespace got it working. I still don’t know why I needed both the Secret and the password in the helm chart to get it to work–it may work with just the Secret, or maybe whatever weird situation caused it was fixed and now just the password in the helm chart will work–but this operation was fairly simple and got everything working so I went with it. I <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/pull/20819">created a PR for this</a> a few months back, but it was rolled into a broader PR tasked with migrating the chart over to its own repository, so I’m not sure if its fixes were ever implemented.</p>
<p>There were some changes directly to the <code>templates/configmap-env.yaml</code> file that were needed, but thankfully many of these have already been addressed courtesy of some PRs:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/pull/19678">Fix helm postgresql secret</a> (#19678)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart/pull/6">Allow external redis instance</a> (#6, replaces <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/pull/20322">#20322</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/pull/20370">Add option to configure external postgresql port</a> (#20370)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mastodon/mastodon/pull/19826">Helm chart improved for ingress</a> (#19826)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="thanks-helm" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thanks-helm">Thanks Helm!</h3>
<p>That about does it for setting up the Helm chart and its corresponding values ahead of installing it… which we won’t actually do for a couple more blog posts yet.</p>
<p>For now, I need to rewind a bit to go over 1) how to install the dependencies we just spent an entire blog post disabling and then configuring anyway, and 2) how to get SSL to work.</p>
<p>Once we get those items squared away, then we can circle back to the completed Helm chart and install a functioning Mastodon instance! Isn’t being a sysadmin great?!</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon, {Part} {II:} {The} {Mastodon} {Helm} Chart},
  date = {2023-01-25},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon, Part II: The Mastodon Helm
Chart.”</span> January 25, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart">https://magsol.github.io/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <category>helm</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 16:27:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/helmsperson.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Mastodon, Part I: My home network topology</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/networking_made_easy.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Horrific jumble of networking wires and equipment stylized like Cthulu (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<p><em>This article is part of a series about installing and configuring a Mastodon instance on a cluster of Raspberry Pi computers running k3s. To go back to previous articles in the series, try any of the links below:</em></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html">Introduction</a></li>
<li>Part I: My home network topology <em>(this post)</em></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html">Part V: Actually installing Mastodon</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">Conclusions</a></li>
</ol>
<p>Admittedly, this post in the series will be less “here’s how to spin up your own instance” than “here’s why I had so many problems that are specific just to me”, so if you have a solid handle on your own home network topology and/or are a DNS savant, feel free to skip this post.</p>
<p>For the rest of us mere networking mortals, let me walk you through a network hiccup that has been stymieing my attempt at an honest-to-goodness homelab kubernetes cluster for the better part of the last couple years.</p>
<section id="thanks-a-lot-bezos" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thanks-a-lot-bezos">Thanks a lot, Bezos</h3>
<p>During the height of the pandemic in summer 2020–and somewhat in preparation for the birth of our daughter–I performed some long-overdue home network upgrades. This included 1) switching over to fiber internet, and 2) upgrading to a mesh network, rather than the janky router-plus-extender setup that honestly never really worked all that well. The router itself was already 5+ years old (purchased when we first moved into the house), so it needed an upgrade anyway.</p>
<p>At the recommendation of some friends, I went with <a href="https://eero.com/">eero</a>. Honestly, I’d still recommend it: it’s been rock-solid, with no problems between my Apple devices (MBP, iPad Pro, and iPhone), my wife’s Android+Windows devices (Surface, Pixels), and our myriad <a href="https://twitter.com/internetofshit">internet-of-sh!t devices</a> strewn throughout the house. Literally zero problems, which I honestly can’t even say for our old router.</p>
<p>…with, I suppose, one exception: putting the eeros into bridge mode.</p>
</section>
<section id="bridge-mode-is-not-what-you-think-it-is" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bridge-mode-is-not-what-you-think-it-is">Bridge mode is not what you think it is</h3>
<p>As far as I’m aware, across all devices–from ISP modems to VirtualBox to Docker to home routers–the term “bridge mode” has a common intuition: it means the device that has been placed into bridge mode relinquishes any intelligent packet organizing methods it may have been using before and simply acts as a simple “bridge” between whatever entities it is connected to. As such, it doesn’t really care what those entities are, it just passes traffic between them.</p>
<p>Not so with eeros.</p>
<p>To illustrate, here is what my home network looked like <em>before</em> starting any of this craziness.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/original.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My home network setup pre-Mastodon, where the main eero connects directly to the AT&amp;T modem and acts as the chief router and DHCP server of the household."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Why yes, I did configure MoCA for my home mesh, thanks for asking.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This setup worked, except… see that Raspberry Pi cluster in the bottom left? That’s where I installed k3s for tinkering, but “tinkering” is pretty much all anything amounted to, because eeros have an odd limitation when it comes to port forwarding: <strong>they don’t allow IP-based service forwarding</strong>, or at least, service forwarding that is based <strong>solely</strong> on IP addresses; they also require MAC addresses. When dealing with ephemeral services created by kubernetes clusters on floating IP ranges, there aren’t associated MAC addresses with these services, which makes it impossible to use software-based load balancers like <a href="https://metallb.universe.tf/">metallb</a>, and therefore impossible to deploy multiple services that use similar configurations–like, say, multiple websites: Mastodon and something else.</p>
<p>So the first thing I had to do, were I to run my own instance, was to figure out a network configuration that would allow me to do IP-based port forwarding. I recalled that my old router had this ability, so I figured: let’s just pull that out of retirement and use it purely for port forwarding!</p>
<p>Following was my first attempt. Note the major changes: the router has taken the place of the “main” eero as connecting directly to the ISP modem, and what was formerly the “main” eero is now just a wireless access point, connected to nothing <em>except</em> the router.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/first_bridge_attempt.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My initial attempt at a home network setup that re-integrated my old router which could perform IP-based port forwarding. It took the place of the main eero by connecting to the ISP modem, and what had been the main eero was now just another access point, connected only to the now-unretired router."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">My first attempt at putting the eeros in bridge mode and un-retiring my old router.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Suffice to say, this didn’t work. I mean, it <em>kind of</em> worked: the Raspberry Pi cluster was getting the right traffic forwarded to it. But seemingly random devices on the network would, suddenly and for no reason I could discern, disconnect and refuse to reconnect unless the <em>entire network</em> was rebooted.</p>
<p>Not exactly a tenable situation. So I reverted to the previous configuration where the eeros were in charge while I tried to figure out what was going on.</p>
<p>Fast forward about 8 months. I finally, <em>finally</em> found <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/eero/comments/nxlspa/psa_bridge_mode_is_not_what_you_think_it_is/">this post on Reddit</a> (because why would eero have it in their technical support documents?) from a couple years ago, with this critical element:</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/eero_bridge_network.jpeg" class="img-fluid" alt="Screenshot of one post from the previous Reddit link, summarizing the precise network topology and positioning of the main eero in the sequence that eero expects in order to function correctly in bridge mode."></p>
<p>Apparently, even in bridge mode, there has to be at least one eero that can “see” the entirety of your home network (i.e., all incoming traffic should pass through it).</p>
<p>This… made absolutely no sense to me, as it directly contravened my understanding of “bridge mode”. But I went with it, and retooled my network to follow this new bit of information.</p>
<p>Here was my next attempt. Like my previous attempt, the router is connected directly to the ISP model. However, <em>unlike</em> my previous attempt, what was the “main” eero in the original configuration–while still connected to the router–now sits between the router and <em>the entire rest of the home network</em>, rather than just the router and… whatever devices deign to connect wirelessly to it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/newest_topology.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="My final attempt at a home network setup that re-integrated my old router which could perform IP-based port forwarding. This took into account that at least one eero still needed to be able to see all the incoming traffic, so I made sure there was one situated in between the now-unretired router and the rest of the home network. This seemed to resolve the issues and has been my stable configuration for several months now."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">My final attempt at a network reconfiguration, this time putting one eero ahead of the rest of the home network.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This configuration, while still strange to me, officially works–or at least, it’s worked for the past few months with no issues.</p>
</section>
<section id="load-balancers-green" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="load-balancers-green">Load balancers: green</h3>
<p>With the issue of the k3s Raspberry Pi cluster being able to receive incoming traffic from the wider internet effectively resolved, I could now undertake the process of installing a Mastodon instance on the cluster with gusto.</p>
<p>In the next post, we’ll look at the <a href="https://github.com/mastodon/chart">Mastodon Helm chart</a> in all its glory. Stay tuned!</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Mastodon, {Part} {I:} {My} Home Network Topology},
  date = {2023-01-23},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Mastodon, Part I: My Home Network
Topology.”</span> January 23, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/">https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <category>networking</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 15:44:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/networking_made_easy.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Running your own Mastodon instance on a Raspberry Pi k3s cluster</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/elephant.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Rear view of a sitting elephant gazing at mountains in the distance (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Introduction <em>(this post)</em></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-23-mastodon-home-network-topology/index.html">Part I: My home network topology</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-01-25-mastodon-helm-chart/index.html">Part II: The Mastodon Helm chart</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-09-configuring-and-installing-prereqs/index.html">Part III: Configuring and installing prerequisites</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-16-ssl-with-lets-encrypt/index.html">Part IV: The waking nightmare that is Let’s Encrypt</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-24-installing-and-configuring-mastodon/index.html">Part V: Actually installing Mastodon</a></li>
<li><a href="../../posts/2023-02-28-mastodon-conclusions/index.html">Conclusions</a></li>
</ol>
<p>As I mentioned in my previous post, I spent the last month of last year spinning up my own Mastodon instance (<a href="https://quinnwitz.house/">which you can check out</a>!) I’ve had a Raspberry Pi cluster of 5x Pi 4B modules sitting around for the better part of the last two years<sup>1</sup>. I’ve occasionally toyed with installing <a href="https://k3s.io/">k3s</a> and experimenting with various bits and pieces of kubernetes, but never actually deployed something I found useful.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/pi_cluster.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A very suspicious looking server rack for the five Raspberry Pi computers."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Don’t worry, they’re well protected.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Don’t get me wrong–I do want to go over how I installed and configured k3s on my Raspberry Pi cluster. It’s remarkable how quickly this area of things moves, and the guides I was working off for this were all 2-3 years old, and <em>remarkably</em> outdated. So a more recent tutorial on that basic component would definitely have its niche, I think.</p>
<p>But first, I want to kick off a series of posts detailing how I got a Mastodon instance running! It took a surprising amount of wrangling, so I wanted to share my experience before I forget the tiny details.</p>
<p>Why would you be interested in this series? Aside from the usual rough-and-tumble of installing anything on kubernetes via <a href="https://helm.sh/">helm</a>, the two parts that took the greatest amount of time and effort were 1) getting the Mastodon <em>dependencies</em> to work, and 2) wrestling <a href="https://letsencrypt.org/">Let’s Encrypt</a> into submission. That first point is interesting because while Mastodon itself works just fine on ARM, the default images included in the Mastodon helm chart for the dependencies do <em>NOT</em>, and so it won’t work out-of-the-box on a Raspberry Pi cluster<sup>2</sup>. And the second point was just plain rage-inducing, and I’d love for folks to not have to experience that.</p>
<p>I’ll fill in the links as I write the posts, so that you can bookmark this page if you’d like, though I’ll make sure to include the links on the other posts as well as I write them. In the meantime, don’t hesitate to drop any pointers / corrections / questions!</p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Yes, I did indeed purchase them two years ago. Would’ve been nigh impossible to get them at any time in between 😬↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>As of February 24, 2023, this is no longer true! <a href="https://blog.bitnami.com/2023/02/bitnami-arm-containers-available-at.html">Here’s the announcement from Bitnami</a> of ARM-compatible images↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Running Your Own {Mastodon} Instance on a {Raspberry} {Pi}
    K3s Cluster},
  date = {2023-01-20},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“Running Your Own Mastodon Instance on a
Raspberry Pi K3s Cluster.”</span> January 20, 2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/">https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>k3s</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 16:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-20-mastodon-instance-k3s-rpi-introduction/elephant.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>2022: A year in review</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/broken_sword.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Close-up of a broken sword lying amidst ruins (generated by Midjourney)."></p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Warning
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>There’s going to be <em>language</em> in this post. Consider skipping if you prefer your blog posts merely warmed and with cream; this one is straight out of the pourover.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>2022 was a fucking shitshow.</p>
<p>Forget the transition out of academia that fell flat on its fucking face in the final mile<sup>1</sup>. Forget the actual running that went from runway to runway, gunning the engine and building some speed on occasion but without ever quite taking off. Forget 2022’s parting shot of giving our entirely family COVID within days of the year’s end (save our daughter, miraculously and thankfully) when we’ve been so diligent for three fucking years. Forget that we’ve been pretty much the only ones still wearing masks on planes and at our daughter’s daycare, as if “I’ve decided to get on with my life” somehow makes the pandemic over simply by willing it; as if it’s impossible to “get on with life” while also taking basic fucking precautions that hurt no one and help everyone.</p>
<p>All of that was rage-inducing beyond words and each deserve their own posts to really break down. But the real story of my 2022 was of burnout that I foolishly thought I could outrun.</p>
<section id="burnout-dances-to-its-own-tune" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="burnout-dances-to-its-own-tune">Burnout dances to its own tune</h3>
<p>I’ve been burned out for quite awhile now; realistically, there are likely roots going all the way back to graduate school, but things really kicked into gear with the tenure-track position and the stress it brought.</p>
<p>The pandemic didn’t create anything new in this regard, but it did act as a force multiplier, frying what little bandwidth I had left and forcing me to confront just how toxic my working circumstances were.</p>
<p>This was all complicated by the birth of my daughter, happening at the same time as my promotion and tenure process, wrapped up in some of the most gratuitous displays of academia’s <em>utter disdain</em> both for growing families and, it turns out, straightforward public health guidelines around pandemic mitigation strategies.</p>
<p>Suffice to say, when I landed a job at Quansight in mid-late 2021, I jumped at the possibility of an exit strategy. Admittedly, I jumped way, way too soon: I was worried of losing the opportunity if I waited (irony), I didn’t have anything approximating a concrete exit strategy from academia (haste), and I thought I could hold down two positions long enough to gracefully exit (fucking LOL).</p>
</section>
<section id="writing-on-the-wall" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="writing-on-the-wall">Writing on the wall</h3>
<p>Even when I formalized a sabbatical beginning August 2022–an entire <em>eight months</em> after I started working full-time at Quansight–I was so far beyond any kind of discernible burnout threshold that it’s a miracle I lasted another three months before leaving.</p>
<p>Through all of 2022, my burnout was so severe that entire consecutive weeks would go by where I napped <em>daily</em> just to make it through the day. I was besieged by migraine headaches at the base of my neck that radiated down my legs; they wouldn’t respond to ibuprofen, and made literally any activity impossible. By the fall, I was having these migraines 3-4 days a <em>week</em>. But the <em>coup de gr<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Chat%7Ba%7D">ce</em>, the real cherry on top of it all was how, on a given work week in 2022, my upper bound for productivity was probably about 25% efficiency.</p>
<p>Yes, I typed that correctly: on a given 40-hour work week, I at my peak could probably crank out about 10 hours of real, actual work. Most of the time, I was operating at some sigma less than that. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zBfTrjPSShs">I’ll take my promotion now</a>.</p>
<p>The weirdest thing about this level of burnout probably answers the obvious burning question following that previous revelation: I had no idea this was all related, or that there was even really a problem. The headaches were annoying, the naps made things bearable (in a sense), and surely I was just still getting the hang of things and I’d soon start churning out productive weeks? After all, I just had to hold out until I could sever all ties to academia in… 6-8 more months.</p>
<p>About that.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/this_is_fine.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="A small child looking on with mild concern as a tiny being is on fire, sitting in a cooking dish, and also seems mildly perturbed by the situation. Meant to evoke similarities with the this-is-fine meme."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Midjourney did a pretty bang-up job when I asked for a tweaked version of “this is fine”.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>To address the (one of many, I suspect) elephant in the room: wasn’t I on sabbatical from my academic role? Yes, dear reader, I was. And it was still requiring at least a handful of hours from me, on a good week. Some sabbatical.</p>
<p>Oh yeah, October. Our entire family got RSV in the second half of October. Didn’t I mention that earlier? No? Yeah, that was an entire week where all three of us were sick (so no daycare for kiddo), followed by a second week where my daughter and I developed secondary bacterial infections! Great for the aforementioned productivity!</p>
</section>
<section id="no-options-given" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="no-options-given">No options given</h3>
<p>If there’s anything positive to be said about burnout, it’s this: eventually, it gives you no choice. You reach a point where it’s physically, mentally, emotionally, spiritually, ecumenically, and grammatically <em>impossible</em> to keep moving forward.</p>
<p>Without going into detail<sup>2</sup>, that point came just before Thanksgiving. I left Quansight. I took the entire month of December off. And hooooooly shit y’all, but that month was, honest-to-goodness, maybe the first time in over a year I not only stopped digging the burnout hole deeper, but <em>actually started filling it back in</em>. I can’t describe the feeling of my brain lighting up and making connections and actually <em>functioning</em>–I spun up our household Mastodon instance in that time<sup>3</sup>! I actually recovered a bit, holy <em>fuck</em>.</p>
<p>And only then did I slowly begin to realize how absolutely <em>fucked</em> I’d been the entire year up until that point. How the <em>fuck</em> did I expect to be able to continue down this road for another <em>six to eight MONTHS</em>?</p>
<p>It seems ridiculous–laughable, if it didn’t border so close to outright dangerous–but only in hindsight.</p>
</section>
<section id="light-even-in-darkness" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="light-even-in-darkness">Light even in darkness</h3>
<p>My 2022 was defined by my burnout… but also by my realization of its full extent. And, in doing so, by the start of me turning things around.</p>
<p>Beyond burnout, there were some other events and accomplishments in 2022 that were cause for celebration by themselves.</p>
<p>My wife quit the job that was stifling her and is now pursuing her dreams as a full-time fiction writer. This was one of the very first things I learned about her all those years ago when we met<sup>4</sup>, and the fact that she’s living it now–and all the challenges and anxieties and freedoms and blessings it comes with–makes me prouder than I’ve been of anyone in years.</p>
<p>Speaking of my wife and her writing, she finished a complete draft of the book she’s been working on for the past bit. I finished reading it a week or so ago, and I <em>fucking love it</em>. I may be a little biased, but I also read 30 books last year according to my StoryGraph<sup>5</sup>, so I have at least an inkling of what I’m talking about. She’s an amazing writer; you should buy it when it’s published!</p>
<p>My daughter is rapidly turning into the most fiery and powerful person I could have ever hoped she would be. It’s exhausting and enthralling and I’m so freaking happy to be her dad.</p>
<p>We did, in fact, solve some of the flooding problems around our house<sup>6</sup>. We had extensive work done on the back and front yards, and I can proudly say that our front yard is virtually problem-free and our backyard is… better. Obviously there’s more to be done, but in exchange for a lot of money there was a good amount of progress toward eliminating the literal rivers that swirl around our house during a downpour.</p>
<p>For all my breathless pearl-clutching around my running failures, 2022 was, by any reasonable measure, an improvement over 2021, and those improvements should be celebrated… even if they aren’t the <em>impossible gains</em> I wanted.</p>
<p>Strava has a fitness estimate tracker; it’s obscenely biased in ways I can’t begin to wrap my head around, but it seems like a moderate-to-low variance estimator, so it provides a decent relative intuition on fitness over time. And I have to say: given my 2022, it’s halfway ok.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/fitness_estimate.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Yeah, my fitness hasn’t been great the past 6 months, but it’s held relatively steady. Given 2022, that’s an accomplishment by itself.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Speaking of running, my total mileage improved year-over-year. I also ran my first half marathon since before COVID<sup>7</sup>. It was the slowest half I’ve ever run (by a lot), but I finished. I also ran a handful of other races last year, which helped remind me that racing is a lot of fun–which helped remind me that <em>running is a lot of fun</em>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/annual_mileage.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Year-over-year total mileage run. More mileage with fewer runs indicate longer runs.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I spun up an entire Mastodon instance, <a href="https://quinnwitz.house/">Casa Quinnwitz</a>, on my homelab Raspberry Pi cluster (shout-out to the Mastodon dev team, which is full of super kind and patient folks). It’s pretty much my new socialz home, since Twitter has been rendered all-but-unusable with Tweetbot and all the other third-party clients going belly-up. I kind of love the vibe there; feels very longer-form-proto-Twitter with a pre-<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eternal_September">Eternal September</a> thing going.</p>
<p><sup>8</sup></p>
</section>
<section id="whats-next" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="whats-next">What’s next?</h3>
<p>I’m back in the academy this semester, teaching my <a href="https://dsp-uga.github.io/sp23">data science practicum</a> course while guiding a half dozen of my remaining students to graduation in May. I have a weekly structure in place that balances my obligations to the academy with my needs for continuing rest, exercise, and <em>my own fun shit</em>. I’m still feeling the after-effects of COVID but am hoping that will taper off as I get back into running again, training for a half marathon in April and multiple shorter races before then. I have a concrete exit strategy from academy, and a timeline of events and milestones to accompany it.</p>
<p>Crucially, I’ve also adopted a new strategy for handling work-related items coming my way: <strong><em>NO</em></strong>.</p>
<p>No, I’m not taking new students.</p>
<p>No, I can’t review for your conference/study section/journal.</p>
<p>No, I’m not open to new research collaborations.</p>
<p>No, I can’t sit on your [insert topic here] panel<sup>9</sup>.</p>
<p>No, I’m not going to be on that committee.</p>
<p>No no no no no. No.</p>
<p>It’s a really hard fucking thing for a lifetime people-pleaser to set up boundaries, but for me in this moment, it’s both a matter of mere survival as well as a pathway to doing what I <em>really</em> love.</p>
<p>Here’s to a 2023 of healing. Much love to all of you 🥂</p>


</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Yes, there will be a future blog post on this. No, I’m not going to expound any further on it here.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Ask if you really want to know.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn3"><p>Don’t worry, I have an entire series of blog posts (six, I think?) planned to go over it in gross detail. Stay tuned!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn4"><p>Just about 17 years ago! 😱 ↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn5"><p>Ditch Goodreads!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn6"><p>This one’s for you, Mom and Dad 🎄✉️ ↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn7"><p>The last half I ran was late 2019, almost a 3-year gap!↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn8"><p>Now I’m just fucking with you. Also I love footnotes, so expect to see a lot of them on every blog post.↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn9"><p>Though I did get invited to one on <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChatGPT/comments/10am8to/do_we_have_a_winner/">ChatGPT</a>, and <em>wow</em> the temptation to say “yes” and then just burn the whole place down is <em>overpowering</em>… I’ll have to think about it.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2023,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {2022: {A} Year in Review},
  date = {2023-01-17},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2023. <span>“2022: A Year in Review.”</span> January 17,
2023. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/">https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 15:42:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2023-01-14-year-that-almost-was/broken_sword.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Pardon de dust (2)</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-12-13-pardon-the-dust/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-12-13-pardon-the-dust/clover.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Our bunny, Clover."></p>
<p>Why hello there. You may have noticed that things look a little bit different around here.</p>
<p>I’m in the process of migrating my blog <em>off</em> <a href="https://getpelican.com/">Pelican</a> and <em>on</em> to <a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a>.</p>
<p>Why, you ask? Honestly, I got tired of having to fix a broken plugin or failed <code>git push</code> <em>every. single. time.</em> that I finished writing out a blog post. It gave an already-infrequent task an even higher activation threshold, and during a stretch where spare bandwidth was an incredible luxury.</p>
<p>In short: I’d really like to blog more often, and from what I’ve seen, Quarto will help me do just that. It definitely requires some extra bandwidth to get things migrated over, but fortunately: I have some of that at the moment :)</p>
<p>Stay tuned! In the meantime, please enjoy the above recent photo of Clover helping us put up our tree.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2022,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Pardon de Dust (2)},
  date = {2022-12-13},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-12-13-pardon-the-dust/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2022. <span>“Pardon de Dust (2).”</span> December 13,
2022. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-12-13-pardon-the-dust/">https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-12-13-pardon-the-dust/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>news</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-12-13-pardon-the-dust/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 15:48:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-12-13-pardon-the-dust/clover.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fiddling with generative art models</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/starfield.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Generated with the text: `4K, wide angle, hyper detailed, starfield, nighttime sky, crescent moons, stars, nebulae, cosmic` by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<p>Much like a lot of the internet over the past couple months, I’ve been tinkering with some AI art generators, mainly <a href="https://www.midjourney.com/">Midjourney</a> (if only because I’m waitlisted on <a href="https://openai.com/dall-e-2/">DALL-E 2</a>).</p>
<p>It’s been surprisingly fun, if challenging. This isn’t really my area of research, but I understand the basic underpinnings:</p>
<p>These models are trained using vast swaths of image-and-text pairings, so the model can develop an association between features in images and the corresponding text that describes them. Obviously this process is <em>very</em> complicated, and also requires not only a great deal of data but also a considerable amount of computing power, so it’s still a very active area of research and is largely out of reach of your every day researcher or individual training their own model. But once the model is trained, users can provide snippets of text, which the model then translates into an image.</p>
<p>Therein lies the magic. There’s a lot of randomness involved in the image generation process, since even a text input as simple as “cat” could mean a LOT of different things, image-wise. That’s partly a feature: two people who give the exact same text input will likely get slight variations of the same concept, and possibly get wildly divergent results.</p>
<p>But it also makes for a challenging user experience: there’s a sort of “lingo” that you have to wrap your head around, a “way of talking to the model” that goes beyond simple word-concept mappings, that only comes with extended use of the models. It gets harder the more specific of an idea you have: your conceptual understanding of the idea may not bear any resemblance to the concept the model learned!</p>
<p>(man this is getting philosophical! let’s see if I can make this a bit more concrete with some examples)</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/empty_beach_v1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Generated with the text: `empty beach, dark storm in distance, one flower blooms from the sand to the side, high detail, atmosphere, Arnold render, ultra-realistic, dramatic lighting, glow, cinematic lighting, epic, 8k` by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Generated with the text: <code>empty beach, dark storm in distance, one flower blooms from the sand to the side, high detail, atmosphere, Arnold render, ultra-realistic, dramatic lighting, glow, cinematic lighting, epic, 8k</code></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>This was actually an image that I generated based off an image <em>someone else had already generated</em> (yeah, we can take public images and run them back through the model with new or additional text).</p>
<p>From here, I ran a couple more of my own modifications:</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/empty_beach_v2.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Generated by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/empty_beach_v3.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Generated by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<p>I really liked the second one, though with the third I love the ambiguity in the landscape: is it water, or is it snow? Hard to say in that lighting.</p>
<p>From here, I started focusing a bit more on landscapes under a starlit sky (like the cover photo). I eventually settled on this one, which I really kinda love (so I made the highest-res version of it that I could):</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/mountains_starfield.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Generated with the text: `wooded mountainous winter landscape under cosmic night sky with distant glowing small town in a valley, nebulae, crescent moon, planetary rings, cinematic, atmospheric, 8k, dramatic lighting, ultra realistic` by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Generated with the text: <code>wooded mountainous winter landscape under cosmic night sky with distant glowing small town in a valley, nebulae, crescent moon, planetary rings, cinematic, atmospheric, 8k, dramatic lighting, ultra realistic</code></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I will say, it definitely takes some doing to get a feel for how it works–what I had in mind was nowhere near what the model spat out, even though I <em>love</em> what it created. Still, there weren’t really any planetary rings (I was thinking of Gaal’s homeworld in the AppleTV+ <em>Foundation</em> series), and the “glowing small town in a valley” seems to have been diffusely spread over the <em>entire</em> valley, almost like fireflies, rather than distinct. Beautiful, no question, but not exactly what I’d had in mind.</p>
<p>One final bit I tried before my trial ran out was a completely different direction:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/rpi_madeof_raspberries.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Generated with the text: `raspberry pi computer made out of raspberries, modern, futuristic` by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Generated with the text: <code>raspberry pi computer made out of raspberries, modern, futuristic</code></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I see a lot of super awesome art being generated from very terse prompts, so I was trying to capture that a little bit here (as opposed to the downright locquacious landscape prompts above).</p>
<p>Some of the earlier images I created had more to do with my family. This first one was created shortly after my wife left her previous job to pursue her longtime dream of being a full-time fiction writer (it was seriously one of the first things I ever learned about her all those years ago): I was inspired to see if the model could capture something about what that looked like, in my head at least.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/writer.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Generated with the text: `a writer working at her computer surrounded by a world of her own creation` by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Generated with the text: <code>a writer working at her computer surrounded by a world of her own creation</code></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>And I really love this next one, as it evokes less of the specific act of writing and more of how it’s about <em>creating</em>.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/creator.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Generated with the text: `writer standing on the boundary between worlds, the world she lives in and the world she creates` by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Generated with the text: <code>writer standing on the boundary between worlds, the world she lives in and the world she creates</code></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We’ve also been huge fans of Zelda for quite awhile (which <a href="https://magsol.github.io/tag/zelda.html">longtime readers already know</a>), and not too long ago I commissioned a fan account to remake a family photo as if it were in the Zelda universe.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/commission.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Commissioned artwork of our own family, redrawn to look like we live in the Zelda universe."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Quite the handsome family, doncha think?</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>So I played with that idea a bit, and while the results weren’t great–I get the feeling the generator has a harder time dealing with <em>very specific real-world concepts</em>, as opposed to more general categories of things–I did get this pretty cute rendering of what is most definitely a Hyrulean family.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/zelda.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Generated with the text: `zelda champions from breath of the wild, family, 1985, highres` by MidjourneyAI."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Generated with the text: <code>zelda champions from breath of the wild, family, 1985, highres</code></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It’s fun to tinker with. In all honesty I’ll probably keep playing with it here and there as the mood strikes; if you want to follow along, <a href="https://www.midjourney.com/app/users/730084120558043179/">there’s a public feed of all the pictures I generate here</a> (note: it’s “public” in that you have to create a free account to see it), since there’s no way I’m going to shell out the $ required to make my images private.</p>
<section id="legal-disclaimer" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="legal-disclaimer">Legal Disclaimer</h3>
<p>At least, I’ll keep tinkering until copyright catches up… which, on that note, I should mention: I agree with everything in this twitter thread on the topic. I want to end on this note, because I think this is very important to keep in mind.</p>
<p></p><div id="tweet-53525"></div><script>tweet={"url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/BunchesOfBees\/status\/1553079149232734208","author_name":"Christopher","author_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com\/BunchesOfBees","html":"\u003Cblockquote class=\"twitter-tweet\" align=\"center\"\u003E\u003Cp lang=\"en\" dir=\"ltr\"\u003EA thing that makes me absolutely insane with discussions about &quot;AI&quot; image generation is their creators freely argue literally both sides of an opposing argument depending on what argument you&#39;re trying to have with them\u003C\/p\u003E&mdash; Christopher (@BunchesOfBees) \u003Ca href=\"https:\/\/twitter.com\/BunchesOfBees\/status\/1553079149232734208?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw\"\u003EJuly 29, 2022\u003C\/a\u003E\u003C\/blockquote\u003E\n\u003Cscript async src=\"https:\/\/platform.twitter.com\/widgets.js\" charset=\"utf-8\"\u003E\u003C\/script\u003E\n\n","width":550,"height":null,"type":"rich","cache_age":"3153600000","provider_name":"Twitter","provider_url":"https:\/\/twitter.com","version":"1.0"};document.getElementById("tweet-53525").innerHTML = tweet["html"];</script><p></p>
<p>Keep in mind, I am not a lawyer, but based on my read there are two legal interpretations of these models: as an <em>author</em> that learns and creates novel work, or a <em>product</em> that synthesizes derivative works. In the case of the former, any kind of substantive duplication of existing work created by someone else is copyright infringement; and in the case of the latter, it’s using novel, <em>unlicensed</em> work in a paid product, which is also copyright infringement.</p>
<p>As someone whose background is in exactly this kind of generative “AI” work, I would generally fall under the latter interpretation of these models as a product (what they “learn” is dubious at best; I would never call their reproductions “novel”). As such, I also agree with the tweet’s author that the moment these companies begin monetizing these models is when, at the very least, they’ve committed a moral rights violation. It’s the same exact reason I’m very uncomfortable with the <a href="https://github.com/features/copilot">GitHub CoPilot product</a>: it’s been trained using billions of lines of code that was written, tested, debugged, scrutinized, and labored over by humans <em>who did not consent to nor were reimbursed for having their code used in a paid product</em>.</p>
<p>That last tweet in the thread is particularly poignant for me, and distills much of the reason for my disillusionment with the tech sector in general. I’m sorry to end on such a sour note, but while I do love the amazing things machine learning is doing, we have to keep at the forefront of our minds that <a href="https://vicki.substack.com/p/neural-nets-are-just-people-all-the">machine learning is, ultimately, a human endeavor</a>, and if it won’t work without humans, we should make sure those humans are <em>taken care of</em>: recognition, compensation, empathy, and so on.</p>
<p><em>steps off soap box…for now</em></p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2022,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {Fiddling with Generative Art Models},
  date = {2022-08-03},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2022. <span>“Fiddling with Generative Art
Models.”</span> August 3, 2022. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art">https://magsol.github.io/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>generative modeling</category>
  <category>deep learning</category>
  <category>raspberry pi</category>
  <category>legal disclaimer</category>
  <category>zelda</category>
  <category>family</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2022 11:54:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-08-03-fiddling-with-generative-art/starfield.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What the f*@$ is this s%#&amp; (2022 ed.)</title>
  <dc:creator>Shannon Quinn</dc:creator>
  <link>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/clover.png" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="Our white bunny, Clover, sitting on the couch, looking beautiful."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Clover disapproves of everything and wants you to get your butt in gear.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I’m not sure where I should even start. How does one sum up a year that felt more like a decade? How does one reflect on a year that eschewed reflection in favor of mere survival?</p>
<p>I want to be the eternal optimist who always sees the silver lining, who always takes away something positive from a negative experience. But to paraphrase (because I can’t find it) someone far more clever than I on Twitter: it feels a bit like trying to find the bright side of things while actively being run over by a zamboni.</p>
<p>Well, I suppose one way would be to try and end this post on a positive note. So to that end, I’ll start with the stuff that sucked in 2021.</p>
<section id="the-bad" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-bad">The Bad</h3>
<p>Where do I even start? The pandemic continued to rage–Alpha, Delta, and Omicron right at the cusp of the new year–and elected leaders around the globe shrugged their collective shoulders, as if saying “we tried nothing and it didn’t work, so I guess that’s it.”</p>
<p>University of Georgia, in lockstep with the Georgia Board of Regents and many other public universities across the country, collectively threw up their hands, hid behind the malevolent cowardice of our elected leaders, and did all of jack and shit to protect any of the hundreds of thousands of dedicated public service workers who have given 140% of themselves to the institution of higher learning since time immemorial. They continued to fart out meaningless platitudes about “rallying together” whenever another surge arrived but refused to take any meaningful or substantive actions recommended by public health experts the world over–like requiring masks or vaccinations–and instead demanded more of already overtaxed, underpaid janitorial staff to do more pointless bullshit like installing platic dividers or cleaning surfaces forty times a day.</p>
<p>Running has continued to be an elusive outlet for stress. Every run feels hard, and more often than not I’m inclined to not run. Which doesn’t do anything to help my mood, but that vicious negative feedback loop continues nonetheless. I hate it but I’m not sure how to break out of it.</p>
<p>Other shit that sucked:</p>
<ul>
<li>Our bun Clover had a bout of GI stasis in the early part of the year. Thankfully, the folks at the UGA Vet Hospital were amazing in getting her well again. Still, scary as shit.</li>
<li>the weather (75F on Christmas? fucking really?)</li>
<li>teaching (and I hate that I hated it, but I’m so, so burned out)</li>
<li>literally the Georgia Board of Regents</li>
<li>annual grant reports (best I can describe is we’re running in place)</li>
<li>burnout in general</li>
<li>mental health in general</li>
<li>every day being a series of bad choices made from a list of exclusively bad choices</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-good" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-good">The Good</h3>
<p>Somehow, through the grace of God and possibly every deity in the multiverse, we have not tested positive for COVID (<em>knocks on wood</em>).</p>
<p></p><div id="youtube-frame" style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; /* 16:9 */ height: 0;"><iframe width="100%" height="" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2EbeCEs9_Tw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div><p></p>
<p>I took my first flight since Dec 2019 to Washington, D.C., for a workshop hosted at George Washington University on teaching with open source technology. It was a <em>blast</em>. Not only was it an absolute pleasure to spend a few days with some of my professional heroes, folks I’ve known for years through Twitter and who share my same passion for open source technology and innovative instrucitonal methods, but it was great just going to a meeting again!</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/dc-workshop.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Group photo from the GW workshop event. Importantly: everyone is wearing a mask!"></p>
<p>Traveling was the strangest thing, both familiar and foreign. Of course I was a nervous wreck going through the airport, but I commend everyone at GWU for taking every precaution, including mandating the use of masks indoors. It was also the first time either one of us single-parented for more than a few hours at a time, and Cathryn did amazingly well! She even managed Z’s weekly bath ON HER OWN.</p>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/sunrise.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Sunrise from the airport in Atlanta, GA."></p>
<p>I was tenured and promoted. Indeed, I somehow won the cosmic coin flip. I am now an Associate (“ass o’ shit”, in the technical parlance) Professor of Computer Science and Cellular Biology.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/phd-thesis.jpg" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="An abstract image generated from my thesis title; arguably, an early diffuser model."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">If my doctoral thesis was an image.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We bought a second car (named “Mipha”), a Honda CRV Hybrid, in the summer. We had assumed we’d need two cars, what with our jobs requiring slightly different hours and wildly different physical locations, it would entail too much logistical square dancing for a single car when daycare pickup / dropoff was added to the mix. Of course, then I taught the fall semester almost entirely remotely because of the Delta surge. Still, it’s been really nice to have a bit more room, and our handful of trips to the mountains with Z would absolutely NOT have been possible with Sam (our Honda Accord Hybrid). Not crazy about the added car insurance, though.</p>
<p>Over Christmas, we managed a trip to Arizona (which, in hindset, we may not have done given Omicron) for a family reunion on Cathryn’s side to celebrate her grandfather’s 101st birthday. It was also the first time Z had ever met the family on Cathryn’s side, and the first time she got to meet her great-grandfather, born a <em>century</em> earlier. We took rapid tests every day, and got PCR tested before and after, and <em>somehow</em> only 1 person in the entire extended family got COVID. It was also the first time Z traveled by airplane, and she was amazing. It was lovely. Exhausting, but lovely.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/desert.png" class="preview-image img-fluid figure-img" alt="Photo of the outside of our Arizona hotel, where oddly enough it's raining."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Rain. All day. In the desert. Yeah, global warming’s a myth.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Other stuff that was neat and definitely didn’t suck:</p>
<ul>
<li>Our house won our HOA’s First Place for holiday decorations, specifically in the “whimsical” category! I’m thinking our 7-foot inflatable menorah had something to do with it.</li>
<li>Both Cathryn and I hired running coaches to help us get back into the swing of things. Baby steps!</li>
<li>I was offered–and accepted–a position with <a href="https://quansight.com">Quansight as Principal Solution Architect</a>. I’ll have a <em>lot</em> more to say about this in a later post.</li>
<li>Bathroom renovations are scheduled, and office renovations are being planned. All that’s left in the Priority A category is to address the outdoor flooding.</li>
<li>We managed a handful of mountain trips with Z, and even one with our friend Laura. Z loooves the outdoors, which is awesome.</li>
<li>I got this blog working again!</li>
<li><em>Age of Calamity</em>’s two expansion packs are fun as hell.</li>
<li>Z is just… the singularity of joy in our lives.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="wrap-up" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wrap-up">Wrap Up</h3>
<p><img src="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/jump.png" class="preview-image img-fluid" alt="Photo of the hopscotch blocks in the park down the street from our house."></p>
<p>It’s cathartic to get all this out in some form. And, of course, there are innumerable positives (and negatives) that I’m forgetting / suppressing / ignoring. I will say this:</p>
<p>I’m genuinely excited for 2022. There’s an insane amount of uncertainty and dread and fear, but there are some changes in store for which I’m really and truly stoked. I just have to hope.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{quinn2022,
  author = {Quinn, Shannon},
  title = {What the f*@\$ Is This s\%\#\&amp; (2022 Ed.)},
  date = {2022-01-05},
  url = {https://magsol.github.io/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-quinn2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Quinn, Shannon. 2022. <span>“What the f*@$ Is This s%#&amp; (2022
Ed.).”</span> January 5, 2022. <a href="https://magsol.github.io/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s">https://magsol.github.io/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>personal</category>
  <category>professional</category>
  <category>clover the bun</category>
  <category>z</category>
  <category>covid-19</category>
  <category>running</category>
  <category>professor</category>
  <category>university</category>
  <category>quansight</category>
  <category>travel</category>
  <category>holidays</category>
  <category>year in review</category>
  <guid>https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jan 2022 21:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://magsol.github.io/posts/2022-01-05-what-the-f-is-this-s/clover.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="192" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
