<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stochastic Stenography</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://magsol.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://magsol.github.io/</id><updated>2022-01-05T21:11:47-05:00</updated><subtitle>Data science, academia, and donuts</subtitle><entry><title>What the f*@$ is this s%#&amp; (2022 ed.)</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2022/01/05/what-the-f-is-this-s/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-05T21:11:47-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T21:11:47-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2022-01-05:/blog/2022/01/05/what-the-f-is-this-s/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/clover.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Clover disapproves of everything and wants you to get your ass in gear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure where I should even start. How does one sum up a year that felt more like a decade? How does one reflect on a year that eschewed reflection in favor of mere survival?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/clover.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Clover disapproves of everything and wants you to get your ass in gear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure where I should even start. How does one sum up a year that felt more like a decade? How does one reflect on a year that eschewed reflection in favor of mere survival?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be the eternal optimist who always sees the silver lining, who always takes away something positive from a negative experience. But to paraphrase (because I can't find it) someone far more clever than I on Twitter: it feels a bit like trying to find the bright side of things while actively being run over by a zamboni.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I suppose one way would be to try and end this post on a positive note. So to that end, I'll start with the stuff that sucked in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Bad&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where do I even start? The pandemic continued to rage--Alpha, Delta, and Omicron right at the cusp of the new year--and elected leaders around the globe shrugged their collective shoulders, as if saying "we tried nothing and it didn't work, so I guess that's it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Georgia, in lockstep with the Georgia Board of Regents and many other public universities across the country, collectively threw up their hands, hid behind the malevolent cowardice of our elected leaders, and did all of jack and shit to protect any of the hundreds of thousands of dedicated public service workers who have given 140% of themselves to the institution of higher learning since time immemorial. They continued to fart out meaningless platitudes about "rallying together" whenever another surge arrived but refused to take any meaningful or substantive actions recommended by public health experts the world over--like requiring masks or vaccinations--and instead demanded more of already overtaxed, underpaid janitorial staff to do more pointless bullshit like installing platic dividers or cleaning surfaces forty times a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running has continued to be an elusive outlet for stress. Every run feels hard, and more often than not I'm inclined to not run. Which doesn't do anything to help my mood, but that vicious negative feedback loop continues nonetheless. I hate it but I'm not sure how to break out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other shit that sucked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our bun Clover had a bout of GI stasis in the early part of the year. Thankfully, the folks at the UGA Vet Hospital were amazing in getting her well again. Still, scary as shit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the weather (75F on Christmas? fucking really?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teaching (and I hate that I hated it, but I'm so, so burned out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;literally the Georgia Board of Regents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;annual grant reports (best I can describe is we're running in place)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;burnout in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mental health in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every day being a series of bad choices made from a list of exclusively bad choices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Good&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow, through the grace of God and possibly every deity in the multiverse, we have not tested positive for COVID (&lt;em&gt;knocks on wood&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                    &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                        src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/2EbeCEs9_Tw'
                        frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen
                        mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;
                    &lt;/iframe&gt;
                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took my first flight since Dec 2019 to Washington, D.C., for a workshop hosted at George Washington University on teaching with open source technology. It was a &lt;em&gt;blast&lt;/em&gt;. Not only was it an absolute pleasure to spend a few days with some of my professional heroes, folks I've known for years through Twitter and who share my same passion for open source technology and innovative instrucitonal methods, but it was great just going to a meeting again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/dc-workshop.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traveling was the strangest thing, both familiar and foreign. Of course I was a nervous wreck going through the airport, but I commend everyone at GWU for taking every precaution, including mandating the use of masks indoors. It was also the first time either one of us single-parented for more than a few hours at a time, and Cathryn did amazingly well! She even managed Z's weekly bath ON HER OWN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/sunrise.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was tenured and promoted. Indeed, I somehow won the cosmic coin flip. I am now an Associate ("ass o' shit", in the technical parlance) Professor of Computer Science and Cellular Biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/phd-thesis.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;If my doctoral thesis was an image&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We bought a second car (named "Mipha"), a Honda CRV Hybrid, in the summer. We had assumed we'd need two cars, what with our jobs requiring slightly different hours and wildly different physical locations, it would entail too much logistical square dancing for a single car when daycare pickup / dropoff was added to the mix. Of course, then I taught the fall semester almost entirely remotely because of the Delta surge. Still, it's been really nice to have a bit more room, and our handful of trips to the mountains with Z would absolutely NOT have been possible with Sam (our Honda Accord Hybrid). Not crazy about the added car insurance, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over Christmas, we managed a trip to Arizona (which, in hindset, we may not have done given Omicron) for a family reunion on Cathryn's side to celebrate her grandfather's 101st birthday. It was also the first time Z had ever met the family on Cathryn's side, and the first time she got to meet her great-grandfather, born a &lt;em&gt;century&lt;/em&gt; earlier. We took rapid tests every day, and got PCR tested before and after, and &lt;em&gt;somehow&lt;/em&gt; only 1 person in the entire extended family got COVID. It was also the first time Z traveled by airplane, and she was amazing. It was lovely. Exhausting, but lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/desert.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Rain. All day. In the desert. Yeah, global warming's a myth.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other stuff that was neat and definitely didn't suck:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our house won our HOA's First Place for holiday decorations, specifically in the "whimsical" category! I'm thinking our 7-foot inflatable menorah had something to do with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both Cathryn and I hired running coaches to help us get back into the swing of things. Baby steps!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was offered--and accepted--a position with &lt;a href="https://quansight.com"&gt;Quansight as Principal Solution Architect&lt;/a&gt;. I'll have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more to say about this in a later post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bathroom renovations are scheduled, and office renovations are being planned. All that's left in the Priority A category is to address the outdoor flooding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We managed a handful of mountain trips with Z, and even one with our friend Laura. Z loooves the outdoors, which is awesome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I got this blog working again!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Age of Calamity&lt;/em&gt;'s two expansion packs are fun as hell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Z is just... the singularity of joy in our lives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/jump.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's cathartic to get all this out in some form. And, of course, there are innumerable positives (and negatives) that I'm forgetting / suppressing / ignoring. I will say this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm genuinely excited for 2022. There's an insane amount of uncertainty and dread and fear, but there are some changes in store for which I'm really and truly stoked. I just have to hope.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="stupid"></category><category term="whatever"></category><category term="clover the bun"></category><category term="z"></category><category term="covid"></category><category term="covid19"></category><category term="board of regents sucks"></category><category term="running"></category><category term="professor"></category><category term="university"></category><category term="quansight"></category><category term="travel"></category><category term="airplane"></category><category term="reunion"></category><category term="holidays"></category><category term="year in review"></category></entry><entry><title>Back in Action</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2021/12/30/back-in-action/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-12-30T16:27:46-05:00</published><updated>2021-12-30T22:13:42-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2021-12-30:/blog/2021/12/30/back-in-action/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://c.tenor.com/ZFc20z8DItkAAAAd/facepalm-really.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a day/week/month/year/decade, this 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apologize for my long silence. Turns out, there are a couple of Pelican plugins that neither play nice with each other, nor with the steady march of upgraded Jupyter components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, two plugins I rely on--&lt;a href="https://github.com/pelican-plugins/liquid-tags"&gt;liquid-tags&lt;/a&gt; and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://c.tenor.com/ZFc20z8DItkAAAAd/facepalm-really.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a day/week/month/year/decade, this 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I apologize for my long silence. Turns out, there are a couple of Pelican plugins that neither play nice with each other, nor with the steady march of upgraded Jupyter components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, two plugins I rely on--&lt;a href="https://github.com/pelican-plugins/liquid-tags"&gt;liquid-tags&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/danielfrg/pelican-jupyter"&gt;pelican-jupyter&lt;/a&gt;--tend to nuke one another when used in parallel. Not surprising, given they both use the exact same underlying registration protocol for adding new liquid tags, so I guess the real mystery is how these two &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; worked at all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I found that I &lt;em&gt;either&lt;/em&gt; have Jupyter notebooks render in all their code-by-text-by-figures beauty, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; embed images and videos. Couldn't have both. After doing some searching and getting the distinct feeling that no one else really cared about the situation, I briefly considered switching static blog devices before regaining a shred of sanity and taking a second look: after all, since both plugins were using the same backend, surely I could jury-rig a solution where I smashed the two together and forced them to play nice?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Turns out, that's pretty much what I did, but &lt;a href="https://github.com/danielfrg/pelican-jupyter/issues/126#issuecomment-1003171465"&gt;with a crucial assist&lt;/a&gt; from the maintainer of the pelican-jupyter plugin. There's an extra config I needed to suppress some of the more problematic CSS from the Jupyter notebooks (this fixed a very strange template error I was getting when compiling the blog), but I still needed a kludge to get the two plugins to even cooperate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured out that by copying two files from the pelican-jupyter plugin over to the liquid-tags plugin--specifically, &lt;code&gt;core.py&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;liquid.py&lt;/code&gt; (though &lt;code&gt;liquid.py&lt;/code&gt; had to be renamed to &lt;code&gt;notebook.py&lt;/code&gt; after the move)--I could essentially merge the two plugins into one. I did have to make some changes to the &lt;code&gt;liquid.py&lt;/code&gt;/&lt;code&gt;notebook.py&lt;/code&gt; imports at the top, so they looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;.core&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;get_html_from_filepath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parse_css&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;.liquid_tags&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;register&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# noqa&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;.mdx_liquid_tags&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;LiquidTags&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so that they referenced the &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; versions of &lt;code&gt;liquid_tags.py&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;mdx_liquid_tags.py&lt;/code&gt; (as they were essentially identical to the ones provided by the pelican-jupyter plugin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond that, the relevant portions of my &lt;code&gt;pelicanconf.py&lt;/code&gt; now looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;pelican.plugins&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;liquid_tags&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;PLUGINS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;liquid_tags&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;                &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# regular ol&amp;#39; liquid tags&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;LIQUID_TAGS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;img&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;include_code&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;gram&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;video&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;youtube&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;notebook&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;LIQUID_CONFIGS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;IPYNB_FIX_CSS&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;False&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; 
                  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;IPYNB_SKIP_CSS&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;False&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; 
                  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;IPYNB_EXPORT_TEMPLATE&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;base&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's a bit odd, since I technically do have the pelican-jupyter plugin installed, but I haven't imported it. Instead, I basically smashed it into the liquid-tags plugin, overwriting the "notebook" tag that was already there (it's old, it sucks) and running with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah! I'm back up and running. Have LOADS to talk about, so stick around!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="blogging"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="what a pain"></category><category term="software is the worst"></category><category term="dependency hell"></category><category term="clobbering"></category></entry><entry><title>Festivus for the Restivus</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2020/12/30/festivus-for-the-restivus/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-30T14:17:58-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T14:42:01-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2020-12-30:/blog/2020/12/30/festivus-for-the-restivus/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/festivus/festivus.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Content warning: rough language ahead. You've been warned.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerry Seinfeld isn't on board with Festivus this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JerrySeinfeld/status/1341820840149733377"&gt;Tweet of JerrySeinfeld/1341820840149733377&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get it, I do. And I respect it. But I'm gonna air me some grievances. My therapist has continued to insist that I do what I need and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/festivus/festivus.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[Content warning: rough language ahead. You've been warned.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jerry Seinfeld isn't on board with Festivus this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JerrySeinfeld/status/1341820840149733377"&gt;Tweet of JerrySeinfeld/1341820840149733377&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get it, I do. And I respect it. But I'm gonna air me some grievances. My therapist has continued to insist that I do what I need and not to feel guilty about it, and right now I need to air some &lt;em&gt;fucking&lt;/em&gt; grievances. So strap in folks; here we go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running has been a sick joke for most of this year. I've been logging miles with some kind of GPS watch since mid-2011, and 2020 has been the lowest-mileage year by a massive margin. For comparison, long-time readers may remember the boondoggles of 2015-2016 when I had metatarsalgia in my feet. Both those years, I still managed to tip the 1,000-mile scale. This year? &lt;strong&gt;711 miles&lt;/strong&gt;. Fuck that shit. Running wasn't an escape; it was a fucking trap of preferring the evil I knew over the evil I didn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, halting my running didn't help much, either. I was still exhausted beyond all measures, and not just physically: mentally, emotionally, and grammatically &lt;em&gt;burned. out.&lt;/em&gt; I managed a couple of walks most days, largely amounting to 10,000 steps or thereabouts, so I guess I met the minimum recommended daily physical activity threshold for the most part. But boy did running leave me stuck with the bill this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the note of bills, let's talk about how much help we've gotten in that area, shall we? As in, fucking none? We'd have gotten more tangible pandemic assistance if we'd wholesale replaced our Georgia state and US federal governments with fucking nail salons, as opposed to the leadership vacuums from Kemp, Congress, and the White House. Jesus goddamn tap-dancing Christ. Frank Underwood in &lt;em&gt;House of Cards&lt;/em&gt; killed people, but he got things done in the process. These Republicans just... kill people; whether it's because of willful incompetence or callous indifference I can't say, but holy shit: literal poop-flinging monkeys could have accomplished more in their steads. You have to put forth actual effort to be &lt;em&gt;this fucking ineffective&lt;/em&gt;. You wanted individualistic self-sufficiency? Well, this is what it looks like, fuckers: if you've already got money, you're fine. If not, welp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've felt a real kinship these past several months with Jeff Daniels' Will McAvoy, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wTjMqda19wk"&gt;particularly as he picks apart this fantasy of America being the "greatest country in the world."&lt;/a&gt; What the fuck does that even mean? That we lead the world in COVID cases and deaths? That we're so star-spangled awesome that anyone with an internet connection can be an armchair epidemiologist? That some so-called moderates are so concerned with curating their centrist appearance that they completely lose sight of the fact that not all (or even most) issues have two sides? That an entire political spectrum in this country has managed to openly flirt with becoming the very thing we fought a war against barely a century ago? That we're so worried about giving anyone slightly more than they "deserve" that we'll decimate public institutions, neglect infrastructure, and reinforce existing inequities, so that only the people who already had money will succeed? Are we really this collectively fucking stupid?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is a fucking nazi cesspool. Facebook is even worse, and Amazon takes the cake for most unethical CEO. Google isn't innocent, either: I've lost any respect I had for my former employer after they fired Timnit Gebru. Then I lost respect for luminaries like Jeff Dean after he doubled-down on some shady post-hoc justification that simultaneously made no sense and also revealed that Google has no collective interest in addressing its structural issues. Then, I lost respect for a number of current Googlers whose work I've admired over the years of following them since graduate school when they kept quiet over this whole thing. Meanwhile, Google is being hammered in EU antitrust courts and I frankly couldn't be happier about it. I hope Facebook gets splintered into dozens of tiny pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can I just say again--people who selectively listen to experts or "experts" because they confirm what said people already believed can go jump in this fire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/festivus/diaf.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sex work is work, and &lt;em&gt;The West Wing&lt;/em&gt; really got this one wrong. Donna, in fact, had it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sex and the City&lt;/em&gt;, for as much as it may have been ahead of its time in general, is super problematic around trans and nonbinary folks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to divorce J.K. Rowling the person from the author of the &lt;em&gt;Harry Potter&lt;/em&gt; books, because she is doing literally everything possible to shit all over what is left of her legacy. I don't know what her problem with trans people is, or why she's so threatened by them, but she can likewise join the aforementioned people who listen only to the "experts" they already agree with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brandon Sanderson doesn't write books nearly fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James S.A. Corey doesn't write books nearly fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patrick Rothfuss doesn't write books nearly fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah, a massive &lt;strong&gt;FUCK YOU&lt;/strong&gt; to the folks I've been seeing on Instagram who don't seem to realize COVID is a thing? Who keep gathering with more people than could possibly be in their pods? Who post pictures of themselves at gyms, bars, restaurants, group runs, and family gatherings for the holidays? They truly are the fuckwads from high school and college who would go off and party instead of working on the team project, difference being that when they invariably came back for the presentation, they'll end up spontaneously combusting and killing both themselves, their teammates, and half their classmates. I've been aggressively un-following these dipshits because if they can't think about anyone other than themselves in the midst of a global pandemic, why would I want to associate with them when the stakes are eventually more mundane? There are a lot of folks who've shown me exactly who they are during this pandemic and they're not anyone I care to know once COVID is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SERIOUSLY. A MODICUM OF LEADERSHIP WOULD HAVE PREVENTED THOUSANDS OF NEEDLESS DEATHS, YOU STAR SPANGLED CESSPOOLS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Telecommunications in the United States is a fucking travesty. In any other [western] country there are dozens of companies in close competition with one another. Here, we have what amounts to local monopolies on broadband, and an effective duopoly on cell providers. And this gets passed off as "innovation"? Our telecom industry is 20 years behind the rest of the world!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Georgia Board of Regents: Governor Kemp's cronies, or just that fucking incompetent? They couldn't be bothered to implement a mask mandate back at the start of the first COVID surge until the entire university system was practically in a state of open rebellion. Rumor has it there's really only a couple bad apples among them, but--in much the same vein as the United States Senate--the fact that a single moronic board member can bring everything to a screeching halt is a bug, not a feature. Ted Cruz can bring the Senate to its knees simply by virtue of his vapid tripe; he doesn't also need a legal basis for his subversion of democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wear. A. Goddamn. Mask. &lt;em&gt;Fuck.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When did it become a feature of a functioning democracy to allow a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/rmayemsinger/status/1343978502551310337"&gt;decaying Confederate monument from Kentucky&lt;/a&gt; to singlehandedly decide the fate of any and all legislation that made its way to the US Senate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the single biggest driver of my growing cynicism has been not the pathetic ineptitudes of our government leaders or even the disinformation being sown by talking heads making untold millions of dollars, but instead the seemingly smart, incisive, and compassionate individuals I knew before the pandemic (or even before the election of Trump) who have since turned into people I no longer recognize. Of course I realize the "change" was, in fact, there all along--it is only my perception that has changed. But it has been truly disheartening and enraging to see acquaintances, friends, and even family here in Athens and elsewhere in the United States who forward along conspiracy theories, repeat hate-filled talking points, and play the role of armchair epidemiologists in magnifying misleading or outright false information around COVID-19. From claiming that supplements can reduce severity of COVID symptoms, to somehow dismissing US oubreak numbers by equating them with China, and since "China's numbers are fudged" therefore the US is doing just fine, to demonizing and even threatening the livelihood of health care workers for the crime of doing their jobs, to giving Trump credit for the rollout of the Pfizer and Moderna vaccines, to &lt;strong&gt;continuing to push back against and ignoring the advice of actual medical and public health experts&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/festivus/dumb.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seems reasonable, right? Until you include the surrounding context: this person initially claimed Trump should take credit for "Operation Warp Speed," followed by a hand-waving rationalization of the &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/12/29/politics/vaccine-rollout-behind-schedule/index.html"&gt;slow&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2020/12/29/covid-19-vaccine-distribution-slow-testing/"&gt;vaccine&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/current-rate-it-ll-be-10-years-americans-adequately-vaccinated-n1252486"&gt;rollout&lt;/a&gt; by blaming supply chain hiccups that come with large-scale product manufacturing. Ignoring, of course, that a vaccine has literally been the single goal of the entire US public health sector since January 2020; how the infrastructure for such a rollout wasn't in place by the summer is a sin worthy of excommunication. But rather than admit as much, we get the above response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's &lt;strong&gt;infuriating&lt;/strong&gt; that we can't just let the experts do their fucking jobs; instead, we have to stake out some pointless fucking pseudo-centrist landscape that doesn't exist, for the purpose of... what? Appealing to the better demons of both sides? That would be reasonable, except for the small problem of one side being a highly imperfect conglomerate of diverse and often conflicting viewpoints, and the other side being a militaristic theocrat's wet dream. But sure, states' rights and framers' intent and all that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, that reminds me: I am fucking DONE with &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Originalism"&gt;originalism&lt;/a&gt; (yes, that goes for the Bible too). There is no 21st-century world in which the intentions of 18th century slaveholders would be remotely interesting, worth considering, or at all relevant. Much like how &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/1357/"&gt;an argument of free speech is effectively a concession&lt;/a&gt;, an argument of framers' intent is likewise an indication that your argument stands on the rhetorical equivalent of a sinkhole; continuing to scream "bUt ThE fRaMeRs!" only reveals your partisan / intellectual / insert motivated reasoning hackery here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dril/status/134787490526658561"&gt;Tweet of dril/134787490526658561&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, one final grievance. With all due respect to Bill Watterson: &lt;a href="https://www.gocomics.com/calvinandhobbes/1993/05/11"&gt;excessively positive people&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, we've even come up with a name for this: toxic positivity. Emphasizing the positive in a given situation, &lt;strong&gt;with the unstated assumption&lt;/strong&gt; that said positives entirely cancel out all negatives. It's been coming up a lot in the context of the pandemic: "well the pandemic has been bad but at least I haven't had to see my boss as much!", as if the two things were even remotely on the same playing field. Granted, it's a specific incarnation of the more general ALWAYS LOOK ON THE BRIGHT SIDE mantra, but it's important to understand that, as complex human beings, we are capable of holding &lt;em&gt;more than one truth&lt;/em&gt; in our heads simultaneously. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2020 is both the year Z entered our lives, and it can also die in a fucking fire. Both are true.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="festivus"></category><category term="2020"></category><category term="fuck 2020"></category><category term="fuck that shit"></category><category term="airing of grievances"></category></entry><entry><title>At home during COVID-19</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2020/05/20/at-home-during-covid-19/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-20T15:39:12-04:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T14:42:01-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2020-05-20:/blog/2020/05/20/at-home-during-covid-19/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/instachaaz.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Image source: &lt;a href="https://instachaaz.threadless.com/"&gt;instachaaz&lt;/a&gt; (the stuff is awesome)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this has certainly been a &lt;strong&gt;unique&lt;/strong&gt; past couple of months. I had a lot of things in mind for the spring 2020 semester and beyond, but I can safely say it's all been completely upended now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to trivialize COVID-19 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/instachaaz.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Image source: &lt;a href="https://instachaaz.threadless.com/"&gt;instachaaz&lt;/a&gt; (the stuff is awesome)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this has certainly been a &lt;strong&gt;unique&lt;/strong&gt; past couple of months. I had a lot of things in mind for the spring 2020 semester and beyond, but I can safely say it's all been completely upended now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to trivialize COVID-19 to the suburban equivalent of "can't go to the community pool for a few months because of a particularly bad case of the fiery poops;" there are real people whose livelihoods are suffering: financially, professionally, and literally, and I think the world as a whole would be a lot better off if we collectively recognized that and pitched in to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lady and I have been establishing new habits and routines, while trying to maintain a semblance of normality during the pandemic. There have been a lot of snacks (peanut butter M&amp;amp;Ms, cookie dough ice cream, hint of lime chips, and of course, Lucky Charms cereal), some creativity in workplace setup (moved an extra computer monitor from upstairs, and set up a surge protector behind the dining table--also had to line one end of the table with aluminum foil, because our cat kept jumping up on the table from that side), and digging out some old mainstays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Classics Never Go Out of Style&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on in the lockdown, The Lady and I kicked off a Zelda-thon, starting with &lt;em&gt;Skyward Sword&lt;/em&gt; on the Nintendo Wii. There's a strange story there: I'd purchased the game for her way back when we lived in separate apartments in Pittsburgh, because she was the Zelda fan between the two of us. Yeah, I'm a gamer, but she's a &lt;em&gt;Zelda&lt;/em&gt; gamer. It was a lot of fun to watch her play the game, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cbwq8ev-EXA"&gt;I occasionally jumped in when she needed to tap out&lt;/a&gt;. But after reaching the penultimate boss, we just... stopped playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;eight years&lt;/em&gt;. We knew this, because when we fired up the game again on the weekend of March 14, we saw the last save file pop up for March 28, 2012. Almost eight years &lt;em&gt;to the day&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since The Lady played most of the game eight years ago, I ended up "driving" this time around. She jumped in whenever she wanted, but we ended up tearing through the game in &lt;strong&gt;10 days&lt;/strong&gt;. It was pretty impressive, and it was great to finally see the end of the game that has been referenced SO MUCH in theory videos around &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt; (which we'll get to!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we knocked out &lt;em&gt;Skyward Sword&lt;/em&gt;, The Lady took the driver's seat for &lt;em&gt;Twilight Princess&lt;/em&gt;. I'd never seen the game played start to finish, and had really never seen anything beyond the quests involving collecting light shards (which is, as I discovered, a meager portion of the game's introduction). Suffice to say, this one took a lot longer; most of the month of April, if memory serves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I took a deep breath and fired up &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt;... in &lt;strong&gt;Master Mode&lt;/strong&gt;. Yes, &lt;a href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2019/08/12/breath-of-fresh-air/"&gt;I've posted about this game here before&lt;/a&gt;, and we ended up beating it sometime in November 2019. But the DLC included an evil modification called "Master Mode", which among other terrible things, has the following effects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every enemy in the game is upgraded by one level (red become blue, blue become brown, brown become silver, silver become &lt;a href="https://cdn.gamer-network.net/2017/usgamer/Breath-of-the-Wild-DLC-Guide-header.jpg/EG11/thumbnail/1920x1080/format/jpg/quality/65/18-12-2018-the-legend-of-zelda-breath-of-the-wild-dlc-everything-we-know.jpg"&gt;gold&lt;/a&gt;, a brand-new level)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enemies heal when they've been out of combat for two seconds (not hyperbole; literally two seconds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brand-new &lt;a href="https://imgix.bustle.com/mic/knzgpkctoycksfpvki9e3kuc7fozfcugpfqn63lps6nee90vzthnydlbjtvt26lx.jpg?w=1020&amp;amp;h=576&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;crop=faces&amp;amp;auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;amp;cs=srgb&amp;amp;q=70"&gt;floating platforms&lt;/a&gt; with enemies, because fuck you that's why&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;brutal&lt;/em&gt;, especially in the first quarter of the game. You end up skipping fights by default, sneaking around a lot more, and fighting as though you cannot take a single hit (because in all likelihood, you can't). I haven't finished it yet, but just this past weekend we completed the last of the DLC "Ballad of the Champions," so really the only thing left of the Main Quests is to destroy Calamity Ganon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, The Lady plans to break out the game that really and truly started it all: &lt;em&gt;Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt;, which I've also never seen played start to finish, so that will be fun to watch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a completely separate video gaming front, I managed to get a Stargate mod working for &lt;em&gt;Sins of a Solar Empire&lt;/em&gt;, and even started playing a small 1v1 as the Ancients against the Wraith. It looks incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/destiny.jpg"&gt;
For fans of &lt;em&gt;Stargate: Universe&lt;/em&gt;, you'll recognize this class of Ancient ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/gateship.jpg"&gt;
Fans of both &lt;em&gt;SG-1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; will instantly recognize this "gate ship"!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/superhive.jpg"&gt;
This looks like a scene straight out of the &lt;em&gt;Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; finale!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't wait to explore some of the other races--Asgard, Goa'uld, and Ori round out the playable races, while a recent update includes some "minor factions" that are always AI-controlled but can still change the dynamics of play: Tau'ri (that's us!), Free Jaffa, Vanir (rogue Asgard offshoot seen in &lt;em&gt;Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;), and Michael's Hybrids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Variety is the Pribe of Libe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While The Lady and I have been re-visiting the classics to keep us grounded, we've also been branching out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, like most, we tried our hand at baking sourdough. And, frankly, it turned out incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/sourdough.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've since baked a new recipe of chocolate chip cookies (which &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; turned out chewy), and have plans to whip up some butterscotch bars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've also been starting up some regular remote get-togethers, from weekly chats with my family to weekly post-run "coffee chats" with some of our running friends. We'll go out for runs by ourselves, come home, get cleaned up, and FaceTime each other while making coffee and getting ready for the day. We're also about to try out remote gaming tomorrow with some friends of ours from Pittsburgh--they, like us, are big board gaming geeks. I'm not sure exactly what we're going to play or how it'll pan out, but I'm excited to try!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lady and I took a page from a &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2020/04/the-best-board-games-to-play-with-your-quarantined-housemates/"&gt;recent list of recommended quarantine board games&lt;/a&gt; and purchased &lt;em&gt;Star Realms&lt;/em&gt;. Think: a super-simple mash-up of &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dominion&lt;/em&gt;. It's a deck-building game with a common "market" of cards you can purchase, and the goal is to use those cards to bludgeon your opponent to death in the most sci-fi manner possible. Meanwhile, I sunk several days in over at &lt;a href="https://www.heroforge.com/"&gt;Hero Forge&lt;/a&gt; designing avatars for her and me. I think they came out pretty well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/heroforge.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of remote activities together, we actually did try our hand at a "remote viewing" of a movie, and it worked remarkably well! Two of our runners friends joined us to watch &lt;em&gt;A League Of Their Own&lt;/em&gt;, both because one of them had never seen it before, and because of &lt;a href="https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2890923-mary-pratt-last-surviving-rockford-peach-dies-at-age-101"&gt;last week's news that the last of the original Rockford Peaches passed away at 101&lt;/a&gt;. We'd originally hoped to use a video synchronization platform like &lt;a href="https://www.netflixparty.com/"&gt;Netflix Party&lt;/a&gt;, but Netflix doesn't have &lt;em&gt;A League Of Their Own&lt;/em&gt;; Amazon Prime does. So we looked into &lt;a href="https://www.kastapp.co/"&gt;Kast&lt;/a&gt;, but after 30 minutes of tinkering, it was clear the app is still too young and rough around the edges; we were constantly having either sound or video issues. So we did it the old-fashioned way: fired up a Zoom chat, and counted down to hitting "Play" out loud. And it actually worked quite well! We were never more than 20 seconds off each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/aloto.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our sudden and constant presence all day every may have caught our pets off guard, but they sure seem to be enjoying it. Zippy is scampering around us, jumping on our laps, and trying to jump on our work table one minute, then is passed out on the couch for hours on end the next. Clover, meanwhile, seems to find a napping spot anywhere she goes, but has started expecting treats at all hours of the day (partly our fault for giving her the occasional piece of banana with breakfast... and piece of fruit or veggie for lunch... and for dinner... ). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/aminals.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest changes on my end (besides the obvious, of course), was buying a new laptop. This has been on my list for several months, as my aging MacBook Pro Mid-2014 has been struggling more and more to keep up with workloads. When the new laptop arrived, it took three entire days to fully transfer and configure it just right; I'm still coming across things here and there that need to be fully fleshed out (e.g., screen saver still isn't the picture collage, and it's not properly password protected, and the desktop backgrounds don't switch out, and other small but noticeable things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the thing I wasn't expecting that hit me really hard when it was time to shut down, wipe, and ship out the old laptop was the melancholy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd purchased this old laptop (aptly-named "Apollo") in September 2014 in the throes of writing my dissertation. I remember it distinctly: sitting in the Squirrel Hill Starbucks, ear pods in, listening to some Pandora station while typing away in the Latex document... when suddenly my ear pods &lt;em&gt;screeeeeched&lt;/em&gt;, my screen froze, and moments later, my ear pods went silent and the screen went dark. I rebooted, and... nothing. According to the Apple Geniuses later that evening, the motherboard has inexplicably fried. It was well out of warranty, so my only option was to purchase a brand-new laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/apollo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was Apollo. It got me through my PhD dissertation and defense, the move to Athens and the start of my tenure-track position at UGA, and through the first five years of it--well into my promotion and tenure process, my first couple of successful grants, and so, so many papers. It was a veritable workhorse of a laptop that, with a little sprucing up, still has some life in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I have a laptop that is literal orders of magnitude more powerful than the previous one, yet it has huge shoes to fill. We'll see if the new laptop--&lt;a href="https://www.zeldadungeon.net/wiki/images/5/52/Dinraal.jpg"&gt;Dinraal&lt;/a&gt;--is up to the task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/dinraal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's next?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure, honestly. We're taking it one day at a time. We're being kind to each other and ourselves. We're trying to be safe, not just for us, but for everyone else around us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay safe and happy, my friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="covid-19"></category><category term="sars-cov-2"></category><category term="work from home"></category><category term="wfh"></category><category term="zelda"></category><category term="snacks"></category><category term="running"></category><category term="social distancing"></category><category term="projects"></category><category term="pandemic"></category><category term="the lady"></category><category term="furbabies"></category><category term="zippy the cat"></category><category term="clover the bun"></category></entry><entry><title>Breath of Fresh (albeit, indoor) Air</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2020/05/20/breath-of-fresh-air/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-20T14:12:42-04:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T14:42:01-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2020-05-20:/blog/2020/05/20/breath-of-fresh-air/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/lakehylia.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a divergence that is simultaneously strange and entirely predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow me to explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, &lt;a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2019/08/07/marathon-training-mode-enable/"&gt;I've been training for my first marathon in 4.5 years for
the past several months&lt;/a&gt;.
It's largely consisted of &lt;a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/training/a20807188/how-do-i-build-a-training-base/"&gt;base-building&lt;/a&gt;,
but in the last couple of weeks we entered the "official …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/lakehylia.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a divergence that is simultaneously strange and entirely predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow me to explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First and foremost, &lt;a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2019/08/07/marathon-training-mode-enable/"&gt;I've been training for my first marathon in 4.5 years for
the past several months&lt;/a&gt;.
It's largely consisted of &lt;a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/training/a20807188/how-do-i-build-a-training-base/"&gt;base-building&lt;/a&gt;,
but in the last couple of weeks we entered the "official" 16-week marathon training
period...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...and my knee started pulling. Oh! And it coincided with the first week of
decent summer weather we've had here in Athens since...2018? And if the past
two weeks are any indication, this summer is going to be &lt;a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2016/08/23/the-summer-doldrums-arent-all-theyre-cracked-up-to-be/"&gt;as bad as that brutal
one in 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/goroncity.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I noticed the pulling in my knee the week before "official" training was
to begin, my coach and I agreed--in the name of being super-cautious this early
in the training cycle--that I would take a week off from running, focus on
cross-training and physical therapy exercises, and let my knee heal up. During
this time, I dove into the 2017 hit &lt;em&gt;Zelda: Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt;, the new Zelda
release for the Nintendo Switch, and logged--to use the technical term--a shitton
of hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/hillside.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me back up a little further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've never been secretive about my love of video gaming (and board gaming, and
regular old sportsball gaming... any kind of gaming, really). But my real passion
in video games has largely been constrained to variants of
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/First-person_shooter"&gt;first-person shooters&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real-time_strategy"&gt;real-time strategy&lt;/a&gt;. This
includes the usual suspects like &lt;em&gt;Left 4 Dead 2&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;StarCraft II&lt;/em&gt;,
but also slight variations like &lt;em&gt;Civilization V&lt;/em&gt; (haven't gotten the hang of &lt;em&gt;VI&lt;/em&gt;
yet), &lt;em&gt;Cities: Skylines&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Homeworld&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Sins of a Solar Empire&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upshot: &lt;em&gt;Zelda&lt;/em&gt; has never really been on my radar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, &lt;strong&gt;of course&lt;/strong&gt; I'm familiar with the Zelda franchise. Back in the days
of the &lt;a href="https://www.dkoldies.com/game-boy-original-system-nintendo/"&gt;OG GameBoy&lt;/a&gt;,
I played &lt;em&gt;Link's Awakening&lt;/em&gt;. A lot of it. I played through it so many times I
eventually figured out how to find enough "secret seashells" to get the Master
Sword just before completing the 4th of the 8 main dungeons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/linksawakening_orig.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(if it's possible to get the sword sooner than that, don't bother,
I don't want to know)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for those who know the larger Zelda lore, this installment exists awkwardly
both within but also without the Zelda story. I mean--SPOILERS for a 20+ year old
game SPOILERS--it was all a dream. Or was it instead a reality that existed
within our own, but vanished when the Wind Fish woke up? Who knows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/linksawakening_switch.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(apparently there was a Nintendo Switch remake of &lt;em&gt;Link's Awakening&lt;/em&gt;?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, while the usual Zelda themes certainly exist in &lt;em&gt;Link's Awakening&lt;/em&gt;,
the specific story points don't. So years later it was a shock to learn that
Link actually had a primary antagonist, &lt;strong&gt;Ganon&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first met my future wife, one of the many things about her that charmed
me was her love of the &lt;em&gt;Zelda&lt;/em&gt; franchise, especially &lt;em&gt;Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt;. I was
never super motivated to play the games myself, but something that seems almost
uniquely exclusive to Zelda games: they're incredibly fun to watch someone else
play! Even better, The Lady and I soon discovered that, not only did we have
different playstyles when it came to video games, but they complemented each other
in a way that really helped her/us solve the puzzles in these games with
ruthless efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even after watching her crush Ganon in &lt;em&gt;Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Twilight Princess&lt;/em&gt;,
and Ganon's progenitor in &lt;em&gt;Skyward Sword&lt;/em&gt; (which I bought her as a gift on the
very first Nintendo console we ever owned together... awwwwwww), I still never
felt the itch to play the game myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when I likewise bought &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt;, again for her to play, I once
more assumed I'd watch, point things out here and there, and let her Zelda
fandom run wild. Plus, I'd seen the reviews of this installment, and knew that
while they'd thrown out a lot of "typical" Zelda grind, they also added a bunch
of new gaming mechanisms that, on the surface, I held my nose for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breakable weapons: I'd played games where weapons only lasted for finite
 amounts of time, and &lt;em&gt;holy shit&lt;/em&gt; did this mechanic annoy the crap out of me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Recipes: I haven't actually played a game with this mechanic, but it's been
 showing up more frequently in RPGs, a gaming genre I generally have a very,
 very hard time getting into.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seasonality: This encompasses not only night/day changes, but also changes
 in weather patterns in-game, and subsequent changes in clothing / preparation
 of countermeasures (food, elixirs) in order to survive. I've played a lot of games
 with the night/day mechanic and have found it "meh" at best, super f*ckin
 annoying at worst. Combined with the need to constantly swap out clothing
 to adjust (and potentially lose abilities the previous clothing gave me) was
 irksome just to think about.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonlinear open world: Again, nothing against nonlinear gameplay--I for one
 love that &lt;em&gt;Civilization&lt;/em&gt; has multiple win conditions, and that the &lt;em&gt;StarCraft II&lt;/em&gt;
 missions are built to discourage "turtling" and force you to get creative--but
 as an avid follower of &lt;a href="https://www.escapistmagazine.com/v2/series/zero-punctuation/"&gt;Zero Punctuation&lt;/a&gt;
 I know how "well" Ubisoft's (for example) "nonlinear" "open world" games have
 faired, and for the life of me I couldn't see a game on Zelda's scope doing
 any better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boy oh boy, was I &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/lostwoods.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched The Lady play a game of her own for quite awhile, and at some point just
kinda thought: eh, why not? and started my own game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was &lt;em&gt;hooked&lt;/em&gt;. I can't even explain why; even while writing that list of
grievances, I kept thinking of examples &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; than &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt; with
those mechanics and getting annoyed all over again. And yet, these are so well-done
in &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt; that I don't even notice them. Even moreso, annoyances
in previous Zelda iterations--the "forced save points" of &lt;em&gt;Skyward Sword&lt;/em&gt;,
the nails-on-a-chalkboard running-back-and-forth over the &lt;em&gt;Ocarina&lt;/em&gt; landscape to
finish a simple side quest, the rupee limitations of literally every other
&lt;em&gt;Zelda&lt;/em&gt; game (until you bought a bigger rupee purse ???), the constant hunt for
more arrows, and the lack of any jumping ability--they're all gone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best thing I can say about this game is that they did an incredible job of
1) identifying the annoying things of previous Zelda games and cutting them out,
and 2) introducing these new mechanics in a way that felt natural and intuitive.
That's really the crux of it: the game is &lt;em&gt;easy to figure out&lt;/em&gt;, even while the
actual gameplay is incredibly, brutally, and satisfyingly challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That mastery of basics is why the game scales to such a &lt;em&gt;massive&lt;/em&gt; landscape (thank
you, travel points!); that's why there's enough room for three distinct and gorgeous
dragons that fill you with excitement every time their music comes out of nowhere;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/dinraal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that's why staying in the nearest stable during a thunderstorm or going deep
into the arctic tundra feels so much like curling up in front of a crackling
fire on a freezing cold day;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/snow.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that's why, even after completing part of a main quest, you'll find yourself
returning over and over to the same points on the map--to see an old friend,
find a new side quest, or exchange some shiny rocks you could sell anywhere for
a better price but you keep coming here because something about it makes you
feel at home;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/zoradomain.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that's why you can take a break in between main quests
to try and ride a stag;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/shrinequest.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and yes, this is an actual side quest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nintendo knocked this one clear out of the park. It's so wonderfully and
incredibly immersive: I go from exploring the freezing cold peaks of the
Hebra mountains to chasing down a monster aficionado with a nighttime shop along
the southeastern coastline with absolutely no recollection of how I transitioned
from one to the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But by far, the single biggest surprise is &lt;strong&gt;the plot&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s nuanced, and
mysterious, and even chilling in some cases, and it has me on the edge of my
seat wanting to know what happens next. Previously, I’ve always felt the plot in
Zelda games was a perpetual weakness: Zelda/Link good, Ganon bad, bludgeon Ganon
until bad goes away and credits roll. But this game--at least so far (I’m not
done yet)--makes me think there’s something at work beyond Ganon and his usual
hijinks. The "good guys" in particular don’t seem perfect; I’m being led to
think they made mistakes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, classes start this week, so it's unlikely I'll be making fast progress
over the next few months. But I do know The Lady was pretty thrilled to unlock
one particular character from previous Zelda games who, while technically
present in this game, required some external convincing to join the quest:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/botw/epona.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am loving everything about this game. Go buy it and forget reality! It's a
great way to kill time while healing from an injury.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="breath of the wild"></category><category term="zelda"></category><category term="running injury"></category><category term="running"></category><category term="gaming"></category><category term="video gaming"></category><category term="nintendo"></category><category term="nintendo switch"></category><category term="ocarina of time"></category><category term="link's awakening"></category><category term="skyward sword"></category><category term="gaming nerds"></category><category term="the lady"></category></entry><entry><title>Quinnwitz in Ireland</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2019/06/03/quinnwitz-in-ireland/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-03T19:24:54-04:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T14:42:01-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2019-06-03:/blog/2019/06/03/quinnwitz-in-ireland/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/gapofdunloe.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;([click to embiggen]({attach}/images/ireland/gapofdunloe_orig.jpg))&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lady and I just returned from a 12-day trip to Ireland (with a stop at the
very start in Kent, England, to visit some &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kmorrell04"&gt;dear friends&lt;/a&gt;
and their &lt;a href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2019/06/03/quinnwitz-in-ireland/kent.jpg"&gt;6-month old&lt;/a&gt; twins!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't begin to describe how incredible the trip was …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/gapofdunloe.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p style="text-align: center;"&gt;([click to embiggen]({attach}/images/ireland/gapofdunloe_orig.jpg))&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lady and I just returned from a 12-day trip to Ireland (with a stop at the
very start in Kent, England, to visit some &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kmorrell04"&gt;dear friends&lt;/a&gt;
and their &lt;a href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2019/06/03/quinnwitz-in-ireland/kent.jpg"&gt;6-month old&lt;/a&gt; twins!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't begin to describe how incredible the trip was. It was one of those dreams
you realize at some point you've been discussing with your significant other for
&lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt;--quips here and there about "wouldn't it be awesome to visit x" or
"when we visit y someday...". Ireland had been at the top of our list of
international locations to see since years before we even got married, but it
was always 5-10 years in the future, and never got any closer to reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until that dear friend's wedding in Bedford, England, in late summer 2017. At
some point during some downtime in that long weekend, Ireland came up again in
the same way it always did, but whether it was the international setting we were
already in or some other twist of fate, The Lady suddenly said: "Let's set a date."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That day in August 2017, we set a tentative, but &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt;, date of May 2019.
And we nailed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logistics of the trip were pretty complicated. First, we wanted to fly
into London and spend a day visiting those friends of ours out in Kent. Next,
we wanted to start our journey in Ireland by spending a few days in Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, we wanted to hike in &lt;a href="https://www.wicklowmountainsnationalpark.ie/"&gt;Wicklow National Park&lt;/a&gt;
before spending a few days in Killarney, exploring the &lt;a href="https://ringofkerrytourism.com/"&gt;Ring of Kerry&lt;/a&gt;
(important note: not a "ring" as in a piece of jewelry).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we wanted to drive to Galway and spend a few days there, before
returning to Dublin and flying back home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tl;dr A travel agent will make your life a lot easier when your international
travels have a lot of moving parts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Emerald Isle&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country was seriously amazing. Ireland is the most incredible combination
of different landscapes and ecosystems all coexisting side by side; driving
from Dublin to Killarney to Galway and back will show multiple distinct
countrysides that change seamlessly yet suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further adieu, I'll post some of my favorite pictures here from the
trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/oscar_wilde.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In front of the Oscar Wilde statue in Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/guinness_storehouse.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Guinness Storehouse in Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/book_of_kells.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href="https://www.tcd.ie/visitors/book-of-kells/"&gt;Book of Kells exhibit&lt;/a&gt; at Trinity College in Dublin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/wicklow_park.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Wicklow park, before a 9-mile hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/wicklow_park2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also Wicklow park, about halfway through the hike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/gap_of_dunloe.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running the &lt;a href="http://www.theringofkerry.com/the-gap-of-dunloe"&gt;Gap of Dunloe&lt;/a&gt; in Killarney.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/gap_me.jpg"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/ireland/gap_lady.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lady and myself running in the Gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/irish_wolfhound.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lady meets an adorable Irish wolfhound during our Ring of Kerry tour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/ring_of_kerry.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coastline stop along the Ring of Kerry tour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/secret_garden.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We met a very friendly regular at the &lt;a href="http://www.secretgardengalway.com/"&gt;Secret Garden&lt;/a&gt; in Galway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/ireland/galway.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sitting in the main square at Galway.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="travel"></category><category term="ireland"></category><category term="#quinnwitzabroad"></category><category term="heritage"></category><category term="dublin"></category><category term="killarney"></category><category term="galway"></category><category term="ring of kerry"></category><category term="cliffs of moher"></category><category term="cliffs of insanity"></category><category term="wicklow"></category></entry><entry><title>StarCraft II Questions</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2019/01/31/starcraft-ii-questions/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-01-31T15:26:42-05:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T14:42:01-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2019-01-31:/blog/2019/01/31/starcraft-ii-questions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/do_you_wanna_play_sc2.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been sick the past couple of days. In between drinking way too much tea,
passing out cold, and actually getting the occasional bit of work done, I've been
(re-)playing a decent amount of &lt;em&gt;StarCraft II&lt;/em&gt;, specifically the &lt;em&gt;Legacy of the Void&lt;/em&gt;
(&lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt;) campaign. It's the final installment of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/do_you_wanna_play_sc2.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been sick the past couple of days. In between drinking way too much tea,
passing out cold, and actually getting the occasional bit of work done, I've been
(re-)playing a decent amount of &lt;em&gt;StarCraft II&lt;/em&gt;, specifically the &lt;em&gt;Legacy of the Void&lt;/em&gt;
(&lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt;) campaign. It's the final installment of SC2, and honestly it's the one
I find most frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, it's not the dialogue, which is &lt;em&gt;super&lt;/em&gt; cliche and overwrought, but it's
endemic across the entire SC2 series. Also, the &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt; gameplay honestly makes
up for it (as is true for most of the SC2 series).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather, my problem is with the actual storytelling. There are lots of
sprawling story elements but a lot of them just don't make
any sense. &lt;em&gt;Heart of the Swarm&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;HotS&lt;/em&gt;)
&lt;a href="https://magsol.wordpress.com/2013/04/01/starcraft-ii-heart-of-the-swarm-review/"&gt;had a few chin-scratching moments&lt;/a&gt;,
but overall the storyline was a pretty clear and well-motivated revenge tale.
Even before that, &lt;em&gt;Wings of Liberty&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;WoL&lt;/em&gt;) was a clear and compact story of
regret and redemption. So while the &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt; gameplay was outstanding, it was
extremely jarring for the story to be so jumbled and reliant on retconning a
large amount of StarCraft lore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So may I present, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-x1YuvUQFJ0"&gt;inspired by RedLetterMedia's treatment of &lt;em&gt;Prometheus&lt;/em&gt;
several years back&lt;/a&gt;, a list
of questions that came to mind. Presented in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/like_farmville.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So apparently Emil Narud / Samir Duran was &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; a fallen Xel'Naga, as he said as much
  in the &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt; epilogue missions. Why was he alive all this time, but not Amon?
  How did he escape Amon's fate?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why did he take the form of a human instead of some all-powerful hybrid like the
  ones he was cultivating in those years? What was stopping Amon from taking the form
  of a human as well?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What were the purposes of Duran's machinations in &lt;em&gt;Brood War&lt;/em&gt;? As stated at the time,
 it was in the service of returning Amon and breeding the hybrid, but if he was
 a full Xel'Naga, why would Amon's resurrection even be necessary? Couldn't Narud
 just remake all life in the universe, then resurrect Amon at his leisure for
 their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_World%27s_End_(film)"&gt;post-universe-destruction celebration party&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/siege_tank_rush.gif"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh man, the &lt;a href="https://starcraft.fandom.com/wiki/Khala"&gt;Khala&lt;/a&gt;. Supposedly the thing
that both saved the Protoss race back in the day, but also nearly led to their
destruction when Amon infiltrated it in &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt;. A nice symmetry, sure, but... ok.
So. The Khala was linked through khaydarin crystals, which are rife throughout
 Protoss technology. The Protoss themselves interface with it through their
 nerve cords, which [SPOILER ALERT] they all sever at the end of &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt; to
 drive Amon back into the Void. But couldn't he just live on in their
 technology?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Would the Protoss have to derive entirely new, non-khaydarin crystal
 technology to completely drive out Amon?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How on Kerrigan's red Char did they manage to sever the nerve cords of
 literally all the Protoss of the Golden Armada--including those who had not
 yet arrived at Aiur--in the two minutes that the keystone was able to contain
 Amon?! &lt;a href="https://starcraft.fandom.com/wiki/Rohana"&gt;Rohana&lt;/a&gt; proved that physical
 distance was not an issue for Amon, only connection to the Khala via nerve cords
 did. How could they have possibly gotten the order out to all those Protoss
 in such a short period?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amon is shown leaving Artanis' body when Zeratul severs his nerve cords. But
 couldn't Amon just possess Artanis? Why was Amon able to inhabit the Khala,
 but not individuals?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mean, where is the Khala even centralized? If it's just the psychic
 connection between Protoss--and therefore completely decentralized--wouldn't
 Amon act more like a virus? Why would severing everyone's nerve cords suddenly
 leave Amon homeless? Is severing your nerve cords like a vaccination?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would Amon even need a "host body" if he's able to take over literally
 all the Khalai Protoss?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/nuclear_launch.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How did Amon control the Zerg? Through an Overmind? Where was it located? If
 not, did he exert control over every individual Zerg? How? Why couldn't he do
 the same thing through the Protoss? Or hell, even the Terrans?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did he possess the Zerg? Why couldn't he control Kerrigan's Zerg? Or again,
 the Protoss?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where was Amon in the intervening period of &lt;em&gt;Heart of the Swarm&lt;/em&gt; when he was
 (presumably) already revived following the conclusion of &lt;em&gt;Wings of Liberty&lt;/em&gt;, but
 not yet the main villain at beginning of &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt;?
 &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/712/"&gt;Drinking at a bar somewhere&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The original StarCraft lore seems to be retconned to suggest (in no uncertain
  terms) that any and all tampering in the development of the Zerg and Protoss
  was the fault of Amon and his followers and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; part of the original plan
  put in motion by the Xel'Naga. Does that mean the Khala was Amon's
  creation, as well as the Overmind? What was even supposed to happen absent the
  Khala or the Overmind?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why was Amon so much more powerful than Ouros? They're both Xel'Naga; wouldn't
 they be evenly matched?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kerrigan was Xel'Naga for all of an hour before she flat-out blasted Amon out
 of existence. How? Why was she better equipped to deal with Amon in such short
 order, compared to a friendly Xel'Naga trapped in the Void for eons?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sure, maybe the combined might of both Narud and Amon kept Ouros trapped
 in the Void, but Narud was only with his master for all of a campaign and a half;
 plus, it was only &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Stukov dealt Narud the killing blow in the epilogue
 that Ouros began the process of giving Kerrigan his essence. Wouldn't the combined
 might of Kerrigan and Ouros be infinitely more powerful than just Amon?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If Amon killed all those slumbering Xel'Naga in Ulnar, why wouldn't they also
 just return to the Void, as Amon did at the end of &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/no_patience.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Tal'darim are introduced in &lt;em&gt;WoL&lt;/em&gt; as a "fanatical" group of Protoss who
 generally do their own thing. In &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt;, it's revealed that they're actually
 in league with Amon. But in &lt;em&gt;WoL&lt;/em&gt;, they are &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; fighting &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; the
 retrieval of the artifact pieces--an essential step to assembling the artifact,
 using it to de-infest Kerrigan, and capturing all that power to resurrect Amon.
 This connection becomes even more confusing when considering that it was
 Moebius Corps who literally hired Jim Raynor and
 his Raiders to assemble the artifact pieces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;i.e., Moebius Corps was led by Emil Narud, aka Samir Duran, aka
 &lt;em&gt;the one dude who's been trying for millennia to resurrect Amon&lt;/em&gt;. Why would
 the Tal'darim fight directly against him? Did it take them the countless ages
 between the &lt;a href="https://starcraft.fandom.com/wiki/Aeon_of_Strife"&gt;Aeon of Strife&lt;/a&gt;
 and &lt;em&gt;HotS&lt;/em&gt; to realize they were working for the same guy?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do the Tal'darim still have their nerve cords? Are they connected to the
  Khala?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It would seem not, since after Alarak becomes their highlord and turns
  them against Amon, I would think Amon's first course of action would be to
  take control of them, but he doesn't, or can't. But it seems like they &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;
  have nerve cords, given Alarak's huge jagged ponytail thing. So are they
  somehow &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; connected to the Khala, despite having nerve cords? If that's
  the case, why can't the Daelaam do the same? Is it a &lt;em&gt;choice&lt;/em&gt; to connect to
  the Khala? Is it like the Force--something you can train yourself to use,
  but which you can also consciously separate yourself from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Alarak is, like, wicked powerful. &lt;em&gt;Crazy&lt;/em&gt; powerful. He breaks through a
  stasis field on the &lt;em&gt;Spear of Adun&lt;/em&gt; like it was tissue paper, and blasts open
  an armored door and destroys a warp crystal on Aiur with a &lt;em&gt;single shot&lt;/em&gt;. Where
  was that ability when he was fighting Malash for highlord?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/7_marines.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="https://starcraft.fandom.com/wiki/Nerazim"&gt;Nerazim&lt;/a&gt; are said to draw
 their power "from the &lt;a href="https://starcraft.fandom.com/wiki/Void"&gt;Void&lt;/a&gt;". What
 even is the Void? Some kind of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mirror_Universe"&gt;parallel evil dimension&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But the Void clearly has toxic and destabilizing effects on the "current"
 dimension, since anytime a rift opens it pretty much wipes everything it touches
 apart. But then, in the epilogue, everyone gears up and heads into the Void! How?!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So, the Dark Templar get their power from the same place as the Xel'Naga? And
 Amon? Wouldn't that mean only a Dark Templar can defeat Amon? Or that Amon
 could pierce Nerazim cloaks?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Or, wouldn't that mean Amon would have total control over their abilities,
 making them just as vulnerable to his influence as the Khalai Protoss?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seriously, how are &lt;em&gt;missiles&lt;/em&gt; going to be an effective weapon in the Void?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Against Narud and Amon?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;AMON&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sc2_questions/i_got_this.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let's talk a bit about Amon's "plan". He wanted to break the
 &lt;a href="https://starcraft.fandom.com/wiki/Infinite_Cycle"&gt;Infinite Cycle&lt;/a&gt;
 and remake all life in his image. But the end credits of &lt;em&gt;LotV&lt;/em&gt; literally
 said, that with Kerrigan's ascension and the alliance's victory over Amon,
 the Infinite Cycles came to an end. So... mission accomplished?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So, from the Void, he uses his pawn / follower / fellow Xel'Naga (???) Narud to
 work on a way to resurrect him, creating "false" hybrid armies in the meantime.
 Were these hybrid basically accelerated versions of what the Infinite Cycles
 were supposed to "naturally" result in? I mean, weren't the Zerg and Protoss
 ultimately meant to merge?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amon corrupted the Zerg, creating an overriding imperative to destroy or
 assimilate the Protoss. Since the Protoss can't be infested, I would assume that
 basically amounts to a "kill" order?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyway, the Overmind cleverly tries to circumvent that order by creating the
 Queen of Blades, with supposedly only slightly more free will than it. Why?
 Where does that slightly-more-free-will come from? Just because she's Terran,
 and therefore not a Xel'Naga creation? Or was it something unique to Kerrigan?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course, she was only infested &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Amon's death. How was Narud/Duran
 planning to resurrect his master, then? It was only the &lt;em&gt;de&lt;/em&gt;-infestation of
 Kerrigan that gave him enough power to resurrect Amon. So until that unlikely
 sequence of infestation-deinfestation events happened, had he just been spending
 a lot of time on his Pelaton and researching
 &lt;a href="https://www.tesla.com/powerwall"&gt;cutting-edge battery technology&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really, I just think &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AX_FxBSEh1A"&gt;this game sucks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(not really tho)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="gaming"></category><category term="starcraft"></category><category term="starcraft ii"></category><category term="legacy of the void"></category><category term="protoss"></category><category term="xel'naga"></category><category term="blizzard"></category></entry><entry><title>An einsum use-case</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2018/06/19/an-einsum-use-case/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-06-19T16:58:02-04:00</published><updated>2018-06-19T16:58:02-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2018-06-19:/blog/2018/06/19/an-einsum-use-case/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/einsum/kOqM5.png"&gt;
(&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/26089893/understanding-numpys-einsum"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been working with some of my students on a paper for the &lt;a href="https://scipy2018.scipy.org/"&gt;SciPy Conference&lt;/a&gt; related to our OrNet project. Part of this involved designing our own &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixture_model#Gaussian_mixture_model"&gt;Gaussian Mixture Model&lt;/a&gt; (GMM). In doing so, I somewhat accidentally-on-purpose stumbled upon the beauty of &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt;. So I wanted to briefly …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/einsum/kOqM5.png"&gt;
(&lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/26089893/understanding-numpys-einsum"&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I've been working with some of my students on a paper for the &lt;a href="https://scipy2018.scipy.org/"&gt;SciPy Conference&lt;/a&gt; related to our OrNet project. Part of this involved designing our own &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mixture_model#Gaussian_mixture_model"&gt;Gaussian Mixture Model&lt;/a&gt; (GMM). In doing so, I somewhat accidentally-on-purpose stumbled upon the beauty of &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt;. So I wanted to briefly motivate its use (expanding upon the &lt;a href="https://medium.com/the-quarks/an-einsum-use-case-8dafcb933c66"&gt;short use-case I wrote on my research group's blog&lt;/a&gt;) and show the performance results of re-implementing iterative computations using &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="Gaussian-Madness"&gt;Gaussian Madness&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="#Gaussian-Madness"&gt;&amp;#182;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the critical steps of this algorithm is to evaluate the probability of any given point $\vec{x}$ under the model that we've learned so far (the current values of $\vec{\mu}$ and $\Sigma$. In higher dimensions (as in, higher than 1), this has a pretty tricky formula:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
$$
P(\vec{x} | \vec{\mu}, \Sigma) = \frac{\exp{(-\frac{1}{2}(\vec{x} - \vec{\mu})^T \Sigma^{-1} (\vec{x} - \vec{\mu}) )}} {\sqrt{(2 \pi)^2 \det{(\Sigma)} }}
$$
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's...messy. The things that make it particularly tough to efficiently evaluate include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the matrix multiplication in the numerator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the inversion of $\Sigma$ in the numerator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the determinant of $\Sigma$ in the denominator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the fact that this has to be computed for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; $\vec{x}$ (thousands), under &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; combination of $\mu$ and $\Sigma$ (often a few dozen), at &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; iteration of the algorithm (often a few dozen)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait! That's not all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also critical to the GMM are the &lt;em&gt;update&lt;/em&gt; steps: re-estimating the current values of the parameters so they (hopefully) better fit your data. This happens &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In multidimensional wonderlands, the updates of the parameters look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
$$
\vec{\mu}_{ki} = \frac{1}{N_k} \sum_{n = 1}^N r_{kn} \vec{x}_n
$$
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
$$
\Sigma_{ki} = \frac{1}{N_k} \sum_{n = 1}^N r_{kn} (\vec{x}_n - \vec{\mu}_{ki})(\vec{x}_n - \vec{\mu}_{ki})^T
$$
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first equation for $\vec{\mu}_{ki}$--the $k^{th}$ component (one of the 50-100) at the $i^{th}$ iteration (often at least a few dozen)--is a "fairly" easy multiplication of each data point $\vec{x}_n$ by some number $r_{kn}$, all summed up and scaled by $\frac{1}{N_k}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second equation is a lot harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For every $\vec{\mu}_{ki}$ we have a corresponding $\Sigma_{ki}$. Which, remember, is a full matrix. This involves taking the $\vec{\mu}_{ki}$ we computed in the first equation, and computing outer products with every data point $\vec{x}_n$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Outer product" is a fancy name for "matrix multiplication"!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="Bring-on-the-Code"&gt;Bring on the Code&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="#Bring-on-the-Code"&gt;&amp;#182;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell jp-mod-noOutputs  "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[1]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;numpy&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;scipy.linalg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sla&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So of course, I initially implemented these two core operations in the way that made the most sense: using &lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt; functions and Python comprehensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For computing $P(\vec{x})$&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell jp-mod-noOutputs  "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[2]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;px1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;det&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sla&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;det&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;inv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sla&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;inv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;inv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;dot&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;((((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;**&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;det&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;**&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;px&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;exp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;strong&gt;for re-computing $\mu$ and $\Sigma$&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell jp-mod-noOutputs  "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[3]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;musig1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu_next&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[:,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;newaxis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;
    
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;zeros&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;shape&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ri&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;zip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu_next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;outer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ri&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma_next&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu_next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma_next&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These were computational &lt;em&gt;bears&lt;/em&gt;. In &lt;code&gt;px1&lt;/code&gt;, the line starting &lt;code&gt;p = ...&lt;/code&gt; is a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; computational cost: doing two dot products inside a loop over all the data points $\vec{x}_n$ is really, really expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in &lt;code&gt;musig1&lt;/code&gt;, the operation to compute the next value of $\Sigma$ involves computing the outer product of every $\vec{x}_n$ subtracted by the current value of $\vec{\mu}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suffice to say, when it came time to actually run the algorithm, it shouldn't come as a surprise that, with a dataset of roughly 130,000 points in 2 dimensions, each iteration of our algorithm took about &lt;strong&gt;52 seconds&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...the &lt;em&gt;vast majority&lt;/em&gt; of which was spent computing dot products!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/einsum/before.png" alt="before"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than half of a single iteration was devoted to dot products in the &lt;code&gt;px1&lt;/code&gt; function above. That's &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just for grins, let's time everything:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell jp-mod-noOutputs  "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[4]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;size&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;130000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# To simulate the data I was working with.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;mu&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Compute an actual mean.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;array&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;([[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;random&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;130000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell   "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[5]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;timeit&lt;/span&gt; px1(X, mu, sigma)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-Cell-outputWrapper"&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea jp-Cell-outputArea"&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea-child"&gt;

    
    &lt;div class="jp-OutputPrompt jp-OutputArea-prompt"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-RenderedText jp-OutputArea-output" data-mime-type="text/plain"&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;301 ms ± 6.99 ms per loop (mean ± std. dev. of 7 runs, 1 loop each)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell   "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[6]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;timeit&lt;/span&gt; musig1(X, r)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-Cell-outputWrapper"&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea jp-Cell-outputArea"&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea-child"&gt;

    
    &lt;div class="jp-OutputPrompt jp-OutputArea-prompt"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-RenderedText jp-OutputArea-output" data-mime-type="text/plain"&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;847 ms ± 5.47 ms per loop (mean ± std. dev. of 7 runs, 1 loop each)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's a full second of computation just for 1 of the Gaussian components (i.e., one pair of $\mu$ and $\Sigma$). Crank that number of components up to 50 and, well, there's your ~50-second runtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was admittedly at a bit of a loss here, considering I was already using NumPy constructs. But at the same time, these were highly structured linear algebra operations; there had to be something more efficient?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="einsum-to-the-Rescue"&gt;&lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt; to the Rescue&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="#einsum-to-the-Rescue"&gt;&amp;#182;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DISCLAIMER: I should highlight that I &lt;em&gt;didn't immediately land on this&lt;/em&gt;. It took some Googling around and some sitting and thinking before I figured out how this could be used. Then it took some more trial-and-error to actually get it to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But work, it did. Holy crap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;np.einsum&lt;/code&gt; is an implementation of the &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/EinsteinSummation.html"&gt;Einstein Summation&lt;/a&gt;, which is a super-fancy term for a cool (but admittedly tricky-to-grasp) shorthand notation for dealing with multiplications and summations of vectors, matrices, and tensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't rehash the basic examples I've found across the web that helped me understand how this works, but I will give special emphasis to two articles:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://obilaniu6266h16.wordpress.com/2016/02/04/einstein-summation-in-numpy/"&gt;Einstein Summation in NumPy&lt;/a&gt;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ajcr.net/Basic-guide-to-einsum/"&gt;A basic introduction to NumPy's einsum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found #2 particularly accessible, but I'd recommend both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took some doing, but I managed to rewrite both equations using &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt;s:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell jp-mod-noOutputs  "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[7]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;px2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;det&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sla&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;det&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;inv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sla&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;inv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;###&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;einsum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;ni,ji,ni-&amp;gt;n&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;inv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;###&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;((((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;**&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;det&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;**&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;px&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;exp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;px&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell jp-mod-noOutputs  "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[8]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;musig2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu_next&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[:,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;newaxis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;###&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma_next&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;einsum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;ni,nj-&amp;gt;ij&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu_next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[:,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;np&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;newaxis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;X&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu_next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;N&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;###&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mu_next&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sigma_next&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;musig2&lt;/code&gt; use actually ended up being a straightforward application of the "each row of $A$ multiplied by $B$" rule at the end of the #2 link above, with the slight wrinkle of making the &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; axis, &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;, the one that is summed over in the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one in &lt;code&gt;px2&lt;/code&gt; was a lot harder, and for a time I wasn't convinced it could be done. At one point I was able to basically split the operation in two &lt;code&gt;einsums&lt;/code&gt; that were more or less identical to the one in &lt;code&gt;musig2&lt;/code&gt;; it basically involved a repeated application of "multiply each row of $A$ by $B$". But I kept hunting around the web, particularly for examples of multiplying many matrices together, and eventually managed to figure this one out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It boiled down to basics of how &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt; works: I knew the output had to be a list of numbers &lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt; long, and that the first and third inputs were identical (&lt;code&gt;ni&lt;/code&gt;). The key was: if everything had 2 axes going in, but only 1 axis was coming out, then all three inputs needed to share one axis that could be summed over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="With-great-power-blah-blah-blah"&gt;With great power blah blah blah&lt;a class="anchor-link" href="#With-great-power-blah-blah-blah"&gt;&amp;#182;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just for fun, let's run our examples again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell   "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[9]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;timeit&lt;/span&gt; px2(X, mu, sigma)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-Cell-outputWrapper"&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea jp-Cell-outputArea"&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea-child"&gt;

    
    &lt;div class="jp-OutputPrompt jp-OutputArea-prompt"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-RenderedText jp-OutputArea-output" data-mime-type="text/plain"&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;6.82 ms ± 32.7 µs per loop (mean ± std. dev. of 7 runs, 100 loops each)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-Cell jp-CodeCell jp-Notebook-cell   "&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputArea jp-Cell-inputArea"&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;In&amp;nbsp;[10]:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-CodeMirrorEditor jp-Editor jp-InputArea-editor" data-type="inline"&gt;
     &lt;div class="CodeMirror cm-s-jupyter"&gt;
&lt;div class=" highlight hl-ipython3"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;timeit&lt;/span&gt; musig2(X, r)
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

     &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-Cell-outputWrapper"&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea jp-Cell-outputArea"&gt;

&lt;div class="jp-OutputArea-child"&gt;

    
    &lt;div class="jp-OutputPrompt jp-OutputArea-prompt"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div class="jp-RenderedText jp-OutputArea-output" data-mime-type="text/plain"&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;7.37 ms ± 260 µs per loop (mean ± std. dev. of 7 runs, 100 loops each)
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To sum up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going from a list comprehension of calls to &lt;code&gt;numpy.dot&lt;/code&gt; to a single &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt; decreased runtime of a single iteration from &lt;strong&gt;300ms&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;7ms&lt;/strong&gt;, a speed-up of over 40x.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going from a loop of &lt;code&gt;numpy.outer&lt;/code&gt; products to a single &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt; decreased runtime of a single iteration from &lt;strong&gt;847ms&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;7.5ms&lt;/strong&gt;, a speed-up of over 110x.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I re-ran &lt;code&gt;cProfile&lt;/code&gt; to see what my performance gains were, and holy &lt;em&gt;crap&lt;/em&gt; Batman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/einsum/after.png" alt="after"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only was my total runtime down from ~52 seconds per iteration to a mere &lt;strong&gt;1.5 seconds per iteration&lt;/strong&gt;, but the most time-consuming block of my code was now &lt;code&gt;einsum&lt;/code&gt; itself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I wasn't going to argue with a full &lt;em&gt;order of magnitude&lt;/em&gt; reduction in runtime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="jp-Cell-inputWrapper"&gt;&lt;div class="jp-InputPrompt jp-InputArea-prompt"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="jp-RenderedHTMLCommon jp-RenderedMarkdown jp-MarkdownOutput " data-mime-type="text/markdown"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our SciPy paper is still under review, so feel free to &lt;a href="https://github.com/scipy-conference/scipy_proceedings/pull/396"&gt;head over there and check out&lt;/a&gt; how we're putting GMMs to use for bioimaging!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
    var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
    mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
    mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
    mathjaxscript.src = '//cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/mathjax/2.7.1/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
    mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
        "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
        "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
        "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
        "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
        "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
        "    displayAlign: 'center'," +
        "    displayIndent: '0em'," +
        "    showMathMenu: true," +
        "    tex2jax: { " +
        "        inlineMath: [ ['$','$'] ], " +
        "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
        "        processEscapes: true," +
        "        preview: 'TeX'," +
        "    }, " +
        "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
        " linebreaks: { automatic: true, width: '95% container' }, " +
        "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'black ! important'} }" +
        "    } " +
        "}); ";
    (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
}
&lt;/script&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="professional"></category><category term="einsum"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="gmm"></category><category term="gaussian mixture model"></category><category term="einstein summation"></category></entry><entry><title>Jedi Outcast: Echoes of a bygone gaming era</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2018/04/27/jedi-outcast-echoes-of-a-bygone-gaming-era/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-27T14:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-04-27T14:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2018-04-27:/blog/2018/04/27/jedi-outcast-echoes-of-a-bygone-gaming-era/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/lolrob.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should start by issuing fair warning: this is a post I've been meaning to write in some form or another for the better part of the last &lt;em&gt;15 years&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commence "old mang" jokes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there was a group of gamers I met many years ago who, to this day …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/lolrob.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should start by issuing fair warning: this is a post I've been meaning to write in some form or another for the better part of the last &lt;em&gt;15 years&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commence "old mang" jokes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there was a group of gamers I met many years ago who, to this day, remain some of my best friends. We don't keep in near-daily contact like we used to, but it doesn't take more than a couple friendly jabs to pick up right where we left off. Particularly at a time when I feel very alien and removed from the gaming community, both by virtue of stage of life as well as events of late, I want to hold up a sliver of the gamer's experience that, at least for me, was phenomenally positive and formative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jedi Outcast&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/jedi_outcast_gog.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(Source: https://www.gog.com/game/star_wars_jedi_knight_ii_jedi_outcast)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire story essentially revolves around a video game: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars_Jedi_Knight_II:_Jedi_Outcast"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jedi Knight II: Jedi Outcast&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. But while this seemingly-innocuous run-of-the-mill Star Wars game was the central impetus, its unique properties--which I can honestly say haven't been replicated in more recent games--gave rise to a community that still impacts me to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jedi Outcast&lt;/em&gt;, colloquially referred to either as "JK2" or "JO", is a first-person shooter that continued the adventures of Kyle Katarn started in the original &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars:_Dark_Forces"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dark Forces&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and carried forward in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Star_Wars_Jedi_Knight:_Dark_Forces_II"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jedi Knight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. It was, far and away, the finest installment of the series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/jk2_play.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JO came with a single-player campaign that involved an attempt by a fallen Jedi to harness Force energy in order to artificially infuse his warriors with the Force, essentially creating dark Jedi on-demand. It was quite engaging! But the real novelty, and probably the most unexpected success, was the multiplayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned before it had some unique properties that gave it its staying power. Among others, and in no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was the first game in the series to feature truly immersive lightsaber mechanics. &lt;em&gt;Dark Forces II&lt;/em&gt; had introduced lightsabers, but to wield it was essentially like watching a monkey hit something with a stick. JO made it look like it came out of a movie.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Force powers were also considerably better-integrated with gameplay. Again, &lt;em&gt;Dark Forces II&lt;/em&gt; had pioneered Force powers, but they were clunky in their use; in fact, you could beat the single player without ever using a single one. JO seamlessly wove their use into the game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The developers open-sourced the server-side JO code almost immediately after release, prompting the explosion of a modding community around the game, building everything from new in-game characters to new multiplayer maps to entire server mods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The multiplayer enabled what we affectionately referred to as a "chat room with a GUI": an environment where players could shoot and duel, but also literally stand around talking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/chat_gui.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the picture above, the dark text boxes you see above some players heads are the tell-tale indicators that the player is typing a message. Meanwhile, battle can literally rage around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All this gave rise to an environment conducive to the formation of "gaming clans": communities of fellow gaming nerds who enjoyed the game and the people in it. Numerous clans popped in and out of existence, with as many varieties of names and purposes and values as individuals on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's where I entered into things: my story begins in the fall of 2003, when I was just starting my first semester as a freshman at Georgia Tech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fall 2003&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd been the proud owner of a JK2 CD-ROM for a year or so at that point, but hadn't had a desktop powerful enough to play it. Now, armed with a brand-new Dell Optiplex with a 3GHz processor and 4GB RAM, I had enough horsepower to give the game a test drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah, and also study Computer Science at one of the finest institutions for the field in the world. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I devoured the single-player JO campaign, loving every minute of it. But when it came to the multiplayer, I was very hesitant. I remembered all too vividly the frantic competitiveness of multiplayer &lt;em&gt;StarCraft&lt;/em&gt; from high school--I'd been ranked in the Top 1000 at one point, but pretty much to the detriment of my sanity--and really didn't want to get similarly sucked into an anxiety-inducing hyper-competitive environment where, at the end of the day, all I had to show for my hours sunk into the game was a migraine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I could say one thing for sure: I was nowhere near as good at the multiplayer as I'd thought I was from the single-player. I got my ass handed to me. A &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt;. But another thing I quickly learned: the vast majority of the folks playing this game were &lt;em&gt;chill&lt;/em&gt;. The whole "chat room with a GUI" thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, I fell into an online clan, called "Imperial Forces". But my courtship with the clan was extremely brief: evidently, any bad clan can have one decent person in it, and after a &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; short membership--maybe a week?--I departed its ranks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And discovered the "Power of Thee."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/poticon.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, it was indeed "cleverly" titled to invoke a particular acronym. But beyond the name, it was the people: every single one of them was both super-chill and &lt;em&gt;super talented&lt;/em&gt;. I could tell there was considerable variation in age, both younger and older than me, but they were wholly welcoming. And so freaking &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky for me, they recruited me. But like any good Jedi organization, new recruits--apprentices--are assigned a master. My master was a veteran of JO, &lt;a href="https://www.ckaleb.com/jedi-outcast/"&gt;a Knight named Kaleb&lt;/a&gt;. He helped me learn the intricacies of the game, as well as the "protocols" that had arisen around the GUI-ified chat room of JO, things like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If someone has a chat window above their head, don't attack them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With great [admin] power comes great responsibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't take things too seriously, otherwise you'll get C4'd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/duel.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, I was deemed ready for my "Trials". Apprentices such as myself pass their Trials and become full members of the clan by winning at least 4 out of 6 lightsaber duels with Knight-level members or higher. I don't remember my exact record--I don't mean to toot my own horn, but it very well might have been 6-0 (Kaleb was a great teacher!)--but I passed my Trials and was duly Knight-ed into PoT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Spring 2004&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide a bit of context: JO was released in 2002. So right as I was hitting a stride with my new clan and actually &lt;em&gt;git good&lt;/em&gt; at multiplayer, the game had already been out for over two years. And on the "clan" scene, two years is an eternity. There were senior members of PoT--the "Council" members, including the original founders--whom I'd never met because they'd already moved on, essentially having gone permanently inactive. The active membership--Knights who'd passed their Trials and made up the bulk of the active membership, and Jedi Masters who were promoted from Knight by virtue of some outstanding contribution to the clan--kept things fresh by recruiting new talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the gears of time ground on. Spring 2004 was a particularly rough time for me personally, as I settled into my second semester of college and I was caught somewhere between who I'd been in high school and who I wanted to become as I moved into adulthood. My roommate, a dear friend from high school, was also going through some really hard times and ended up dropping out halfway through the semester, so I ended up being alone more often than not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the risk of sounding melodramatic, JO and PoT was an anchor; I was getting to know my fellow clanmates better, chatting with them directly over AOL Instant Messenger instead of exclusively through JO. Getting to know them as people, rather than avatars. Sharing experiences. It... helped. In more ways than I can recount, even now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that anchor was shifting in ways I hadn't been around long enough to realize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summer 2004&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In many ways, this was one of PoT's strongest seasons. In others, it was almost its end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd (somehow) secured an internship at an Atlanta-based supply-chain company, but because they had no idea what they wanted me to do, I found myself with a lot of free time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I exercised some of the new network connections I'd made through JO and organized an &lt;em&gt;inter-clan match&lt;/em&gt;: a day-long competition between PoT and &lt;em&gt;They Might Be Jedi&lt;/em&gt;, or TMBJ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/pot_v_tmbj1.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TMBJ was &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; JO clan. Everyone wanted to join them, and failing that (which was often), wanted to &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; them. They were kind, they were competitive, and they were &lt;em&gt;good at everything&lt;/em&gt;. Their most famous member went by the handle "ShroomDuck", and he was a singularly talented individual who was equal parts charming in person, deadly with a lightsaber, and wicked talented with JO modding tools, Photoshop, and web design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, a bit of a personal hero at the time. So, I submitted a challenge to TMBJ through him and on behalf of PoT to engage in a bit of well-mannered duels to the death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guess what? We &lt;em&gt;won&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/pot_v_tmbj2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/pot_v_tmbj3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TMBJ was stacked with talent, but somehow our own cohesiveness and teamwork--led by the inordinately talented likes of IronSlayer, Bill the Pony, Rob, John, Vader, and my master Kaleb--bested the JO juggernaut that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, mere weeks later, it all came crashing down: pretty much every one of those individuals announced that, for various reasons, they were leaving. We all knew it wasn't coincidence they were all leaving at the same time, but as I was still a Knight at the time and not privy to the discussions of the Council (to which Kaleb had been promoted since), I didn't have any details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly, we were a shell of ourselves: the 5-6 people who comprised a good 75% of the clan's activity were gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been told before--by coaches, by therapists, by parents, and by my wife--that I don't know how to quit. It's not always meant as a compliment, either; there are times when you really should cut your losses and walk away. I've learned how to do that more as I've gotten older, but suffice to say, my 19-year old self knew little to nothing of that skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I dug in. Over the next several months, I configured my own server to use for PoT (IronSlayer had run our local server until then), helped revamp the clan website, and advertised the clan whenever I was in-game. I sought out contacts I'd made in-game and brought them to our servers, increasing the baseline activity level that would attract more new blood. I relentlessly badgered the shattered Council with ideas, initiatives, and new recruits, insisting the new blood was there if I could just have permission to recruit them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fall 2004&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To their credit, after the initial shock wore off (and with some prodding on my part), the Council got down to work. I was quickly promoted to Jedi Master, and in short order, instated on the Council to fill the open seats left by the departures of the previous season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kaleb had a made a 1-year anniversary graphic back when he'd still been in the clan, so I followed suit as both a tribute to someone who'd taught me everything and also as a nudge to everyone else that I wasn't going anywhere, and neither should they.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/mag_year.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes--I even learned from Kaleb how to make custom player skins. I wasn't nearly as talented as he was, as I basically applied minor tweaks to a default built-in skin, but I was awfully proud of the "PoT" shoulder and thigh logos, the shamrocks on the calves, the lightning bolt across the chest, and the giant "69" emblazoned on the back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/mag_skin.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our ranks started swelling again. Too fast on occasion, even; we had to shut down recruitment at times in order to fully process applications and keep some semblance of order on our servers. Some of the best friends I made through PoT either appeared during this time, or the circumstances were such that an acquaintance deepened into a friendship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/rob_startup_screen.bmp"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rob&lt;/em&gt; was this way: a total goofball who was one of the best "gunners" (term for a JO player who preferred the point-and-shoot weapons to lightsabers) I'd ever encountered. To the casual observer, he and I appeared almost as opposites: I was all about structure and regimen; he just wanted to shoot at something and crack jokes. But when we were both promoted to the Council in the wake of the summer departures, against all odds we worked extraordinarily well together, our differing styles complementing each other and resulting in a friendship that endures to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/tahiri_snipe.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tahiri&lt;/em&gt; was another. He always kept a veil of secrecy around him, in no small part because his in-game avatar was female (his name "Tahiri" follows an Extended Universe character by the same name, who is female as well). But over AIM I learned he was a mere year older than I was, and as we worked closely to keep PoT alive in that summer and fall of 2004, we forged a relationship similar to the one I had with Rob, with the roles reversed: I kept him from being too rigid, and he kept me from being too slapdash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2005&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We continued recruiting, and I even managed to snare my literal Best Man, The Danimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/recruiting.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our renewed membership enabled us to engage in more inter-clan matches. We even managed to win a few of them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/uj.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Didn't do so well here--if TMBJ was #1, UJ was #2. Especially in saber duels, they were unstoppable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/njoc.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;NJOC was a much smaller clan, and through a rigorous practice regimen in the weeks leading up to the match, we actually ended up winning!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do want to mention something here, given &lt;a href="https://www.ckaleb.com/jedi-outcast/"&gt;Kaleb brought it up in his blog post&lt;/a&gt; some months ago: the Delta Order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/do_logo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the intervening months after the departures of mid-2004, it was clear--especially from the matches--that PoT was seriously lacking in gunning talent. Rob was still among the best I'd ever seen at any point in the game, but if he wasn't around, we really had nobody who could even come close to matching his play level. I was getting better, but again we really didn't have anyone else who was a pure gunner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delta Order was an attempt to remedy that: Rob and I would work together to groom younger members who demonstrated a knack for gunning to be the next Rob, essentially. It wasn't meant as a super-secret infiltrate-clans-from-within, CIA-like operation. Admittedly, we could have just as easily had a regular low-key practice session for anyone who wanted practice shooting things, but we thought this might make it more "official" and interesting to the younger players if they got a cool logo to go with their training efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It worked, somewhat: we trained Monkeh into one of the finest gunners in the clan (outside Rob, of course), and brought a lot of other players' skills more into parity with the general audience of the game. It was partially thanks to the Delta Order that we ended up winning the aforementioned match against NJOC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2006&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, we started organizing &lt;em&gt;intra-clan&lt;/em&gt; matches in the form of summer tournaments. These were a &lt;em&gt;blast&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We made entire brackets, and organized two separate double-elimination tournaments: one with best-of-three lightsaber duels, and the other with first-to-15-kills run-and-gun duels, appealing to the two flavors of JO player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The response was overwhelming, and was a huge boost to the clan. Though to this day, I'm stll not sure how &lt;em&gt;Rob&lt;/em&gt; of all people won the lightsaber competition. I think I just forgot to fill out the rest of the other bracket, but am pretty sure that was the year Rob won both competitions. WTF?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/bracket_saber.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/brackets_ffa.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in here, I colluded with a couple of my friends in PoT to stage an April 1 trick where we would all announce our immediate retirements from PoT. Tahiri wasn't pleased. Note the shift as he starts with sheer panic, then later after reading an "April Fool's!" follow-up post, shifts to relief with some good-old-fashioned ribbing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/demoted.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were having a lot of fun. I'm glossing over a lot--there was intra-clan drama, clashing of personalities, and the Council (myself included) made a lot of noob mistakes in handling them--but for all intents and purposes, the clan was humming along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2007&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For all practical purposes, this is where my role in PoT--after a solid four years--started waning. I was entering into the last year of my undergraduate studies at Georgia Tech and eyeing graduate school, was in a serious relationship that I was trying to convert from long-distance to short-distance, and JO was really starting to show its age: fewer new players were appearing, and more experienced hands were leaving. While we still technically had a full complement on the Council, only three of us--Rob, Tahiri, and myself--were still active in any meaningful capacity. Our Jedi Master ranks were pretty thin, and while we had many active Knights, our apprentice prospects were drying up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, it was time to start having difficult conversations: PoT, at least in its current form, wasn't going to last forever. And that end was looking to come sooner and sooner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the months that followed, a lot of options were thrown out, from continuing as we were to converting into a less formal "gaming community" (TMBJ had followed this route, having given up its JO-specific branding over a year prior) to disbanding entirely. None were particularly appealing; we didn't want PoT to simply disappear, but our leadership was aging; I knew I couldn't invest the kind of time and effort in revamping PoT that I'd put in back in mid-2004.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: this was one of the first lessons I learned in walking away. But, in classic "me", it wasn't because I came to some incredibly-wise decision to that effect, but because I was slapped in the face with the right decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, we made the decision to convert to a "gaming community" that had affiliations with multiple games, including JO, but also: Battlefront, StarCraft II, and even Left 4 Dead 2. We had a ranking system set up, and a representative "Senatorial" ambassadorship for each game. The clan seemed on board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then simmering egos exploded, and it became clear: we'd made the wrong decision. We quickly changed course, and decided it was time for the venerable PoT experiment to end. In our naive excitement to keep PoT alive, we ignored very real structural problems in the membership that had not been addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even now, I struggle for words to encapsulate everything the Power of Thee taught me, from making my own character skins; configuring and administering dedicated servers; hacking the shit out of Photoshop to make halfway-decent signature graphics; glitching JO in precisely the right way to grab the Flechette launcher through the floor; bunny-hopping; @@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@@-ing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even more important, and less amenable to precise wording, is the relationships I made and continue to learn from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kaleb&lt;/strong&gt;, who I don't speak to nearly often enough but really taught me everything I know, and even though we disagreed on some things in the end I still have the utmost respect for; he fights for who he loves, and that's a kind of interpersonal honor that is rare these days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Underwhelmed&lt;/strong&gt;, who selflessly hosted our forums for &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt;, and until I lost touch with him was a kind of unofficial mentor; I hope he's still rescuing tacos and giving them safe haven in his stomach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mormi Ganry&lt;/strong&gt;, a fellow tech guru whose commitment to always doing the right thing was above reproach; of course, this included that amazing instance when he managed to upload Linksys router firmware onto the open admin console for an unsecured D-Link router that belonged to a troll on our server...&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rob&lt;/strong&gt;, who despite (or because of?) his incessant in-game trash-talking, was one of the most honest and heartfelt individuals I'd ever met&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tahiri&lt;/strong&gt;, who was my conscience on more than one occasion, and my instructor on many others, and who helped me through relationship issues during my formative years&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jelle&lt;/strong&gt;, a fiercely loyal friend who I actually visited in Belgium during my 2007 study abroad, and who I also don't speak to nearly often enough, but who also kept me honest when we disagreed on multiple different fronts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Xixes&lt;/strong&gt;, who was the quintessential "PoTnah": always available to help anyone who might need it, always willing to lend a hand, always happy to jump into a clan match even if he knew he wasn't the right person for the job; he'd give it everything he had&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SwordFish&lt;/strong&gt;, a Canadian with a wicked hilarious sense of a humor and endless capacity for friendship who I have since sadly lost touch with&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monkeh&lt;/strong&gt;, an often-controversial individual who spoke almost exclusively in l33t-sp34k, who didn't care if he rubbed you the wrong way, and who turned into an exceptional gunner, but whose dedication to PoT and its leadership was never in question&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iain&lt;/strong&gt;, a quiet and polite member whose unassuming disposition masked a clever wit and incredibly sharp intellect, and especially technical talent, that led us to grant an overdue post-PoT promotion to Jedi Master&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...and many, many others: Vader, John, Bill the Pony, IronSlayer, Pablo, Jason, Anakin, Chrury, Deadclown, Rica, Secca, Snarf, Ragnarok, SeparateWays, and plenty others whom I'm forgetting or never knew that well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suffice to say, the clan--really, the people in it--were instrumental in making me into who I am now. I use a lot of the same leadership strategies in my day job, mentoring and instructing new students and training them into researchers; working through personnel conflicts and managing competing egos; and somehow making sure I have time to keep my own skills up to par with the playing field at large. In retrospect, it's amazing how such an otherwise run-of-the-mill FPS could have had such an outsized impact on me, but I'm eternally grateful for it, and hope only that I can continue to learn from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I find where Tahiri went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/jk2/tahiri_haha.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="gaming"></category><category term="jedi"></category><category term="star wars"></category><category term="first person shooter"></category><category term="fps"></category><category term="online communities"></category><category term="power of thee"></category></entry><entry><title>Resolutions for 2018</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2018/01/21/new-years-resolutions-2018/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-21T14:28:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-21T14:28:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2018-01-21:/blog/2018/01/21/new-years-resolutions-2018/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A solid three weeks late on the new year's resolutions, but still a marked improvement over last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...I didn't post resolutions last year...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been involved with a small faculty writing group since mid-December, with
the expressed goal of helping its participants develop and sustain regular
writing habits. Since …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A solid three weeks late on the new year's resolutions, but still a marked improvement over last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...I didn't post resolutions last year...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been involved with a small faculty writing group since mid-December, with
the expressed goal of helping its participants develop and sustain regular
writing habits. Since any new resolution's long-term success is pretty much
exclusively contingent on whether or not a habit is formed, I'm also trying
to eliminate some bad habits (since new habits are easier to form if they,
in effect, &lt;a href="https://jamesclear.com/three-steps-habit-change"&gt;take the place of the bad habits&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So without further adieu (and with a bit of inspiration from
&lt;a href="https://punkrockor.com/2018/01/02/punk-rock-ors-new-years-resolutions/"&gt;Dr. Albert&lt;/a&gt;),
here are my 2018 resolutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write and/or edit every single day (operationally I'm aiming for at least
30 minutes/day, 5 days/week, and go from there).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog more frequently. Despite starting this cool pelican blog back in 2015
for the &lt;em&gt;expressed&lt;/em&gt; purpose of basically doing what
&lt;a href="https://jakevdp.github.io/"&gt;Jake VanderPlas&lt;/a&gt; does on his blog--but with &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt;
research--I have yet to really bring that idea to fruition. That changes this year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make some progress on a few fun side projects!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few side projects that have languished over the last several
months (changing this blog's layout was one). I'd love to actually finish one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/snow_bunny.png" width="600" style="border-radius: 75%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="new year"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="side projects"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="habits"></category></entry><entry><title>New year, new blog layout</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2018/01/06/new-year-new-blog-layout/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-06T17:47:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-06T17:47:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2018-01-06:/blog/2018/01/06/new-year-new-blog-layout/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to put a fresh coat of paint on things for awhile around here,
especially since the old Flex template didn't have a really good way of supporting
embedded Jupyter notebooks without completely upending the CSS (love the theme
otherwise!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a page (or really, an …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Happy 2018!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been wanting to put a fresh coat of paint on things for awhile around here,
especially since the old Flex template didn't have a really good way of supporting
embedded Jupyter notebooks without completely upending the CSS (love the theme
otherwise!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking a page (or really, an entire layout) from &lt;a href="https://jakevdp.github.io/"&gt;Jake's blog&lt;/a&gt;,
I can now embed Jupyter notebooks without trashing the whole layout of the site.
There are some posts I've been wanting to make for awhile that will require a
considerable amount of code, so I'm excited to be able to dig into them now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll be following up soon with a lengthier resolutions post, but for now I just
wanted to say "I'm still alive" and roll out the new layout. Happy new year everyone!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="new year"></category><category term="blog"></category></entry><entry><title>Summer of Data Science 2017: Wrap-up</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/08/15/sods-2017-wrap-up/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-15T16:38:18-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-15T16:38:18-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2017-08-15:/blog/2017/08/15/sods-2017-wrap-up/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci/status/895856449687080960"&gt;Tweet of BecomingDataSci/895856449687080960&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Long Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that's stuck with me from my middle school obsession with the &lt;em&gt;Wing Commander&lt;/em&gt; books and video games was this quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;No battle plan survives contact with the enemy.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly as true as ever with the admittedly &lt;em&gt;extremely ambitious …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci/status/895856449687080960"&gt;Tweet of BecomingDataSci/895856449687080960&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Long Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that's stuck with me from my middle school obsession with the &lt;em&gt;Wing Commander&lt;/em&gt; books and video games was this quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;No battle plan survives contact with the enemy.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly as true as ever with the admittedly &lt;em&gt;extremely ambitious&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/05/31/summer-of-data-science-2017/"&gt;SoDS 2017 goals I laid out in my previous post&lt;/a&gt;. Still, they're worthwhile to go through and reflect over in preparation for the inevitable SoDS 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Teaching: 1360E improvements and 4360/6360 preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one I've done well with, and am continuing to work on (though &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SpectralFilter/status/896119490324201472"&gt;today's nuking of the AutoLab grading VM&lt;/a&gt; will set me back a bit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer was the second rendition of &lt;a href="https://eds-uga.github.io/csci1360e-su17/"&gt;CSCI 1360E, also taught as an online course&lt;/a&gt; just like last summer's (there is scheduled to be one more, next summer 2018. after that, who knows?). It started with over 20 students and ended with around 12--a pretty tough attrition rate--but still a vast improvement over last summer's 6/3. Ran into fewer autograder problems, the questions were more relevant and targeted to the lecture material, and the lectures themselves were smoother overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now deep in the process of building the fifth and final course I proposed back in Fall 2015 to fruition: &lt;a href="https://eds-uga.github.io/csci4360-fa17/"&gt;CSCI 4360/6360 Data Science II&lt;/a&gt;. I've planned out the lecture schedule for the semester, linked them up with the primary sources I'll be referencing, and even managed to snag all the necessary guest lecturers for the various trips I have to make. Of course, I'm lagging on the concrete lecture material, and as stated I nuked the VM that would host and autograde homework assignments, so this is still a mixed bag...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To update the enrollment numbers: currently 36 students registered (30 graduates, 6 undergraduates). I expect this to wobble considerably over the next week as classes officially begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(yes, you read that right: I proposed five brand-new courses my first fall semester; I've since taught three of them. a fourth was taught by another professor, since we couldn't figure out a way to clone me a &lt;em&gt;seventeenth&lt;/em&gt; time)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;: I'd give myself a B/B+, A- if you bring in the fact that, by the end of the summer, I was fully integrated with &lt;a href="https://airflow.incubator.apache.org/"&gt;Airflow&lt;/a&gt; for auto-posting lectures in 1360E.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Research: NSF CAREER proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was quite the process: an internal peer review with other colleagues at UGA, edits from my wife, and a night-before top-down rewrite reminiscent of when I scrapped my Ph.D. dissertation slides at 10pm the night before my defense. But I submitted something I was proud of, even if it doesn't stand a snowball's chance in hell of being funded. I stated before that I submitted for the feedback; even though I'd really, really love to have the grant funded, any feedback from the agency itself will be valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, that was my one grant-writing goal. I've managed to pick up a few others this summer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://aigrant.org/"&gt;AIGrant&lt;/a&gt;: Submitted this a few weeks ago. Really excited to work on the project I proposed; I hope the folks there are as excited as I am about it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2017/nsf17552/nsf17552.htm"&gt;NSF CRII&lt;/a&gt;: This is sort of a "CAREER Lite", since it's only 2 years and a &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; upper limit on the amount of funding you can request. But it's likewise geared toward young investigators like myself; however, I've applied the last two years and been rejected both times, and this is my last year of eligibility, so we'll see. I submitted this just this past week on Wednesday; fingers crossed!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ropensci.org/fellowships/"&gt;rOpenSci Fellowships&lt;/a&gt;: I have a completed draft that I've edited a few times with some feedback from the program officers. I'm still not ready to submit, but I think I have a compelling application for the Sept 1 deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-RM-17-006.html"&gt;NIH New Innovator&lt;/a&gt;: This one is a bit of a reach, considering it's a 10-page application due Sept 8, and it's pretty much the only one on this list I haven't had a chance to start on. Plus, I've received conflicting information from the informational webinar I attended and someone who applied last year and was rejected, so I'm wondering if I should let this one slide this year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sloan.org/fellowships/"&gt;Sloan Research Fellowships&lt;/a&gt;: Running my one-page application through the meatgrinder to get the best submission possible for the Sept 15 deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.simonsfoundation.org/mathematics-and-physical-science/simons-investigators/#mmls-investigators"&gt;Simons Investigators&lt;/a&gt;: the internal deadline for this is Sept 15, but assuming I get the nod (evidently no one else at UGA usually applies for this one?!), I'll be getting some feedback from previous Simons Investigators for some help in addressing what the foundation is really looking for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there's a grant I'm working on with Continuum Analytics' Matt Rocklin (yes, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mrocklin"&gt;that Matt Rocklin!&lt;/a&gt;), a smaller NIH grant on biosurveillance with the awesome folks at UGA Public Health, a potential biology grant to NSF with my Cellular Biology colleagues, and a mentored NIH K-award in neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all &lt;em&gt;this year&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, this is somewhat atypical. If I really do end up submitting to all these, I will have substantially increased my grantwriting output, exceeding that of my first two years &lt;em&gt;combined&lt;/em&gt;. I'm really, really hoping I land on something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;: A (upgrade to A+ if any actually get &lt;em&gt;funded&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal: Coursera's optimization course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;literally did not happen.&lt;/em&gt; I think I completed the first week of lectures and the practice assignment. Nothing after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely want to take another crack at this next summer, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;: F.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated at the beginning, a mixed bag. I've had some really great momentum with grantwriting this year, far better than any year so far. Teaching has been pretty productive as well (if not exhausting with all the brand-new courses), though the Coursera goal was a bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, that may have something to do with a completely inadvertent achievement: my running this year has come roaring back. My last five weeks have been particularly awesome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sods2017wrapup/strava.png" width="960"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two years after my wife and I moved to Athens (2015 and 2016) were both injury-plagued and just plain stressful. Consequently, my running took a hit: I haven't set a PR in any distance since 2014, I haven't run a full marathon since &lt;a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2015/06/19/race-report-the-hilliest-marathon-evar/"&gt;early 2015&lt;/a&gt;, and in general my mileage has taken a dive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sods2017wrapup/yearly.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But check out this year's trajectory! Nearly 800 miles, and we're only a week into August. That puts me on pace for right around 1,300 miles--a nice comfy middle ground between the monster year that was 2014 and each of the subsequent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also started noticing that I'm actually getting faster, which is something I likewise haven't experienced with my running for a couple years. Where I've typically felt as though I'm just on "cruise control", this increased mileage has also seen my finishing times go down without any conscious decision on my part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which led me--perhaps in a half-crazed moment of weakness--to put the following goals on the Athens Fleet Feet board several weeks ago at their four-year anniversary celebration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sods2017wrapup/goals.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running is my release. Without it, nothing else I do is going to be very good. When running is going well, other things are going well, and vice versa. So here's hoping I've set myself on a good track!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="data science"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="computer vision"></category><category term="imaging"></category><category term="machine learning"></category><category term="deep learning"></category><category term="nvidia"></category><category term="gpu"></category><category term="online courses"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="cat detector"></category><category term="generative adversarial networks"></category><category term="latent subspace"></category><category term="manifolds"></category><category term="bioimaging"></category><category term="grant writing"></category><category term="running"></category></entry><entry><title>Summer of Data Science 2017</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/05/31/summer-of-data-science-2017/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-31T23:03:42-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-31T23:03:42-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2017-05-31:/blog/2017/05/31/summer-of-data-science-2017/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/images/carpelibrum.png"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, while I was still in Portland, OR enjoying the last few days of &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/"&gt;PyCon 2017&lt;/a&gt;, Renee (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci"&gt;@BecomingDataSci&lt;/a&gt;) mentioned on Twitter that she might bring back the "Summer of Data Science" she kicked off last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: use the summer as an opportunity to learn and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/images/carpelibrum.png"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, while I was still in Portland, OR enjoying the last few days of &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/"&gt;PyCon 2017&lt;/a&gt;, Renee (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci"&gt;@BecomingDataSci&lt;/a&gt;) mentioned on Twitter that she might bring back the "Summer of Data Science" she kicked off last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: use the summer as an opportunity to learn and/or accomplish something data science-related in a goal-oriented, data-driven way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;@BecomingDataSci/status/869608575978676226&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a tenure-track professor still yet to endure the 3rd-year review, pretty much everything data science related revolves around furthering my eventual tenure dossier. But the summers are still considerably more flexible for me to accomplish some of these goals than the fall or spring (I love teaching, but it's all-consuming). I also have more than just myself--networks of collaborators and research assistants who can help me with these goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So without further adieu, I'd like to put forth my own Summer of Data Science, 2017 Edition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Teaching: 1360E improvements and 4360/6360 preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm teaching an online course this summer, starting June 5 and continuing through the end of July: &lt;a href="https://eds-uga.github.io/csci1360e-su17/"&gt;CSCI 1360E Foundations of Informatics and Analytics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, more colloquially, I just call it "introduction to data science."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's one of the five courses I proposed in my first year (a story for another time, believe me...) and taught for the first time last summer, and in-person last fall. I'm teaching it again this summer and hoping to make some of the standard improvements, such as sprucing up slides and fixing autograder bugs from previous incarnations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More pressing is CSCI 4360/6360 Data Science II, which has yet to have its own website. This course has &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been taught, but is slated for Fall 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did I mention there are already over 40 students registered, undergraduate and graduate combined?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is supposed to be the "corner cases" of data science: lesser-used and/or more powerful analysis methods that aren't necessarily the first tools or techniques you reach for in a given situation. This will include, but certainly not be limited to, concepts like randomized algorithms, semi-supervised learning, and backpropagation; techniques like out-of-core processing, distributed computing, and functional programming; tools like &lt;a href="https://julialang.org/"&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://numba.pydata.org/"&gt;numba&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://dask.pydata.org/en/latest/"&gt;dask&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you ask: No. I'm &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; covering Spark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the conceptual framework is in place, but practically none of the architectural logistics have been established. So this will take up virtually all of my time for the remainder of the summer, once the following item is completed...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Research: NSF CAREER proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of this goal is it has a hard end date: &lt;strong&gt;July 19&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage is that the &lt;a href="https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2017/nsf17537/nsf17537.htm"&gt;NSF CAREER&lt;/a&gt; is the pinnacle of NSF early-career investigator awards. Its importance cannot be overstated; its &lt;em&gt;je ne sais quoi&lt;/em&gt; is on display in the faces of new investigators when you mention it around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've connected with my university's grant proposal officers, and am participating in a peer review process that involves two rounds of review: first with fellow CAREER submitees (as in, we exchange each other's current drafts!), and second with the university grant officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An investigator can only make three submission attempts for the CAREER. The CAREER is only open for submissions once per year. If chosen, the investigator must still be un-tenured at time of award. These conditions place brutal limits on how long you can wait to start making submissions, and I already skipped submitting my first two years. Still, I have no illusions about the uphill battle I have, so my goal this first time around is simply to &lt;strong&gt;acquire feedback&lt;/strong&gt;: from my peers, from my grants officers, and from the NSF reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal: Coursera's optimization course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I signed up to take Coursera's &lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/discrete-optimization/home/welcome"&gt;Discrete Optimization course&lt;/a&gt; out of the University of Melbourne, taught by none other than &lt;a href="https://pascalvanhentenryck.engin.umich.edu/"&gt;Professor Pascal Van Hentenryck&lt;/a&gt; at Michigan and &lt;a href="http://www.coffr.in/"&gt;Dr. Carleton Coffrin&lt;/a&gt;, currently at Los Alamos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimization is pretty much the backbone of modern machine learning, and yet I have almost no formal training in it--beyond incidentally covering it in various machine learning and statistics courses as part of some broader topic in which it's used. Oddly, the most rigorous instruction I received as a graduate student in optimization was a &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/site/cellandsystemsmodeling/"&gt;Cell &amp;amp; Systems Modeling course&lt;/a&gt; where we used various optimization techniques to find parameter values for population models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially in conjunction with what I hope to teach in CSCI 4360 in the fall, this would be invaluable both professionally as well as personally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="data science"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="computer vision"></category><category term="imaging"></category><category term="machine learning"></category><category term="deep learning"></category><category term="nvidia"></category><category term="gpu"></category><category term="online courses"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="cat detector"></category><category term="generative adversarial networks"></category><category term="latent subspace"></category><category term="manifolds"></category><category term="bioimaging"></category></entry><entry><title>So, you want to conduct research with me?</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/03/16/so-you-want-to-conduct-research-with-me/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-03-16T15:59:21-04:00</published><updated>2017-03-16T15:59:21-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2017-03-16:/blog/2017/03/16/so-you-want-to-conduct-research-with-me/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/images/joker_play_a_game.jpg"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deviation #1&lt;/em&gt;: This is wholly separate from the &lt;a href="http://shouldigetaphd.com/"&gt;"should I get a Ph.D."&lt;/a&gt; question. For that I would recommend one of numerous guides that ask all the right questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deviation #2&lt;/em&gt;: This is also wholly separate from how to &lt;em&gt;succeed&lt;/em&gt; in a Ph.D. program, though there is some …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/images/joker_play_a_game.jpg"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deviation #1&lt;/em&gt;: This is wholly separate from the &lt;a href="http://shouldigetaphd.com/"&gt;"should I get a Ph.D."&lt;/a&gt; question. For that I would recommend one of numerous guides that ask all the right questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deviation #2&lt;/em&gt;: This is also wholly separate from how to &lt;em&gt;succeed&lt;/em&gt; in a Ph.D. program, though there is some overlap. In general, there are some key items to consider and habits to build as you work your way through a Ph.D., and for those questions I highly recommend &lt;a href="http://karpathy.github.io/2016/09/07/phd/"&gt;Andrej Karpathy's excellent survival guide to a Ph.D.&lt;/a&gt;, some of which may be mirrored here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, the specific question I'm addressing here is &lt;strong&gt;how to succeed in graduate research as one of my students.&lt;/strong&gt; In order of somewhat-importance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1: Familiarize yourself with my research interests.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a no-brainer, but you'd be surprised how many emails I get from individuals expressing profound interest in working with me, only to see they have &lt;strong&gt;i)&lt;/strong&gt; no experience whatsoever in any of my interests (which isn't necessarily a deal-breaker!), and &lt;strong&gt;ii)&lt;/strong&gt; don't appear to know what I work on (which &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a deal-breaker). If you work with me, you're going to do something at the intersection of bioimaging + distributed computing + biosurveillance; something that involves computer vision and machine learning in a public health setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=4EjRiycAAAAJ"&gt;Google Scholar&lt;/a&gt; record, my group's &lt;a href="https://github.com/quinngroup"&gt;GitHub repositories&lt;/a&gt;, and my &lt;a href="https://quinngroup.github.io/"&gt;lab website&lt;/a&gt; to get at least a basic idea of the sort of work I do, and to jog your thinking along the lines of what you might be able to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2: Take into consideration the following expectations.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work hard, play hard, and be able to talk about both:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect my students to develop into excellent scientific communicators. In practice, this means I want you to be able to talk about your work to experts in the same field, experts in different fields, and even non-scientists. I want you to get comfortable giving talks and writing papers. If English isn't your first language, that's ok! Just be aware this expectation may take more time than you think.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect my students to participate in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_science"&gt;Open Science&lt;/a&gt;. In practice, this means I want you to publish all the code you write in &lt;a href="https://github.com/quinngroup"&gt;public repositories&lt;/a&gt;, mirror all your papers on &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/"&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt;, participate in and contribute to open source projects, and maybe even contribute to a blog. Research is only interesting when you can pick through the code, explore the data, and regenerate the results. Know or learn how to use &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;scientific notebooks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/"&gt;version control&lt;/a&gt;, wikis, and even &lt;a href="https://www.docker.com/"&gt;containers&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect my students to demonstrate a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/sama/status/792823320441786368"&gt;promising slope of accomplishment&lt;/a&gt;. Put simply, &lt;a href="https://josh.works/blog/2015/6/25/a-little-bit-of-slope-makes-up-for-a-lot-of-y-intercept"&gt;I recruit for potential (slope), not experience (y-intercept)&lt;/a&gt;. You don't have to know everything about machine learning, statistics, and linear algebra, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; be an expert programming in Python just to be able to work with me. However, I do expect that you will be able to pick up these skills very quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I expect my students to take ownership of their projects, pushing the envelope of what is known and beyond what even I would suggest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3: Prepare yourself to be a self-sufficient researcher.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;strong&gt;does NOT mean&lt;/strong&gt; I expect you to do everything! The whole point of being a student is that you have a mentor, a supervisor who is (in theory) more experienced than you, from whom you can learn. It is indeed my job to guide you and teach you what I know, and I will most certainly do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;strong&gt;DOES mean&lt;/strong&gt; that, by the end of your time here, I want you to be the expert on your project! You should take the project and run with it, rather than wait for me to tell you what to do next. Build your intuition about the problem through "moving fast and breaking things," to use the tech startup parlance. Ask forgiveness rather than permission. Insert witticism here that basically says KEEP TRYING THINGS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even as you start your project, you may come across roadblocks that I don't have an answer for. That's how research works: we're pushing the limits of our collective knowledge! I may have some intuition from previous problems, and I'll certainly share that, but asking me "What do I do next?" is going to frustrate both of us very, very quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another example: &lt;a href="http://simplystatistics.org/2017/03/16/evo-ds-class/"&gt;the levels of data science classes&lt;/a&gt;. You don't have to be anywhere above Level 2 when you arrive (maybe you're still working your way through Level 1!), but I expect you to work &lt;strong&gt;through Level 7 by the time you leave.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;If you've made it this far, and are still interested...&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...then I encourage you to reach out to me and express your interest! I have just a few final pieces of advice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DavidBindel/status/1054859324143616000"&gt;read this brief Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mickeykats/status/1074874785795112960"&gt;this brief Twitter thread as well&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, &lt;strong&gt;do NOT&lt;/strong&gt; send me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a form email with a 10-page summary of your accomplishments (as I said, I don't hire for y-intercept, I hire for slope)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an email with misspellings or grammatical errors (recall that I emphasize good scientific communication skills)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a message that starts with "Dear Ms Quinn" (first, I'm a doctor; second, I'm a guy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href="https://magsol.github.io/pages/contact.html"&gt;write an email&lt;/a&gt; that's 3-5 sentences at most, &lt;strong&gt;with a specific mention of the work you find interesting and want to pursue further&lt;/strong&gt;. For extra credit, mention some kind of improvement or extension to the work that you came up with on your own. This tells me a lot of things all at once, most important of which is that you're serious about wanting to work with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because if you can handle graduate school...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/images/grad-school.jpg"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...I really do believe you can handle anything.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="professional"></category><category term="phd"></category><category term="graduate school"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="mentoring"></category><category term="computer science"></category><category term="graduate student"></category></entry><entry><title>Game-ify Your Raspberry Pi</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/01/06/gameify-your-raspberry-pi/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-06T18:47:37-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-06T18:47:37-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2017-01-06:/blog/2017/01/06/gameify-your-raspberry-pi/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rpi/raspberrypi3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project over the 2016 holiday season was to take the Raspberry Pi 3 I've had sitting around the house idling for the previous nine months and turn it into a &lt;a href="https://retropie.org.uk/"&gt;RetroPie-ified gaming emulator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RetroPie is a phenomenal bit of software that combines the work of several projects into a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rpi/raspberrypi3.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project over the 2016 holiday season was to take the Raspberry Pi 3 I've had sitting around the house idling for the previous nine months and turn it into a &lt;a href="https://retropie.org.uk/"&gt;RetroPie-ified gaming emulator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RetroPie is a phenomenal bit of software that combines the work of several projects into a single package that was primarily designed to be deployed on Raspberry Pis, but which can also be set up on a regular ol' PC. If you're using a Raspberry Pi, it's built on top of the &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/downloads/raspbian/"&gt;Raspbian OS&lt;/a&gt;, so all the commands familiar to you will still be available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have to say up front: the folks with RetroPie have done an &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt; job. The documentation was excellent, and while I'll walk through the installation and configuration here, with only one notable exception everything went exactly as prescribed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;RetroPie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assuming you have all the &lt;a href="https://retropie.org.uk/documentation/building-your-own-retropie-machine/"&gt;needed hardware&lt;/a&gt;, installing the RetroPie OS on your Pi is &lt;a href="https://github.com/RetroPie/RetroPie-Setup/wiki/First-Installation"&gt;pretty straightforward&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use some sort of imaging software to write the RetroPie image to an SD card (I used &lt;a href="http://www.tweaking4all.com/hardware/raspberry-pi/macosx-apple-pi-baker/"&gt;ApplePi Baker&lt;/a&gt; without any problems, but you could also just use the &lt;code&gt;dd&lt;/code&gt; command in the Terminal, which directly moves bytes from one place to another).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Insert the SD card into your Pi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boot! I had a few false-starts that were the result of the SD card not being fully inserted, so nothing came up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If all goes well, you should see the wonderful Raspbian logo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rpi/raspberry-pi-logo.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configuring RetroPie&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing you'll need to do when RetroPie boots is to configure whatever controller you're going to use. I went out and purchased some standard-issue &lt;a href="http://gaming.logitech.com/en-us/product/f310-gamepad"&gt;Logitech USB gamepads&lt;/a&gt; and they seem to be functioning very well. You can also use your keyboard if you want for this, but it pretty much has to be something that can be connected via USB directly to the Pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few pointers in this step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To skip a particular button configuration, just &lt;strong&gt;press and hold any button for a second&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you make a mistake in configuring a button, you have to get all the way to the bottom before you can scroll back up and fix it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It took me 5-6 tries to get this completely right. Just go back and do it again if you mess something up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;EmulationStation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you successfully configure a gamepad, you'll be taken to the main landing page: EmulationStation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rpi/emulationstation.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where are teh gamez0rz?!1&lt;/em&gt;, you might be saying. Well, since ROMs are a legal gray area, you're kinda on your own there. BUT! We have something else we need to do first anyway: set up a network configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Network Configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a Raspberry Pi 2 or earlier, your network choices are limited to an ethernet connection. With the advent of Raspberry Pi 3s, suddenly wifi is an option! Turns out, I have a 3, and it is this wifi that caused me a couple hours' grief until I figured out what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to the wifi configuration in EmulationStation. You'll be taken to a network selection screen--protip, the Pi 3 &lt;strong&gt;cannot&lt;/strong&gt; connect to 5GHz networks--where you can select your wifi network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll then need to type in the wifi password. Provided you get it right, that should be it! You're all set to go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself entering your password again...and again...and again...and again...and can't figure out why it's failing, read on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Keyboard Layout&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For whatever reason, my keyboard was misconfigured--the layout was set to English (U.K.), resulting in some special characters being remapped. However, since the Raspbian password interface echoes stars &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; back, I had no idea I was typing a completely wrong password until I fired up a command prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, once you diagnose this issue, it's fairly easy to fix. Raspbian has a &lt;a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/forums/viewtopic.php?f=28&amp;amp;t=80127"&gt;utility built-in for changing your keyboard layout&lt;/a&gt;. You just have to navigate in EmulationStation to the option that gives you a command prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case, once I had a working network connection, I just used SSH to perform any other operations on the Pi (e.g. uploading new games). The default username/password for RetroPie is &lt;code&gt;pi/raspberry&lt;/code&gt;, which I suggest you change either from the EmulationStation main menu, or after your first SSH login.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Moonlight on Raspberry Pi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should have a working RetroPie at this point, so that's cool!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as awesome as the Pis are, they're not exactly brimming with horsepower. As such, if you try running N64 or PS2 emulators, you may find as I did that anything requiring 3D shaders gets &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; jittery, to the point of unplayable. RetroPie has &lt;a href="https://github.com/RetroPie/RetroPie-Setup/wiki"&gt;detailed configuration options for every emulator&lt;/a&gt; to help you get the absolute most out of your Pi, but there are some things a tiny CPU with an embedded stock GPU just can't do, and one of those is render 3D shaders the way they were meant to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what? Give up? &lt;em&gt;Nay!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rpi/moonlight.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/irtimmer/moonlight-embedded/wiki"&gt;Moonlight Embedded&lt;/a&gt; is the open source version of NVIDIA's GameStream as used by the NVIDIA Shield. Basically, it's a way of streaming the output of an NVIDIA GPU to another input, like a TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, we're basically turning our Pi into a glorified Chromecast--it'll take the output from a dedicated GPU and stream it directly to the TV it's connected to. Yes, this means you're not actually playing games &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; the Raspberry Pi--you're playing them on whatever computer has the GPU in it (oh and it has to be an NVIDIA GPU, GTX 650 or higher)--but all Moonlight requires is Raspbian, which is what RetroPie is built on!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href="https://blog.jhot.me/guide-install-moonlight-on-raspbian-retropie-9d1318b8ddf8#.etf7g4bo6"&gt;this installation guide&lt;/a&gt; perfect (make sure you download the latest versions of everything!), with the lone exception that, just before downloading and installing Moonlight itself, I also needed to install one more library:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;sudo apt-get install libenet-dev&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Include that with the other libraries installed just before Moonlight, and everything else should just work. The rest of the instructions take you through configuring the gamepads so they correctly send their input back to the GPU (so, y'know, you don't have to sit at your computer while staring at your TV).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Happy Fun Times!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, lots of happy fun times. But also &lt;a href="http://docs.happyfuntimes.net/docs/introduction.html"&gt;HappyFunTimes&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're really into the party games, installing this gaming server may be the best thing ever. It's a brilliant setup: gamepads are HTML5 canvases that run on smartphones, essentially mimicking controllers so everyone with a smartphone can play. The games range from stupidly simple to shockingly sophisticated. I may post configuration for that later, but I figure: if you're building the Ultimate Gaming Pi, why not include that, too?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, I give you the results at our house:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/rpi/zelda.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="pi"></category><category term="raspberry pi"></category><category term="retropie"></category><category term="retro"></category><category term="gaming"></category><category term="video games"></category><category term="nvidia"></category><category term="shield"></category><category term="steam"></category></entry><entry><title>Open Science in Big Data (OSBD) Workshop</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2016/09/26/osbd2016-workshop/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-26T09:10:19-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-26T09:10:19-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2016-09-26:/blog/2016/09/26/osbd2016-workshop/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/washingtondc.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in May of this year, some of the other computer science professors and I put together a proposal for a workshop. The workshop would be in conjunction with the December 2016 &lt;a href="http://cci.drexel.edu/bigdata/bigdata2016/"&gt;IEEE BigData Conference&lt;/a&gt;, and would focus specifically on the intersection of big data and open science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/washingtondc.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in May of this year, some of the other computer science professors and I put together a proposal for a workshop. The workshop would be in conjunction with the December 2016 &lt;a href="http://cci.drexel.edu/bigdata/bigdata2016/"&gt;IEEE BigData Conference&lt;/a&gt;, and would focus specifically on the intersection of big data and open science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June, we got the good news: it was accepted!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is "Open Science"?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been interested in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_science"&gt;open science&lt;/a&gt; since I started graduate school. I'd been using Apache projects since college, learning how to set up and configure my own LAMP stack (yes, I'll admit I dabbled in PHP for a few years, but I'm clean now!), but had never really contributed to an open source project until the 2010 Google Summer of Code. During that time, I worked on adding spectral clustering the &lt;a href="http://mahout.apache.org"&gt;Apache Mahout&lt;/a&gt; library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While open source is great and wonderful, this is just one component of Open Science. It's another reason I'm incredibly excited about the "container revolution": Docker and its ilk. This concept makes entire pipelines perfectly reproducible, to the point where it's now possible for entire scientific projects to be replicated with a single command: from running the analysis, to building the figures, to assembling the final PDF file (which, by the way, can be uploaded to &lt;a href="http://arxiv.org"&gt;arXiv&lt;/a&gt; for everyone to read!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These other aspects--open sourcing data, reproducibility scripts, and entire pipelines--are veritable educational and research gold mines, but are arguably much more difficult than simply dumping some code on GitHub. &lt;strong&gt;These difficulties are only exacerbated in the realm of "big data".&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are the goals of the workshop?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals of the workshop are threefold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;: we aim to &lt;em&gt;identify some of the biggest challenges&lt;/em&gt; in democratizing big data analytics. Open Science is a critical component of both educational pedagogy and scientific research. With the increasing relevance of big data analytics, making these tools and resources available to the next generation of scientists and big data practitioners is crucial. Unfortunately, this is also extremely challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second&lt;/strong&gt;: we aim to bring together big data practitioners from multiple backgrounds to &lt;em&gt;discuss and establish the current state of affairs&lt;/em&gt; with respect to reproducibility in big data analytics and machine learning. Priorities change and constraints differ between researchers and developers in academia versus industry versus government; nonetheless, open science and big data are important to practitioners in each of these areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Third&lt;/strong&gt;: we aim to &lt;em&gt;examine and propose possible routes forward&lt;/em&gt; to advance the continued integration of open science in big data analytics, putting tools, techniques, data, and documentation in the hands of researchers, students, and other big data practitioners. We will identify emerging trends in terms of open science best practices, and how these can be incorporated into current big data endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;What kinds of proceedings is the workshop accepting?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope to have two tracks: a full research paper session, and a student (short) paper session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Papers submitted to the OSBD workshop should, at the very minimum, have a significant Open Science component. This can take several forms, including but not limited to any combination of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses free and open source packages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Openly available online, e.g. GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scripts are available to reproduce figures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data are openly available e.g. dat, datahub.io&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are welcoming of original research into big data analytics, so long as there is an open science component.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, in the spirit of Open Science and reproducibility, we strongly encourage our presenters to incorporate live code demos, data walkthroughs, or some other hands-on activity into their talks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;When is the submission deadline?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The deadline for workshop paper submissions is &lt;strong&gt;Sunday, October 25, 2016&lt;/strong&gt;. This provides a 2-week buffer zone between the notification deadline of the main IEEE BigData conference, in case you want to repackage your conference submission for the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Where can one find more information about OSBD?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a website: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://osbd.github.io/" target="_blank"&gt;https://osbd.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The website contains information about the topics around the workshop, the invited speakers who will be attending (keynote and panelists), the important dates around the workshop, and the instructions for formatting and submitting your paper to the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are very excited about this workshop, and encourage you to submit! We look forward to seeing you in December!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/openscience.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cs.uga.edu/~squinn"&gt;Shannon Quinn&lt;/a&gt;, Co-chair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cs.uga.edu/~jam/"&gt;John Miller&lt;/a&gt;, Co-chair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cs.uga.edu/~suchi/"&gt;Suchi Bhandarkar&lt;/a&gt;, Co-chair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://cs.uga.edu/~yihong/"&gt;Yi Hong&lt;/a&gt;, Co-chair&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="professional"></category><category term="workshop"></category><category term="big data"></category><category term="ieee"></category><category term="open science"></category></entry><entry><title>A twitterbot for posting weekly running stats</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2016/05/16/a-twitterbot-for-posting-weekly-running-stats/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-05-16T15:09:59-04:00</published><updated>2016-05-16T15:09:59-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2016-05-16:/blog/2016/05/16/a-twitterbot-for-posting-weekly-running-stats/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/stravatwitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We runners (we're a crazy bunch), for the most part, like our stats. How many miles do you log each week? Each month? How are your average race paces trending? Are your long runs both feeling good and getting faster?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, we're a little obsessed with our numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's no …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/stravatwitter.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We runners (we're a crazy bunch), for the most part, like our stats. How many miles do you log each week? Each month? How are your average race paces trending? Are your long runs both feeling good and getting faster?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, we're a little obsessed with our numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's no surprise, then, that web services have popped up to help us aggregate some of these numbers. One of the most obvious is &lt;a href="https://connect.garmin.com/"&gt;Garmin Connect&lt;/a&gt;, home for pretty much anyone who uses the Garmin GPS watches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another that I've used before is &lt;a href="http://www.dailymile.com/"&gt;Daily Mile&lt;/a&gt;. However in recent months I've become frustrated enough with the site to leave entirely. By all accounts, no part of the site has been updated in &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2013/05/20/my-ideal-running-statistics-site/"&gt;other alternatives&lt;/a&gt; are simply much more pleasant to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there was one crucial feature of Daily Mile I really liked: connecting it to your Twitter account to post weekly summaries of your recorded workouts. I liked it so much, in fact, I created a small web service to do the same thing, &lt;a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2014/06/11/open-beta-for-twathletic/"&gt;but for monthly summaries&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://wherearethepancakes.files.wordpress.com/2014/06/example.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously that service no longer exists, but ever since I've been wanting to get something similar up and running again. Especially now that I don't even have weekly summaries anymore--just couldn't stomach Daily Mile any longer--I wanted to take the opportunity (and the shiny new blog) to go through a step-by-step procedure of creating your own Twitter / Strava app for posting weekly summaries on Twitter of your running mileage!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preliminaries&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things you'll need before we get started:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python 3.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.tweepy.org/"&gt;tweepy&lt;/a&gt; (for interfacing with Twitter)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://pythonhosted.org/stravalib/"&gt;stravalib&lt;/a&gt; (for interfacing with Strava)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/magsol/pybot"&gt;pybot&lt;/a&gt; (shameless plug, but it will help)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Twitter and Strava use OAuth as their method of app authentication. These libraries just make it easier to interact with the services; they abstract a lot of the details of authentication and communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in case you're interested: &lt;a href="https://dev.twitter.com/overview/documentation"&gt;Twitter's docs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://strava.github.io/api/"&gt;Strava's docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 1: Create a Strava app&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to your &lt;a href="https://www.strava.com/settings/api"&gt;user settings&lt;/a&gt; and create an app that can interface with your account. Important pieces of information you'll need later: &lt;strong&gt;Client ID&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Client Secret&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Your access token&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can test if it works. Fire up an IPython terminal, get your &lt;code&gt;access_token&lt;/code&gt;, and run the following code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;stravalib&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Client&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;access_token&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;access_token&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_athlete&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should see something along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[]:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Athlete&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1234567&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;firstname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Firstname&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;lastname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sa"&gt;b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Lastname&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 2: Retrieve last week's data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole point is to get weekly mileage reports. Thankfully, the &lt;code&gt;get_activities&lt;/code&gt; method in stravalib has an &lt;code&gt;after&lt;/code&gt; optional parameter we can use to precisely tune what time interval we want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, though, we need to create a timestamp that represents the 1-week time frame. If we assume this will only be executed on the day we want the summary--say, every Monday--then we need to tally up all the runs from the day before all the way back to the previous Monday, inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;timedelta&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;weeks&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;after&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;month&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;day&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;activities&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_activities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;after&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;after&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming we run this chunk of code on a Monday, it should give us every Strava activity from the previous Monday up to the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, we're not done yet. This includes everything--not just our runs, but any other activities that we recorded; yoga, weights, elliptical, and so on. We need to filter these out. We also need to filter out the edge case of any activities that have been recorded &lt;em&gt;today&lt;/em&gt;, since we don't want to include these in a report of &lt;em&gt;last&lt;/em&gt; week's activities!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activities&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Run&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; \
    &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;start_date_local&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;day&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;day&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, let's pause and discuss what's happening here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the most obvious: we're looping through the &lt;code&gt;activities&lt;/code&gt; generator we obtained in the last line of the previous step. Second, the &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; statement at the end filters out any activities that aren't a run. Finally, the &lt;code&gt;activity.id&lt;/code&gt; part out front says, we're building a list of the unique IDs that identify each activity. The last part is our timeframe edge case: if we recorded an activity today, even a running activity, don't include it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are we only holding onto the IDs? It has to do with detail. Strava maintains a hierarchy of details available to users that vary with authentication, connection, etc. Simply put, when we request a list of activities, &lt;a href="http://strava.github.io/api/v3/activities/#get-activities"&gt;the default detail level is 2, which is "summary" level&lt;/a&gt;. However, some of the metrics we need--calories in particular!--require level 3, or "detailed". To get this level of detail, we need to query for individual activities...one at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence, a list of activity IDs! Now we can loop through the IDs, requesting details on each run and tabulating up the mileage and calories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;stravalib&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;unithelper&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="n"&gt;mileage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;calories&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity_id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;activity_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# This is annoying; all the default distances are in meters! Luckily,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# stravalib comes with a nice unit helper utility to do the conversion.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;unithelper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;miles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mileage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;num&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Rounds to 2 sig figs.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;calories&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;calories&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it! In those two variables--&lt;code&gt;mileage&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;calories&lt;/code&gt;--you have all the data you need to summarize your running workouts for the last week. Now we just need to post this information on Twitter!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 3: Create a PyBot&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, time for a shameless plug: yes, I'm the &lt;a href="https://github.com/magsol/pybot"&gt;pybot&lt;/a&gt; author. It's still highly experimental, and largely uncompleted, but for our purposes it will suffice nicely as a barebones framework to interact with Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clone the repo and follow the setup script to create a Twitter app and connect it to your account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;git clone https://github.com/magsol/pybot.git&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;cd pybot&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="err"&gt;sbin/create_pybot.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That will walk you through the instructions for creating an app, generating OAuth credentials, and stubbing out your first pybot. Feel free to give it whatever name you'd like; for the purposes of this tutorial, I'll assume we've named it &lt;code&gt;artbot&lt;/code&gt; (don't ask). Congratulations! You've created a twitter bot!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 4: Customize the bot's behavior&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our bot is pretty simple: every Monday at some specified time, it will wake up, read all the prior week's running activities, and post the summary before going back to sleep for another week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It won't be prompted by anything other than time. So the specific action override we're looking for in PyBot parlance is &lt;code&gt;on_tweet&lt;/code&gt;, and the interval we'll use is &lt;code&gt;tweet_interval&lt;/code&gt;. The latter is easy enough--a full week between tweets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;tweet_interval&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;60&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;60&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;24&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we go any further: does anyone see anything wrong with the above code snippet?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll give you a hint: imagine you started this bot on a Tuesday, instead of a Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep, there it is. This interval we've defined is exactly 1 week, but it &lt;em&gt;doesn't account for when we actually START the bot&lt;/em&gt;. We need this to be a little more intelligent. If you want the posting to happen weekly every Monday, it shouldn't matter when you actually start running the bot, right? It should be smart enough to figure out when it needs to post for the first time, &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; post weekly thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A neat component of PyBot is that, in addition to giving hard time frames, you can also specify functions to compute the interval on-the-fly, subject to some other constraints that are dynamic (like on what day of the week you happen to fire up the bot).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make things easy on us, we'll use the &lt;code&gt;datetime&lt;/code&gt; convention in the Python documentation for &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3.5/library/datetime.html#datetime.datetime.weekday"&gt;identifying individual days of the week&lt;/a&gt;. This tutorial assumes Mondays (which corresponds to &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;), but you can use whatever value you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to store this as a configuration parameter in the bot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Put this somewhere in the bot_init() method&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;update_day&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Corresponds to Monday.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, we need a &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt; to compute the interval between updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Put this somewhere in the bot_init() method&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;tweet_interval&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_compute_interval&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We've referenced an internal method we're calling &lt;code&gt;_compute_interval&lt;/code&gt;, as of yet undefined. Let's go ahead and define it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Put this somewhere in the bot class declaration&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;_compute_interval&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;interval&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;60&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;60&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;24&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# The default interval; we&amp;#39;ll start here&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Are we on the right day of the week?&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;weekday&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;config&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;update_day&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;interval&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Nothing to do! Yay!&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# If we get to this point, it means the index of the current day--&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# as in, right when the code gets HERE--doesn&amp;#39;t match the index of the&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# day we&amp;#39;ve said we want to perform this update. So we need to do a&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# little bit of work to compute that date.&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# This is a hack, so the index of the CURRENT day will always be&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# smaller than the index of the TARGET day.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;7&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Essentially, all we&amp;#39;ve done is replace the 7 above with whatever&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# it needs to be in order to get us to our target day.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;target&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;24&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;60&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;60&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that our interval is in place, we'll need to override the &lt;code&gt;on_tweet&lt;/code&gt; action to do what we want whenever it's called (which will be once each week on the day we've specified!). Remember, this method is called once we've hit our interval. So this is where it all comes together!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;on_tweet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# First, pull in the stats from Strava.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;now&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;timedelta&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;weeks&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;after&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;year&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;month&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last_week&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;day&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;activities&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_activities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;after&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;after&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Second, filter by activity type and time frame.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activities&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;#39;Run&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;start_date_local&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;day&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;current&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;day&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Third, tabulate up the stats for mileage and calories.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;mileage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;calories&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mf"&gt;0.0&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity_id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;client&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;get_activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;activity_id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;unithelper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;miles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;mileage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;distance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;num&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Rounds to 2 sig figs.&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;calories&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;activity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;calories&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# Finally, use the stats to craft a tweet. This can be any format&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# you want, but I&amp;#39;ll use the example one from the start of the post.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;tweet&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;My training last week: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{:d}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; workouts for &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{:.2f}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; miles and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;{:d}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt; calories burned.&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;format&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;l&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mileage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;calories&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;update_status&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;tweet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's it! You have everything you need; now, just set the bot to run &lt;em&gt;ad nauseum&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;python artbot.py&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should run forever, sleeping for most of it but waking every week to post your summary. If you notice something isn't working right, check the logs; they should specify if there are problems e.g. with permissions posting to Twitter, or connections hanging and disconnecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all there is to it! There are obviously a lot of technical hurdles I largely glossed over--creating the apps for both Strava and Twitter can be a little more involved than the average person would like, and Python versions (especially 2.x vs 3.x) can wreak havoc on your code. I tried to be as reproducible as I could, though until Jupyter notebooks decide to play nice with Pelican (or maybe the other way around?) these code embeddings will have to suffice. Sigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to leave a comment if you have any questions! I've also posted the bot in the &lt;code&gt;examples&lt;/code&gt; folder in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/magsol/pybot"&gt;pybot GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt; as &lt;code&gt;artbot.py&lt;/code&gt;. Happy tweeting!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="howto"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="strava"></category><category term="running"></category><category term="oauth"></category><category term="tweepy"></category><category term="twitter"></category><category term="pybot"></category></entry><entry><title>Reviewing a reviewed grant's reviews</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2016/02/02/reviewing-a-reviewed-grants-reviews/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-02-02T10:18:34-05:00</published><updated>2016-02-02T10:18:34-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2016-02-02:/blog/2016/02/02/reviewing-a-reviewed-grants-reviews/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rejection in any context sucks. As a new faculty trying to prove himself (to himself, but most importantly, to his tenure committee), I particularly hate rejections in the context of grant proposals and paper submissions. The "nice" thing about the latter rejection is that it's marginally easier to resubmit a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rejection in any context sucks. As a new faculty trying to prove himself (to himself, but most importantly, to his tenure committee), I particularly hate rejections in the context of grant proposals and paper submissions. The "nice" thing about the latter rejection is that it's marginally easier to resubmit a manuscript elsewhere; there are more journals and conferences than ever, especially in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/write_grants.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last September, I submitted a proposal in line with &lt;a href="http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2015/nsf15569/nsf15569.htm"&gt;NSF's 15-569 program solicitation&lt;/a&gt;: the Research Initiation Initiative in Computer and Information Science and Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insert jokes involving "initiation initiative" imagery here (sorry, I don't have an avalanche of Advil).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat unsurprisingly but nonetheless disappointingly, I received notification today that the proposal was rejected. I say unsurprising because the proposal itself was incredibly rushed; we hit "submit" about two minutes before deadline. It was my first major grant proposal, so there were bound to be some mishaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So: let's get into the reviewer feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reviewer 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the longest review (aside from the Panel Summary). The reviewer listed the Strengths and Weaknesses of the proposal (which I appreciate). For instance, one of the given strengths:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposed work seeks to address these limitations: the innovation of this work is the combination of traditional and nontraditional data sets in a tool for disease forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And weaknesses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The research plan is lacking detail, which significantly call into question the intellectual merit of the proposal. For example, very little detail is given regarding how the models in Task 1 and 2 will be tested. Eg, how will the team determine that the models are operating at a sufficient level of accuracy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This point is particularly brutal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's unclear how the proposed work will help him differentiate his work from work done previously with graduate advisors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, more than anything else, is dangerous territory. The first weakness can be described as a consequence of rushed writing. The second is systemic and not trivial to assuage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, this reviewer gave the proposal a rating of "Fair."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reviewer 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback here wasn't quite as structured as Reviewer 1, but still provided a reasonable level of detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strengths are the concept of developing a [...] based on [...], and [...], both in terms of [...] and [...]. Another strength is the PI's experience with [...], and in using [...].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put another way: the reviewer liked the general idea, and the fact that I've had a little experience with it in the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, several major concerns are: 1) as far as I can see, the PI doesn't have a great deal of experience working with [...].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was an excellent point. I mentioned a particular strategy but formally don't have any training with it. I neglected my own rule of "justify everything" here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) No clear description of the data mining and statistical methods for error evaluation and estimation of signals from the inevitable noise from [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rookie mistake on my part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3) validation of system predictions underdeveloped, when this would be of major importance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also a rookie mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4) finally, the choice of [...] seems idiosyncratic. The budget is for [...]. No involvement of [...], which again casts some uncertainty as to successfully developing and implementing the [...].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ties back with the reviewer's first criticism: since I don't have much experience with this certain strategy, the next best thing would be to provide funding for someone who does, which I did not do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the reviewer's summary included this line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will also be remarkable if all the activities proposed can be achieved within 2 years, especially given that most of the work will presumably be carried out by graduate and undergraduate students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a way, this is something of a relief: my original plan had been to submit a &lt;a href="http://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2015/nsf15555/nsf15555.htm"&gt;CAREER proposal&lt;/a&gt; on this topic; if a reviewer thinks the topic is too large-scale to be done in two years, it may be the right scale for a 5-year CAREER award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the reviewer gave the proposal a rating of "Fair."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reviewer 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third reviewer is something of an outlier, though &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-VRBWLpYCPY"&gt;not in the usual way&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback was extremely succinct, and universally positive (knee-jerk aside: was this a student?). It was also at a very high level; it never addressed the details of the proposal, only the big-picture ideas. Here's the summary:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, the proposed research activities have significant potential to be transformative. The two core objectives and corresponding tasks ([...]) seem ambitious to the reviewer. Integration of research and educational activities are relevant and intersect various disciplines (computer sciences, cellular biology, genetics).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well-written, but nonetheless out of sync with the other two reviewers. Don't get me wrong--I &lt;strong&gt;greatly&lt;/strong&gt; appreciate some positive feedback on my first NSF proposal as PI! This reviewer gave the proposal a "Very Good" rating, which is also a nice shot to the ego. But it's clear there were some glaring weaknesses that, for whatever reason, this reviewer chose not to elucidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Panel Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing surprising here. The strengths from the previous reviewers were identified, along with the numerous accompanying weaknesses. The panel did address the issue of broader impacts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the proposal has merits, the PI may need to clarify clearly as to the major justification for developing the proposed tool in relation to other initiatives in this area, eg [...]. The panel also highlighted several problems and questions with regards to [...]. Until these problems are addressed, it was felt that the broader impact of this project, particularly the probability of [...], is likely to be moderate to low&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, along with a "Low Competitive" panel recommendation, pretty much sums things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the vast majority of weaknesses, their immediate impetus can be summed up thusly: &lt;em&gt;I started writing the grant the day before deadline.&lt;/em&gt; That's a no-no, and contributed directly to the panicked flurry at the end and lack of detail in the proposal itself. Starting earlier will solve these problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last point that genuinely concerns me, though, is the first reviewer's comment on differentiating myself from my graduate advisors. It's true that this proposal took work I started as a graduate student, and I agree that it's important to build an independent research group such that I don't have to rely on my graduate advisors for funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I suppose I could boil this down to time constraints as well: given more elbow room, I could have provided a more detailed development plan that clearly differentiated itself from work done before. Rather than relying on the "we propose to &lt;em&gt;extend&lt;/em&gt;..." mantra, I could have delved into much greater detail on the methods I'd wanted to use and why their application would be novel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you have it: a review of grant reviews. Nothing left to do here but incorporate the feedback and push out more effective proposals in the months to come!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="professional"></category><category term="academia"></category><category term="grants"></category><category term="reviewer feedback"></category><category term="rejection"></category></entry><entry><title>Introductions</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2015/11/07/introductions/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2015-11-07T12:14:02-05:00</published><updated>2015-11-07T12:14:02-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2015-11-07:/blog/2015/11/07/introductions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, this seems to be working. Kinda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took some inspiration from &lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/"&gt;Jake VanderPlas' Pythonic Perambulations&lt;/a&gt; and opted for a similar route: Pelican as the backend blogging machine, github as the host, and (eventually) embedded Jupyter notebooks. Unfortunately, Jake's addition to the Pelican plugins to &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-plugins/blob/master/liquid_tags/notebook.py"&gt;allow Jupyter notebooks&lt;/a&gt; uses CSS …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, this seems to be working. Kinda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took some inspiration from &lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/"&gt;Jake VanderPlas' Pythonic Perambulations&lt;/a&gt; and opted for a similar route: Pelican as the backend blogging machine, github as the host, and (eventually) embedded Jupyter notebooks. Unfortunately, Jake's addition to the Pelican plugins to &lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican-plugins/blob/master/liquid_tags/notebook.py"&gt;allow Jupyter notebooks&lt;/a&gt; uses CSS that is, shall we say, unfriendly to Pelican themes outside of the Octopress default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that part is still incomplete. As are many of the links and some of the plugins. But ultimately, I'm hoping to use this to supplant my current pair of blogs that jointly detail what my plan for this space is: academia, general data science, and other musings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal"></category><category term="pelican"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="github"></category><category term="jupyter"></category></entry></feed>