<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Stochastic Stenography - personal, professional</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://magsol.github.io/feeds/personal-professional.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://magsol.github.io/</id><updated>2022-01-05T21:11:47-05:00</updated><subtitle>Data science, academia, and donuts</subtitle><entry><title>What the f*@$ is this s%#&amp; (2022 ed.)</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2022/01/05/what-the-f-is-this-s/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-01-05T21:11:47-05:00</published><updated>2022-01-05T21:11:47-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2022-01-05:/blog/2022/01/05/what-the-f-is-this-s/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/clover.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Clover disapproves of everything and wants you to get your ass in gear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure where I should even start. How does one sum up a year that felt more like a decade? How does one reflect on a year that eschewed reflection in favor of mere survival?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/clover.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Clover disapproves of everything and wants you to get your ass in gear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not sure where I should even start. How does one sum up a year that felt more like a decade? How does one reflect on a year that eschewed reflection in favor of mere survival?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be the eternal optimist who always sees the silver lining, who always takes away something positive from a negative experience. But to paraphrase (because I can't find it) someone far more clever than I on Twitter: it feels a bit like trying to find the bright side of things while actively being run over by a zamboni.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I suppose one way would be to try and end this post on a positive note. So to that end, I'll start with the stuff that sucked in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Bad&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where do I even start? The pandemic continued to rage--Alpha, Delta, and Omicron right at the cusp of the new year--and elected leaders around the globe shrugged their collective shoulders, as if saying "we tried nothing and it didn't work, so I guess that's it."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;University of Georgia, in lockstep with the Georgia Board of Regents and many other public universities across the country, collectively threw up their hands, hid behind the malevolent cowardice of our elected leaders, and did all of jack and shit to protect any of the hundreds of thousands of dedicated public service workers who have given 140% of themselves to the institution of higher learning since time immemorial. They continued to fart out meaningless platitudes about "rallying together" whenever another surge arrived but refused to take any meaningful or substantive actions recommended by public health experts the world over--like requiring masks or vaccinations--and instead demanded more of already overtaxed, underpaid janitorial staff to do more pointless bullshit like installing platic dividers or cleaning surfaces forty times a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running has continued to be an elusive outlet for stress. Every run feels hard, and more often than not I'm inclined to not run. Which doesn't do anything to help my mood, but that vicious negative feedback loop continues nonetheless. I hate it but I'm not sure how to break out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other shit that sucked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our bun Clover had a bout of GI stasis in the early part of the year. Thankfully, the folks at the UGA Vet Hospital were amazing in getting her well again. Still, scary as shit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the weather (75F on Christmas? fucking really?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teaching (and I hate that I hated it, but I'm so, so burned out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;literally the Georgia Board of Regents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;annual grant reports (best I can describe is we're running in place)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;burnout in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;mental health in general&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;every day being a series of bad choices made from a list of exclusively bad choices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;The Good&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somehow, through the grace of God and possibly every deity in the multiverse, we have not tested positive for COVID (&lt;em&gt;knocks on wood&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="videobox"&gt;
                    &lt;iframe width="640" height="390"
                        src='https://www.youtube.com/embed/2EbeCEs9_Tw'
                        frameborder='0' webkitAllowFullScreen
                        mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;
                    &lt;/iframe&gt;
                &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took my first flight since Dec 2019 to Washington, D.C., for a workshop hosted at George Washington University on teaching with open source technology. It was a &lt;em&gt;blast&lt;/em&gt;. Not only was it an absolute pleasure to spend a few days with some of my professional heroes, folks I've known for years through Twitter and who share my same passion for open source technology and innovative instrucitonal methods, but it was great just going to a meeting again!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/dc-workshop.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traveling was the strangest thing, both familiar and foreign. Of course I was a nervous wreck going through the airport, but I commend everyone at GWU for taking every precaution, including mandating the use of masks indoors. It was also the first time either one of us single-parented for more than a few hours at a time, and Cathryn did amazingly well! She even managed Z's weekly bath ON HER OWN.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/sunrise.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was tenured and promoted. Indeed, I somehow won the cosmic coin flip. I am now an Associate ("ass o' shit", in the technical parlance) Professor of Computer Science and Cellular Biology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/phd-thesis.jpg"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;If my doctoral thesis was an image&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We bought a second car (named "Mipha"), a Honda CRV Hybrid, in the summer. We had assumed we'd need two cars, what with our jobs requiring slightly different hours and wildly different physical locations, it would entail too much logistical square dancing for a single car when daycare pickup / dropoff was added to the mix. Of course, then I taught the fall semester almost entirely remotely because of the Delta surge. Still, it's been really nice to have a bit more room, and our handful of trips to the mountains with Z would absolutely NOT have been possible with Sam (our Honda Accord Hybrid). Not crazy about the added car insurance, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over Christmas, we managed a trip to Arizona (which, in hindset, we may not have done given Omicron) for a family reunion on Cathryn's side to celebrate her grandfather's 101st birthday. It was also the first time Z had ever met the family on Cathryn's side, and the first time she got to meet her great-grandfather, born a &lt;em&gt;century&lt;/em&gt; earlier. We took rapid tests every day, and got PCR tested before and after, and &lt;em&gt;somehow&lt;/em&gt; only 1 person in the entire extended family got COVID. It was also the first time Z traveled by airplane, and she was amazing. It was lovely. Exhausting, but lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/desert.png"&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Rain. All day. In the desert. Yeah, global warming's a myth.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other stuff that was neat and definitely didn't suck:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our house won our HOA's First Place for holiday decorations, specifically in the "whimsical" category! I'm thinking our 7-foot inflatable menorah had something to do with it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Both Cathryn and I hired running coaches to help us get back into the swing of things. Baby steps!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was offered--and accepted--a position with &lt;a href="https://quansight.com"&gt;Quansight as Principal Solution Architect&lt;/a&gt;. I'll have a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; more to say about this in a later post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bathroom renovations are scheduled, and office renovations are being planned. All that's left in the Priority A category is to address the outdoor flooding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We managed a handful of mountain trips with Z, and even one with our friend Laura. Z loooves the outdoors, which is awesome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I got this blog working again!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Age of Calamity&lt;/em&gt;'s two expansion packs are fun as hell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Z is just... the singularity of joy in our lives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Wrap Up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/what-the-f-is-this-s/jump.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's cathartic to get all this out in some form. And, of course, there are innumerable positives (and negatives) that I'm forgetting / suppressing / ignoring. I will say this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm genuinely excited for 2022. There's an insane amount of uncertainty and dread and fear, but there are some changes in store for which I'm really and truly stoked. I just have to hope.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="good"></category><category term="bad"></category><category term="stupid"></category><category term="whatever"></category><category term="clover the bun"></category><category term="z"></category><category term="covid"></category><category term="covid19"></category><category term="board of regents sucks"></category><category term="running"></category><category term="professor"></category><category term="university"></category><category term="quansight"></category><category term="travel"></category><category term="airplane"></category><category term="reunion"></category><category term="holidays"></category><category term="year in review"></category></entry><entry><title>At home during COVID-19</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2020/05/20/at-home-during-covid-19/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-05-20T15:39:12-04:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T14:42:01-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2020-05-20:/blog/2020/05/20/at-home-during-covid-19/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/instachaaz.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Image source: &lt;a href="https://instachaaz.threadless.com/"&gt;instachaaz&lt;/a&gt; (the stuff is awesome)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this has certainly been a &lt;strong&gt;unique&lt;/strong&gt; past couple of months. I had a lot of things in mind for the spring 2020 semester and beyond, but I can safely say it's all been completely upended now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to trivialize COVID-19 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/instachaaz.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Image source: &lt;a href="https://instachaaz.threadless.com/"&gt;instachaaz&lt;/a&gt; (the stuff is awesome)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this has certainly been a &lt;strong&gt;unique&lt;/strong&gt; past couple of months. I had a lot of things in mind for the spring 2020 semester and beyond, but I can safely say it's all been completely upended now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to trivialize COVID-19 to the suburban equivalent of "can't go to the community pool for a few months because of a particularly bad case of the fiery poops;" there are real people whose livelihoods are suffering: financially, professionally, and literally, and I think the world as a whole would be a lot better off if we collectively recognized that and pitched in to help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lady and I have been establishing new habits and routines, while trying to maintain a semblance of normality during the pandemic. There have been a lot of snacks (peanut butter M&amp;amp;Ms, cookie dough ice cream, hint of lime chips, and of course, Lucky Charms cereal), some creativity in workplace setup (moved an extra computer monitor from upstairs, and set up a surge protector behind the dining table--also had to line one end of the table with aluminum foil, because our cat kept jumping up on the table from that side), and digging out some old mainstays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Classics Never Go Out of Style&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early on in the lockdown, The Lady and I kicked off a Zelda-thon, starting with &lt;em&gt;Skyward Sword&lt;/em&gt; on the Nintendo Wii. There's a strange story there: I'd purchased the game for her way back when we lived in separate apartments in Pittsburgh, because she was the Zelda fan between the two of us. Yeah, I'm a gamer, but she's a &lt;em&gt;Zelda&lt;/em&gt; gamer. It was a lot of fun to watch her play the game, and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cbwq8ev-EXA"&gt;I occasionally jumped in when she needed to tap out&lt;/a&gt;. But after reaching the penultimate boss, we just... stopped playing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;eight years&lt;/em&gt;. We knew this, because when we fired up the game again on the weekend of March 14, we saw the last save file pop up for March 28, 2012. Almost eight years &lt;em&gt;to the day&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since The Lady played most of the game eight years ago, I ended up "driving" this time around. She jumped in whenever she wanted, but we ended up tearing through the game in &lt;strong&gt;10 days&lt;/strong&gt;. It was pretty impressive, and it was great to finally see the end of the game that has been referenced SO MUCH in theory videos around &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt; (which we'll get to!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we knocked out &lt;em&gt;Skyward Sword&lt;/em&gt;, The Lady took the driver's seat for &lt;em&gt;Twilight Princess&lt;/em&gt;. I'd never seen the game played start to finish, and had really never seen anything beyond the quests involving collecting light shards (which is, as I discovered, a meager portion of the game's introduction). Suffice to say, this one took a lot longer; most of the month of April, if memory serves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I took a deep breath and fired up &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt;... in &lt;strong&gt;Master Mode&lt;/strong&gt;. Yes, &lt;a href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2019/08/12/breath-of-fresh-air/"&gt;I've posted about this game here before&lt;/a&gt;, and we ended up beating it sometime in November 2019. But the DLC included an evil modification called "Master Mode", which among other terrible things, has the following effects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every enemy in the game is upgraded by one level (red become blue, blue become brown, brown become silver, silver become &lt;a href="https://cdn.gamer-network.net/2017/usgamer/Breath-of-the-Wild-DLC-Guide-header.jpg/EG11/thumbnail/1920x1080/format/jpg/quality/65/18-12-2018-the-legend-of-zelda-breath-of-the-wild-dlc-everything-we-know.jpg"&gt;gold&lt;/a&gt;, a brand-new level)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enemies heal when they've been out of combat for two seconds (not hyperbole; literally two seconds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brand-new &lt;a href="https://imgix.bustle.com/mic/knzgpkctoycksfpvki9e3kuc7fozfcugpfqn63lps6nee90vzthnydlbjtvt26lx.jpg?w=1020&amp;amp;h=576&amp;amp;fit=crop&amp;amp;crop=faces&amp;amp;auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;amp;cs=srgb&amp;amp;q=70"&gt;floating platforms&lt;/a&gt; with enemies, because fuck you that's why&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;brutal&lt;/em&gt;, especially in the first quarter of the game. You end up skipping fights by default, sneaking around a lot more, and fighting as though you cannot take a single hit (because in all likelihood, you can't). I haven't finished it yet, but just this past weekend we completed the last of the DLC "Ballad of the Champions," so really the only thing left of the Main Quests is to destroy Calamity Ganon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once this is done, The Lady plans to break out the game that really and truly started it all: &lt;em&gt;Ocarina of Time&lt;/em&gt;, which I've also never seen played start to finish, so that will be fun to watch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a completely separate video gaming front, I managed to get a Stargate mod working for &lt;em&gt;Sins of a Solar Empire&lt;/em&gt;, and even started playing a small 1v1 as the Ancients against the Wraith. It looks incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/destiny.jpg"&gt;
For fans of &lt;em&gt;Stargate: Universe&lt;/em&gt;, you'll recognize this class of Ancient ship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/gateship.jpg"&gt;
Fans of both &lt;em&gt;SG-1&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; will instantly recognize this "gate ship"!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/superhive.jpg"&gt;
This looks like a scene straight out of the &lt;em&gt;Atlantis&lt;/em&gt; finale!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't wait to explore some of the other races--Asgard, Goa'uld, and Ori round out the playable races, while a recent update includes some "minor factions" that are always AI-controlled but can still change the dynamics of play: Tau'ri (that's us!), Free Jaffa, Vanir (rogue Asgard offshoot seen in &lt;em&gt;Atlantis&lt;/em&gt;), and Michael's Hybrids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Variety is the Pribe of Libe&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While The Lady and I have been re-visiting the classics to keep us grounded, we've also been branching out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, like most, we tried our hand at baking sourdough. And, frankly, it turned out incredible!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/sourdough.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've since baked a new recipe of chocolate chip cookies (which &lt;em&gt;mostly&lt;/em&gt; turned out chewy), and have plans to whip up some butterscotch bars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've also been starting up some regular remote get-togethers, from weekly chats with my family to weekly post-run "coffee chats" with some of our running friends. We'll go out for runs by ourselves, come home, get cleaned up, and FaceTime each other while making coffee and getting ready for the day. We're also about to try out remote gaming tomorrow with some friends of ours from Pittsburgh--they, like us, are big board gaming geeks. I'm not sure exactly what we're going to play or how it'll pan out, but I'm excited to try!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lady and I took a page from a &lt;a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2020/04/the-best-board-games-to-play-with-your-quarantined-housemates/"&gt;recent list of recommended quarantine board games&lt;/a&gt; and purchased &lt;em&gt;Star Realms&lt;/em&gt;. Think: a super-simple mash-up of &lt;em&gt;Magic: The Gathering&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Dominion&lt;/em&gt;. It's a deck-building game with a common "market" of cards you can purchase, and the goal is to use those cards to bludgeon your opponent to death in the most sci-fi manner possible. Meanwhile, I sunk several days in over at &lt;a href="https://www.heroforge.com/"&gt;Hero Forge&lt;/a&gt; designing avatars for her and me. I think they came out pretty well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/heroforge.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of remote activities together, we actually did try our hand at a "remote viewing" of a movie, and it worked remarkably well! Two of our runners friends joined us to watch &lt;em&gt;A League Of Their Own&lt;/em&gt;, both because one of them had never seen it before, and because of &lt;a href="https://bleacherreport.com/articles/2890923-mary-pratt-last-surviving-rockford-peach-dies-at-age-101"&gt;last week's news that the last of the original Rockford Peaches passed away at 101&lt;/a&gt;. We'd originally hoped to use a video synchronization platform like &lt;a href="https://www.netflixparty.com/"&gt;Netflix Party&lt;/a&gt;, but Netflix doesn't have &lt;em&gt;A League Of Their Own&lt;/em&gt;; Amazon Prime does. So we looked into &lt;a href="https://www.kastapp.co/"&gt;Kast&lt;/a&gt;, but after 30 minutes of tinkering, it was clear the app is still too young and rough around the edges; we were constantly having either sound or video issues. So we did it the old-fashioned way: fired up a Zoom chat, and counted down to hitting "Play" out loud. And it actually worked quite well! We were never more than 20 seconds off each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/aloto.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our sudden and constant presence all day every may have caught our pets off guard, but they sure seem to be enjoying it. Zippy is scampering around us, jumping on our laps, and trying to jump on our work table one minute, then is passed out on the couch for hours on end the next. Clover, meanwhile, seems to find a napping spot anywhere she goes, but has started expecting treats at all hours of the day (partly our fault for giving her the occasional piece of banana with breakfast... and piece of fruit or veggie for lunch... and for dinner... ). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/aminals.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest changes on my end (besides the obvious, of course), was buying a new laptop. This has been on my list for several months, as my aging MacBook Pro Mid-2014 has been struggling more and more to keep up with workloads. When the new laptop arrived, it took three entire days to fully transfer and configure it just right; I'm still coming across things here and there that need to be fully fleshed out (e.g., screen saver still isn't the picture collage, and it's not properly password protected, and the desktop backgrounds don't switch out, and other small but noticeable things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the thing I wasn't expecting that hit me really hard when it was time to shut down, wipe, and ship out the old laptop was the melancholy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd purchased this old laptop (aptly-named "Apollo") in September 2014 in the throes of writing my dissertation. I remember it distinctly: sitting in the Squirrel Hill Starbucks, ear pods in, listening to some Pandora station while typing away in the Latex document... when suddenly my ear pods &lt;em&gt;screeeeeched&lt;/em&gt;, my screen froze, and moments later, my ear pods went silent and the screen went dark. I rebooted, and... nothing. According to the Apple Geniuses later that evening, the motherboard has inexplicably fried. It was well out of warranty, so my only option was to purchase a brand-new laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/apollo.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was Apollo. It got me through my PhD dissertation and defense, the move to Athens and the start of my tenure-track position at UGA, and through the first five years of it--well into my promotion and tenure process, my first couple of successful grants, and so, so many papers. It was a veritable workhorse of a laptop that, with a little sprucing up, still has some life in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I have a laptop that is literal orders of magnitude more powerful than the previous one, yet it has huge shoes to fill. We'll see if the new laptop--&lt;a href="https://www.zeldadungeon.net/wiki/images/5/52/Dinraal.jpg"&gt;Dinraal&lt;/a&gt;--is up to the task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wfh/dinraal.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What's next?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not sure, honestly. We're taking it one day at a time. We're being kind to each other and ourselves. We're trying to be safe, not just for us, but for everyone else around us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay safe and happy, my friends.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="covid-19"></category><category term="sars-cov-2"></category><category term="work from home"></category><category term="wfh"></category><category term="zelda"></category><category term="snacks"></category><category term="running"></category><category term="social distancing"></category><category term="projects"></category><category term="pandemic"></category><category term="the lady"></category><category term="furbabies"></category><category term="zippy the cat"></category><category term="clover the bun"></category></entry><entry><title>Resolutions for 2018</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2018/01/21/new-years-resolutions-2018/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-21T14:28:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-21T14:28:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2018-01-21:/blog/2018/01/21/new-years-resolutions-2018/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A solid three weeks late on the new year's resolutions, but still a marked improvement over last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...I didn't post resolutions last year...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been involved with a small faculty writing group since mid-December, with
the expressed goal of helping its participants develop and sustain regular
writing habits. Since …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A solid three weeks late on the new year's resolutions, but still a marked improvement over last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(...I didn't post resolutions last year...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been involved with a small faculty writing group since mid-December, with
the expressed goal of helping its participants develop and sustain regular
writing habits. Since any new resolution's long-term success is pretty much
exclusively contingent on whether or not a habit is formed, I'm also trying
to eliminate some bad habits (since new habits are easier to form if they,
in effect, &lt;a href="https://jamesclear.com/three-steps-habit-change"&gt;take the place of the bad habits&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So without further adieu (and with a bit of inspiration from
&lt;a href="https://punkrockor.com/2018/01/02/punk-rock-ors-new-years-resolutions/"&gt;Dr. Albert&lt;/a&gt;),
here are my 2018 resolutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write and/or edit every single day (operationally I'm aiming for at least
30 minutes/day, 5 days/week, and go from there).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blog more frequently. Despite starting this cool pelican blog back in 2015
for the &lt;em&gt;expressed&lt;/em&gt; purpose of basically doing what
&lt;a href="https://jakevdp.github.io/"&gt;Jake VanderPlas&lt;/a&gt; does on his blog--but with &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt;
research--I have yet to really bring that idea to fruition. That changes this year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make some progress on a few fun side projects!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few side projects that have languished over the last several
months (changing this blog's layout was one). I'd love to actually finish one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/snow_bunny.png" width="600" style="border-radius: 75%" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="new year"></category><category term="blog"></category><category term="writing"></category><category term="side projects"></category><category term="research"></category><category term="habits"></category></entry><entry><title>Summer of Data Science 2017: Wrap-up</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/08/15/sods-2017-wrap-up/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-15T16:38:18-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-15T16:38:18-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2017-08-15:/blog/2017/08/15/sods-2017-wrap-up/</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci/status/895856449687080960"&gt;Tweet of BecomingDataSci/895856449687080960&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Long Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that's stuck with me from my middle school obsession with the &lt;em&gt;Wing Commander&lt;/em&gt; books and video games was this quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;No battle plan survives contact with the enemy.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly as true as ever with the admittedly &lt;em&gt;extremely ambitious …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci/status/895856449687080960"&gt;Tweet of BecomingDataSci/895856449687080960&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Long Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that's stuck with me from my middle school obsession with the &lt;em&gt;Wing Commander&lt;/em&gt; books and video games was this quote:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;No battle plan survives contact with the enemy.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly as true as ever with the admittedly &lt;em&gt;extremely ambitious&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/05/31/summer-of-data-science-2017/"&gt;SoDS 2017 goals I laid out in my previous post&lt;/a&gt;. Still, they're worthwhile to go through and reflect over in preparation for the inevitable SoDS 2018.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Teaching: 1360E improvements and 4360/6360 preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one I've done well with, and am continuing to work on (though &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SpectralFilter/status/896119490324201472"&gt;today's nuking of the AutoLab grading VM&lt;/a&gt; will set me back a bit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This summer was the second rendition of &lt;a href="https://eds-uga.github.io/csci1360e-su17/"&gt;CSCI 1360E, also taught as an online course&lt;/a&gt; just like last summer's (there is scheduled to be one more, next summer 2018. after that, who knows?). It started with over 20 students and ended with around 12--a pretty tough attrition rate--but still a vast improvement over last summer's 6/3. Ran into fewer autograder problems, the questions were more relevant and targeted to the lecture material, and the lectures themselves were smoother overall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm now deep in the process of building the fifth and final course I proposed back in Fall 2015 to fruition: &lt;a href="https://eds-uga.github.io/csci4360-fa17/"&gt;CSCI 4360/6360 Data Science II&lt;/a&gt;. I've planned out the lecture schedule for the semester, linked them up with the primary sources I'll be referencing, and even managed to snag all the necessary guest lecturers for the various trips I have to make. Of course, I'm lagging on the concrete lecture material, and as stated I nuked the VM that would host and autograde homework assignments, so this is still a mixed bag...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To update the enrollment numbers: currently 36 students registered (30 graduates, 6 undergraduates). I expect this to wobble considerably over the next week as classes officially begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(yes, you read that right: I proposed five brand-new courses my first fall semester; I've since taught three of them. a fourth was taught by another professor, since we couldn't figure out a way to clone me a &lt;em&gt;seventeenth&lt;/em&gt; time)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;: I'd give myself a B/B+, A- if you bring in the fact that, by the end of the summer, I was fully integrated with &lt;a href="https://airflow.incubator.apache.org/"&gt;Airflow&lt;/a&gt; for auto-posting lectures in 1360E.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Research: NSF CAREER proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was quite the process: an internal peer review with other colleagues at UGA, edits from my wife, and a night-before top-down rewrite reminiscent of when I scrapped my Ph.D. dissertation slides at 10pm the night before my defense. But I submitted something I was proud of, even if it doesn't stand a snowball's chance in hell of being funded. I stated before that I submitted for the feedback; even though I'd really, really love to have the grant funded, any feedback from the agency itself will be valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, that was my one grant-writing goal. I've managed to pick up a few others this summer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://aigrant.org/"&gt;AIGrant&lt;/a&gt;: Submitted this a few weeks ago. Really excited to work on the project I proposed; I hope the folks there are as excited as I am about it!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2017/nsf17552/nsf17552.htm"&gt;NSF CRII&lt;/a&gt;: This is sort of a "CAREER Lite", since it's only 2 years and a &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; upper limit on the amount of funding you can request. But it's likewise geared toward young investigators like myself; however, I've applied the last two years and been rejected both times, and this is my last year of eligibility, so we'll see. I submitted this just this past week on Wednesday; fingers crossed!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://ropensci.org/fellowships/"&gt;rOpenSci Fellowships&lt;/a&gt;: I have a completed draft that I've edited a few times with some feedback from the program officers. I'm still not ready to submit, but I think I have a compelling application for the Sept 1 deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/rfa-files/RFA-RM-17-006.html"&gt;NIH New Innovator&lt;/a&gt;: This one is a bit of a reach, considering it's a 10-page application due Sept 8, and it's pretty much the only one on this list I haven't had a chance to start on. Plus, I've received conflicting information from the informational webinar I attended and someone who applied last year and was rejected, so I'm wondering if I should let this one slide this year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://sloan.org/fellowships/"&gt;Sloan Research Fellowships&lt;/a&gt;: Running my one-page application through the meatgrinder to get the best submission possible for the Sept 15 deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.simonsfoundation.org/mathematics-and-physical-science/simons-investigators/#mmls-investigators"&gt;Simons Investigators&lt;/a&gt;: the internal deadline for this is Sept 15, but assuming I get the nod (evidently no one else at UGA usually applies for this one?!), I'll be getting some feedback from previous Simons Investigators for some help in addressing what the foundation is really looking for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there's a grant I'm working on with Continuum Analytics' Matt Rocklin (yes, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mrocklin"&gt;that Matt Rocklin!&lt;/a&gt;), a smaller NIH grant on biosurveillance with the awesome folks at UGA Public Health, a potential biology grant to NSF with my Cellular Biology colleagues, and a mentored NIH K-award in neuroscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all &lt;em&gt;this year&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, this is somewhat atypical. If I really do end up submitting to all these, I will have substantially increased my grantwriting output, exceeding that of my first two years &lt;em&gt;combined&lt;/em&gt;. I'm really, really hoping I land on something!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;: A (upgrade to A+ if any actually get &lt;em&gt;funded&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal: Coursera's optimization course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;literally did not happen.&lt;/em&gt; I think I completed the first week of lectures and the practice assignment. Nothing after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Definitely want to take another crack at this next summer, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall&lt;/strong&gt;: F.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As stated at the beginning, a mixed bag. I've had some really great momentum with grantwriting this year, far better than any year so far. Teaching has been pretty productive as well (if not exhausting with all the brand-new courses), though the Coursera goal was a bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, that may have something to do with a completely inadvertent achievement: my running this year has come roaring back. My last five weeks have been particularly awesome:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sods2017wrapup/strava.png" width="960"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two years after my wife and I moved to Athens (2015 and 2016) were both injury-plagued and just plain stressful. Consequently, my running took a hit: I haven't set a PR in any distance since 2014, I haven't run a full marathon since &lt;a href="https://wherearethepancakes.wordpress.com/2015/06/19/race-report-the-hilliest-marathon-evar/"&gt;early 2015&lt;/a&gt;, and in general my mileage has taken a dive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sods2017wrapup/yearly.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But check out this year's trajectory! Nearly 800 miles, and we're only a week into August. That puts me on pace for right around 1,300 miles--a nice comfy middle ground between the monster year that was 2014 and each of the subsequent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also started noticing that I'm actually getting faster, which is something I likewise haven't experienced with my running for a couple years. Where I've typically felt as though I'm just on "cruise control", this increased mileage has also seen my finishing times go down without any conscious decision on my part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which led me--perhaps in a half-crazed moment of weakness--to put the following goals on the Athens Fleet Feet board several weeks ago at their four-year anniversary celebration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/sods2017wrapup/goals.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running is my release. Without it, nothing else I do is going to be very good. When running is going well, other things are going well, and vice versa. So here's hoping I've set myself on a good track!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="data science"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="computer vision"></category><category term="imaging"></category><category term="machine learning"></category><category term="deep learning"></category><category term="nvidia"></category><category term="gpu"></category><category term="online courses"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="cat detector"></category><category term="generative adversarial networks"></category><category term="latent subspace"></category><category term="manifolds"></category><category term="bioimaging"></category><category term="grant writing"></category><category term="running"></category></entry><entry><title>Summer of Data Science 2017</title><link href="https://magsol.github.io/blog/2017/05/31/summer-of-data-science-2017/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-05-31T23:03:42-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-31T23:03:42-04:00</updated><author><name>Shannon Quinn</name></author><id>tag:magsol.github.io,2017-05-31:/blog/2017/05/31/summer-of-data-science-2017/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/images/carpelibrum.png"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, while I was still in Portland, OR enjoying the last few days of &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/"&gt;PyCon 2017&lt;/a&gt;, Renee (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci"&gt;@BecomingDataSci&lt;/a&gt;) mentioned on Twitter that she might bring back the "Summer of Data Science" she kicked off last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: use the summer as an opportunity to learn and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src="/images/carpelibrum.png"&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, while I was still in Portland, OR enjoying the last few days of &lt;a href="https://us.pycon.org/2017/"&gt;PyCon 2017&lt;/a&gt;, Renee (&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/BecomingDataSci"&gt;@BecomingDataSci&lt;/a&gt;) mentioned on Twitter that she might bring back the "Summer of Data Science" she kicked off last year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short: use the summer as an opportunity to learn and/or accomplish something data science-related in a goal-oriented, data-driven way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;@BecomingDataSci/status/869608575978676226&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a tenure-track professor still yet to endure the 3rd-year review, pretty much everything data science related revolves around furthering my eventual tenure dossier. But the summers are still considerably more flexible for me to accomplish some of these goals than the fall or spring (I love teaching, but it's all-consuming). I also have more than just myself--networks of collaborators and research assistants who can help me with these goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So without further adieu, I'd like to put forth my own Summer of Data Science, 2017 Edition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Teaching: 1360E improvements and 4360/6360 preparation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm teaching an online course this summer, starting June 5 and continuing through the end of July: &lt;a href="https://eds-uga.github.io/csci1360e-su17/"&gt;CSCI 1360E Foundations of Informatics and Analytics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or, more colloquially, I just call it "introduction to data science."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's one of the five courses I proposed in my first year (a story for another time, believe me...) and taught for the first time last summer, and in-person last fall. I'm teaching it again this summer and hoping to make some of the standard improvements, such as sprucing up slides and fixing autograder bugs from previous incarnations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More pressing is CSCI 4360/6360 Data Science II, which has yet to have its own website. This course has &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been taught, but is slated for Fall 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did I mention there are already over 40 students registered, undergraduate and graduate combined?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is supposed to be the "corner cases" of data science: lesser-used and/or more powerful analysis methods that aren't necessarily the first tools or techniques you reach for in a given situation. This will include, but certainly not be limited to, concepts like randomized algorithms, semi-supervised learning, and backpropagation; techniques like out-of-core processing, distributed computing, and functional programming; tools like &lt;a href="https://julialang.org/"&gt;Julia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://numba.pydata.org/"&gt;numba&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://dask.pydata.org/en/latest/"&gt;dask&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you ask: No. I'm &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; covering Spark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, the conceptual framework is in place, but practically none of the architectural logistics have been established. So this will take up virtually all of my time for the remainder of the summer, once the following item is completed...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Research: NSF CAREER proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantage of this goal is it has a hard end date: &lt;strong&gt;July 19&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage is that the &lt;a href="https://www.nsf.gov/pubs/2017/nsf17537/nsf17537.htm"&gt;NSF CAREER&lt;/a&gt; is the pinnacle of NSF early-career investigator awards. Its importance cannot be overstated; its &lt;em&gt;je ne sais quoi&lt;/em&gt; is on display in the faces of new investigators when you mention it around them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've connected with my university's grant proposal officers, and am participating in a peer review process that involves two rounds of review: first with fellow CAREER submitees (as in, we exchange each other's current drafts!), and second with the university grant officers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An investigator can only make three submission attempts for the CAREER. The CAREER is only open for submissions once per year. If chosen, the investigator must still be un-tenured at time of award. These conditions place brutal limits on how long you can wait to start making submissions, and I already skipped submitting my first two years. Still, I have no illusions about the uphill battle I have, so my goal this first time around is simply to &lt;strong&gt;acquire feedback&lt;/strong&gt;: from my peers, from my grants officers, and from the NSF reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Personal: Coursera's optimization course&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I signed up to take Coursera's &lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/discrete-optimization/home/welcome"&gt;Discrete Optimization course&lt;/a&gt; out of the University of Melbourne, taught by none other than &lt;a href="https://pascalvanhentenryck.engin.umich.edu/"&gt;Professor Pascal Van Hentenryck&lt;/a&gt; at Michigan and &lt;a href="http://www.coffr.in/"&gt;Dr. Carleton Coffrin&lt;/a&gt;, currently at Los Alamos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Optimization is pretty much the backbone of modern machine learning, and yet I have almost no formal training in it--beyond incidentally covering it in various machine learning and statistics courses as part of some broader topic in which it's used. Oddly, the most rigorous instruction I received as a graduate student in optimization was a &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/site/cellandsystemsmodeling/"&gt;Cell &amp;amp; Systems Modeling course&lt;/a&gt; where we used various optimization techniques to find parameter values for population models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially in conjunction with what I hope to teach in CSCI 4360 in the fall, this would be invaluable both professionally as well as personally.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</content><category term="personal, professional"></category><category term="data science"></category><category term="python"></category><category term="computer vision"></category><category term="imaging"></category><category term="machine learning"></category><category term="deep learning"></category><category term="nvidia"></category><category term="gpu"></category><category term="online courses"></category><category term="teaching"></category><category term="education"></category><category term="cat detector"></category><category term="generative adversarial networks"></category><category term="latent subspace"></category><category term="manifolds"></category><category term="bioimaging"></category></entry></feed>